<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <?xml-model href="../../Schemas/eltec-1.rng" type="application/xml" 
            schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
    <?xml-model href="../../Schemas/eltec-1.rng" type="application/xml" 
            schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:t="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ENG18411"
 xml:lang="en">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>The Twins: A Domestic Novel : ELTeC edition</title>
    <author ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/44385259/">Tupper, Martin Farquhar (1810-1889).</author>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>ELTeC conversion</resp>
     <name>Lou Burnard</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="words">34573</measure>
    <measure unit="pages">87</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <publisher ref="https://distant-reading.net">COST Action "Distant Reading for European Literary
     History" (CA16204)</publisher>
    <distributor ref="https://zenodo.org/communities/eltec/">Zenodo.org</distributor>
    <date when="2021-04-09"/>
    <availability>
     <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/>
    </availability>
    <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3462435">ELTeC</ref>
    <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4662444">ELTeC release 1.1.0</ref>
    <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3533868">ELTeC-eng</ref>
    <ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4662490">ELTeC-eng release 1.0.1</ref>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl type="digitalSource"><title>The Project Gutenberg eBook of The Twins, by Martin Farquhar
     Tupper, A.M., F.R.S..</title><ref
     target="http://www.gutenberg.org/files/16574/16574-h/16574-h.htm">Gutenberg</ref> <respStmt>
     <resp>Produced by </resp>
     <name>Jonathan Ingram, Janet Blenkinship and the Online Distributed Proofreading Team </name>
     </respStmt></bibl>
    <bibl type="firstEdition" n="B7392"><title>The Twins: A Domestic Novel</title><author> Martin
     Farquhar Tupper. </author><publisher>London: Bentley</publisher> <date>1844</date> <ref
     target="http://dbooks.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/books/PDFs/590995737.pdf"/></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc n="eltec-1">
   <p/>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
   </langUsage>
   <textDesc>
    <authorGender xmlns="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns" key="M"/>
    <size xmlns="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns" key="short"/>
    <reprintCount xmlns="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns" key="low"/>
    <timeSlot xmlns="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns" key="T1"/>
   </textDesc>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2021-04-09">Converted by checkUp script for new release</change>
   <change when="2020-11-14">Converted by checkUp script for new release</change>
   <change when="2019-11-09">Checked by releaseChecker script</change>
   <change when="2019-05-20">LB convert to ELTeC-1</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="T1MSL">
  <front>
   <div type="titlepage">
    <pb n="12"/>
    <p>THE TWINS;</p>
    <p/>
    <p>A DOMESTIC NOVEL.</p>
    <p>BY</p>
    <p>MARTIN FARQUHAR TUPPER, A.M., F.R.S.</p>
    <p>AUTHOR OF</p>
    <p>PROVERBIAL PHILOSOPHY.</p>
    <p>HARTFORD:</p>
    <p>PUBLISHED BY SILAS ANDRUS &amp; SON</p>
    <p>1851.</p>
   </div>
   <pb n="13"/>
  </front>
  <body>
   <pb n="14"/>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
    <head>PLACE: TIME: CIRCUMSTANCE.</head>
    <p>Burleigh-Singleton is a pleasant little watering-place on the southern coast of England,
     entirely suitable for those who have small incomes and good consciences. The latter, to
     residents especially, are at least as indispensable as the former: seeing that, however just
     the reputation of their growing little town for superior cheapness in matters of meat and
     drink, its character in things regarding men and manners is quite as undeniable for pre-eminent
     dulness.</p>
    <p>Not but that it has its varieties of scene, and more or less of circumstances too: there are,
     on one flank, the breezy Heights, with flag-staff and panorama; on the other, broad and level
     water-meadows, skirted by the dark-flowing Mullet, running to the sea between its tortuous
     banks: for neighbourhood, Pacton Park is one great attraction—the pretty market-town of
     Eyemouth another—the everlasting, never-tiring sea a third; and, at high-summer, when the
     Devonshire lanes are not knee-deep in mire, the nevertheless immeasurably filthy, though
     picturesque, mud-built village of Oxton.</p>
    <p>Then again (and really as I enumerate these multitudinous advantages, I begin to relent for
     having called it dull), you may pick up curious agate pebbles on the beach, as well as
     corallines and scarce sea-weeds, good for gumming on front-parlour windows; you may fish
     <hi>for</hi> whitings in the bay, and occasionally catch them; you may wade in huge caoutchouc
     boots among the muddy shallows of the Mullet, and shoot <hi>at</hi> cormorants and curlews; you
     may walk to satiety between high-banked and rather dirty cross-roads; and, if you will scramble
     up the hedge-row, may get now and then peeps of undulated country landscape.</p>
    <p>Moreover, you have free liberty to drop in any where to "tiffin"—Burleigh being very
     Indianized, and a guest always welcome; indeed,
     <pb n="15"/>so Indianized is it, so populous in jaundiced cheek and ailing livers, that you may
     openly assert, without fear of being misunderstood (if you wish to vary your common phrase of
     loyalty), that Victoria sits upon the "musnud" of Great Britain; you may order curry in the
     smallest pot-house, and still be sure to get the rice well-cooked; you may call your house-maid
     "ayah," without risk of warning for impertinence; you may vent your wrath against indolent
     waiters in eloquence of "jaa, soostee;" and, finally, you may go to the library, and besides
     the advantage of the day-before-yesterday's Times, you may behold in bilious presence an
     affable, but authoritative, old gentleman, who introduces himself, "Sir, you see in me the hero
     of Puttymuddyfudgepoor."</p>
    <p>You may even now see such an one, I say, and hear him too, if you will but go to Burleigh;
     seeing he has by this time over-lived the year or so whereof our tale discourses. He has, by
     dint of service, attained to the dignity of General H.E.I.C.S., and—which he was still longer
     coming to—the wisdom of being a communicative creature; though possibly, by a natural rëaction,
     at present he carries anti-secresy a little too far, and verges on the gossiping extreme. But,
     at the time to which we must look back to commence this right-instructive story, General Tracy
     was still drinking "Hodgson's Pale" in India, was so taciturn as to be considered almost dumb,
     and had not yet lifted up his yellow visage upon Albion's white cliffs, nor taken up
     head-quarters in his final rest of Burleigh-Singleton.</p>
    <p>Nevertheless, with reference to quartering at Burleigh, a certain long-neglected wife of his,
     Mrs. Tracy, had; and that for the period of at least the twenty-one years preceding: how and
     wherefore I proceed to tell.</p>
    <p>A common case and common fate was that of Mrs. Tracy. She had married, both early and
     hastily, a gallant lieutenant, John George Julian Tracy, to wit, the military germ of our
     future general; their courtship and acquaintance previous to matrimony extended over the not
     inconsiderable space of three whole weeks—commencing with a country ball; and after marriage,
     honey-moon inclusive, they lived the life of cooing doves for three whole months.</p>
    <p>And now came the furlough's end: Mr. Tracy, in his then habitual reserve (a quiet man was
     he), had concealed its existence altogether: and, for aught Jane knew, the hearty invalid was
     to remain at home for ever: but months soon slip away; and so it came to pass, that on a
     certain next Wednesday he must be on his way back to the Presidency of Madras, and—if she will
     not follow him—he must leave her.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="16"/>However, there was a certain old relative, one Mrs. Green, a childless widow—rich,
     capricious, and infirm—whom Jane Tracy did not wish to lose sight of: her money was well worth
     both watching and waiting for; and the captain, whom a lucky chance had now lifted out of the
     lieutenancy, was easily persuaded to forego the pleasure of his wife's company till the
     somewhat indefinite period of her old aunt's death.</p>
    <p>How far sundry discoveries made in the unknown regions of each other's temper reconciled him
     to this retrograding bachelorship, and her to her widowhood-bewitched, I will not undertake to
     say: but I will hazard the remark, anti-poor-law though it seemeth, that the separation of man
     and wife, however convenient, lucrative, or even mutually pleasant, is a dereliction of duty,
     which always deserves, and generally meets, its proper and discriminative punishment. Had the
     young wife faithfully performed her Maker's bidding, and left all other ties unstrung to cleave
     unto her lord; had she considered a husband's true affections before all other wealth, and
     resolved to share his dangers, to solace his cares, to be his blessing through life, and his
     partner even unto death, rather than selfishly to seek her own comfort, and consult her own
     interest—the tale of crime and sadness, which it is my lot to tell, would never have had truth
     for its foundation.</p>
    <p>Ill-matched for happiness though they were, however well-matched as to mutual merit, the
     common man of pleasure and the frivolous woman of fashion, still the wisest way to fuse their
     minds to union, the likeliest receipt for moral good and social comfort, would have been this
     course of foreign scenes, of new faces, sprinkled with a seasoning of adventure, hardship,
     danger, in a distant land. Gradually would they have learned to bear and forbear; the petty
     quarrel would have been forgotten in the frequent kindness; the rougher edges of temper and
     opinion would insensibly have smoothed away; new circumstances would have brought out better
     feelings under happier skies; old acquaintances, false friends forgotten, would have
     neutralized old feuds: and, by long-living together, though it were perhaps amid various
     worries and many cares, they might still have come to a good old age with more than average
     happiness, and more than the common run of love. Patience in dutiful enduring brings a sure
     reward: and marriage, however irksome a constraint to the foolish and the gay, is still so wise
     an ordinance, that the most ill-assorted couple imaginable will unconsciously grow happy, if
     they only remain true to one another, and will learn the wisdom always to hope and often to
     forgive.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="17"/>The Tracys, however, overlooked all this, and mutual friends (those invariable foes
     to all that is generous and unworldly) smiled upon the prudence of their temporary separation.
     The captain was to come home again on furlough in five years at furthest, even if the aunt held
     out so long; and this availed to keep his wife in the rear-guard; therefore, Mrs. Tracy wiped
     her eyes, bade adieu to her retreating lord in Plymouth Sound, and determined to abide, with
     other expectant dames and Asiatic invalided heroes, at Burleigh-Singleton, until she might go
     to him, or he return to her: for pleasant little Burleigh, besides its contiguity to arriving
     Indiamen, was advantageous as being the dwelling-place of aforesaid Mrs. Green;—that wealthy,
     widowed aunt, devoutly wished in heaven: and the considerate old soul had offered her designing
     niece a home with her till Tracy could come back.</p>
    <p>During the first year of absence, ship-letters and India-letters arrived duteously in
     consecutive succession: but somehow or other, the regular post, in no long time afterwards,
     became unfaithful to its trust; and if Mrs. Jane heard quarterly, which at any rate she did
     through the agent, when he remitted her allowance, she consoled herself as to the captain's
     well-being: in due course of things, even this became irregular; he was far up the country,
     hunting, fighting, surveying, and what not; and no wonder that letters, if written at all,
     which I rather doubt, got lost. Then there came a long period of positive and protracted
     silence—months of it—years of it; barring that her checks for cash were honoured still at
     Hancock's, though they could tell her nothing of her lord; so that Mrs. Tracy was at length
     seriously recommended by her friends to become a widow; she tried on the cap, and looked into
     many mirrors; but, after long inspection, decided upon still remaining a wife, because the
     weeds were so clearly unbecoming. Habit, meanwhile, and that still-existing old aunt, who
     seemed resolved to live to a hundred, kept her as before at Burleigh: and, seeing that a few
     months after the captain's departure she had presented the world, not to say her truant lord,
     with twins, she had always found something to do in the way of, what she considered, education,
     and other juvenile amusement: that is to say, when the gayeties of a circle of fifteen miles in
     radius left her any time to spare in such a process. The twins—a brace of boys—were born and
     bred at Burleigh, and had attained severally to twenty years of age, just before their father
     came home again as brevet-major-general. But both they, and that arrival, deserve special
     detail, each in its own chapter.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <pb n="18"/>
    <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
    <head>THE HEROES.</head>
    <p>Mrs. Tracy's sons were as unlike each other as it is well possible for two human beings to
     be, both in person and character. Julian, whose forward and bold spirit gained him from the
     very cradle every prerogative of eldership (and he did struggle first into life, too, so he was
     the first-born), had grown to be a swarthy, strong, big-boned man, of the Roman-nosed, or, more
     physiognomically, the Jewish cast of countenance; with melo-dramatic elf-locks, large whiskers,
     and ungovernable passions; loud, fierce, impetuous; cunning, too, for all his overbearing
     clamour; and an embodied personification of those choice essentials to criminal happiness—a
     hard heart and a good digestion. Charles, on the contrary (or, as logicians would say, on the
     contradictory), was fair-haired, blue-eyed, of Grecian features; slim, though well enough for
     inches, and had hitherto (as the commonalty have it) "enjoyed" weak health: he was gentle and
     affectionate in heart, pure and religious in mind, studious and unobtrusive in habits. It was a
     wonder to see the strange diversity between those own twin-brothers, born within the same hour,
     and, it is superfluous to add, of the same parents; brought up in all outward things alike, and
     who had shared equally in all that might be called advantage or disadvantage, of circumstance
     or education.</p>
    <p>Certain is it that minds are different at birth, and require as different a treatment as
     Iceland moss from cactuses, or bull-dogs from bull-finches: certain is it, too, that Julian,
     early submitted and resolutely broken in, would have made as great a man, as Charles, naturally
     meek, did make a good one; but for the matter of educating her boys, poor Mrs. Tracy had no
     more notion of the feat, than of squaring the circle, or determining the longitude. She kept
     them both at home, till the peevish aunt could suffer Julian's noise no longer: the house was a
     Pandemonium, and the giant grown too big for that castle of Otranto; so he must go at any rate;
     and (as no difference in the treatment of different characters ever occurred to any body) of
     course Charles must go along with him. Away they went to an expensive school, which Julian's
     insubordination on the instant could not brook—and, accordingly, he ran away; without doubt,
     Charles must be taken away too. Another school was tried, Julian
     <pb n="19"/>got expelled this time; and Charles, in spite of prizes, must, on system, be
     removed with him: so forth, with like wisdom, all through the years of adolescence and
     instruction, those ill-matched brothers were driven as a pair. Then again, for fashion's sake,
     and Aunt Green's whims, the circumspective mother, notwithstanding all her inconsistencies,
     gave each of them prettily bound hand-books of devotion; which the one used upon his knees, and
     the other lit cigars withal; both extremes having exceeded her intention: and she proved
     similarly overreached when she persisted in treating both exactly alike, as to liberal
     allowances, and liberty of will; the result being, that one of her sons "foolishly" spent his
     money in a multitude of charitable hobbies; and that the other was constantly supplied with
     means for (the mother was sorry to say it, vulgar) dissipation. By consequence, Charles did
     more good, and Julian more evil, than I have time to stop and tell off.</p>
    <p>If any thing in this life must be personal, peculiar, and specific, it is education: we take
     upon ourselves to speak thus dogmatically, not of mere school-teaching only, <hi>musa</hi>,
     <hi>musæ</hi>, and so forth; nor yet of lectures, on relative qualities of carbon and nitrogen
     in vegetables; no, nor even of schemes of theology, or codes of morals; but we do speak of the
     daily and hourly reining-in, or letting-out, of discouragement in one appetite, and
     encouragement in another; of habitual formation of characters in their diversity; and of
     shaping their bear's-cub, or that child-angel, the natural human mind, to its destined ends;
     that it may turn out, for good, according to its several natures, to be either the
     strong-armed, bold-eyed, rough-hewer of God's grand designs, or the delicate-fingered polisher
     of His rarest sculptures. Julian, well-trained, might have grown to be a Luther; and many a
     gentle soul like Charles, has turned out a coxcomb and a sensualist.</p>
    <p>The boys were born, as I have said, in the regulation order of things, a few months after
     Captain Tracy sailed away for India some full score of years, and more, from this present hour,
     when we have seen him seated as a general in the library at Burleigh; and, until the last year,
     they had never seen their father—scarcely ever heard of him.</p>
    <p>The incidents of their lives had been few and common-place: it would be easy, but wearisome,
     to specify the orchards and the bee-hives which Julian had robbed as a school-boy; the
     rebellions he had headed; the monkey tricks he had played upon old fish-women; and the cruel
     havoc he made of cats, rats, and other poor tormented creatures, who had ministered to his
     wanton and brutalizing joys. In like
     <pb n="20"/>manner, wearily, but easily, might I relate how Charles grew up the nurse's
     darling, though little of his flaunting mother's; the curly-pated young book-worm; the
     sympathizing, innoffensive, gentle heart, whose effort still it was to countervail his
     brother's evil: how often, at the risk of blows, had he interposed to save some drowning puppy:
     how often paid the bribe for Julian's impunity, when mulcted for some damage done in the way of
     broken windows, upset apple-stalls, and the like: how often had he screened his bad
     twin-brother from the flagellatory consequences of sheer idleness, by doing for him all his
     school-tasks: how often striven to guide his insensate conscience to truth, and good, and
     wisdom: how often, and how vainly!</p>
    <p>And when the youths grew up, and their good and evil grew up with them, it were possible to
     tell you a heart-rending tale of Julian's treachery to more than one poor village beauty; and
     many a pleasing trait of Charles's pure benevolence, and wise zeal to remedy his brother's
     mischiefs. The one went about doing ill, and the other doing good: Julian, on account of
     obligations, more truly than in spite of them, hated Charles; and yet one great aim of all
     Charles's amiabilities tended continually to Julian's good, and he strove to please him, too,
     while he wished to bless him. The one had grown to manhood, full of unrepented sins, and ripe
     for darker crime: the other had attained a like age of what is somewhat satirically called
     discretion, having amassed, with Solon of old, "knowledge day by day," having lived a life of
     piety and purity, and blest with a cheerful disposition, that teemed with happy thoughts.</p>
    <p>They had, of course, in the progress of human life, been both laid upon the bed of sickness,
     where, with similar contrast, the one lay muttering discontent, and the other smiling
     patiently: they had both been in dangers by land and by sea, where Julian, though not a little
     lacking to himself at the moment of peril, was still loudly minacious till it came too near;
     while Charles, with all his caution, was more actually courageous, and in spite of all his
     gentleness, stood against the worst undaunted: they had both, with opposite motives and
     dissimilar modes of life, passed through various vicissitudes of feeling, scene, society; and
     the influence of circumstance on their different characters, heightened or diminished, bettered
     or depraved, by the good or evil principle in each, had produced their different and probable
     results.</p>
    <p>Thus, strangely dissimilar, the twin-brothers together stand before us: Julian the strong
     impersonation of the animal man, as Charles of the intellectual; Julian, matter; Charles,
     spirit; Julian, the creature of this
     <pb n="21"/>world, tending to a lower and a worse: Charles, though in the world, not of the
     world, and reaching to a higher and a better.</p>
    <p>Mrs. Tracy, the mother of this various progeny, had been somewhat of a beauty in her day,
     albeit much too large and masculine for the taste of ordinary mortals; and though now very
     considerably past forty, the vain vast female was still ambitious of compliment, and greedy of
     admiration. That Julian should be such a woman's favourite will surprise none: she had, she
     could have, no sympathies with mild and thoughtful Charles; but rather dreaded to set her
     flaunting folly in the light of his wise glance, and sought to hide her humbled vanity from his
     pure and keen perceptions. His very presence was a tacit rebuke to her social dissipation, and
     she could not endure the mild radiance of his virtues. He never fawned and flattered her, as
     Julian would; but had even suffered filial presumption (it could not be affection—O dear, no!)
     to go so far as gently to expostulate at what he fancied wrong; he never gave her reason to
     contrast, with happy self-complacence, her own soul's state with Charles's, however she could
     with Julian's: and then, too, she would indulgently allow her foolish mind—a woman's, though a
     parent's—to admire that tall, black, bandit-looking son, above the slight build, the delicate
     features, and almost feminine elegance of his brother: she found Julian always ready to
     countenance and pamper her gayest wishes, and was glad to make him her escort every where—at
     balls, and fêtes, and races, and archery parties; while as to Charles, he would be the
     stay-at-home, the milk-sop, the learned pundit, the pious prayer-monger, any thing but the
     ladies' man. Yes: it is little wonder that Mrs. Tracy's heart clave to Julian, the masculine
     image of herself; while it barely tolerated Charles, who was a rarefied and idealized likeness
     of the absent and forgotten Tracy.</p>
    <p>But the mother—and there are many silly mothers, almost as many as silly men and silly
     maids—in her admiration of the outward form of manliness, overlooked the true strength, and
     chivalry, and nobleness of mind which shone supreme in Charles. How would Julian have acted in
     such a case as this?—a sheep had wandered down the cliff's face to a narrow ledge of rock,
     whence it could not come back again, for there was no room to turn: Julian would have pelted
     it, and set his bull-dog at it, and rejoiced to have seen the poor animal's frantic leaps from
     shingly shelf to shelf, till it would be dashed to pieces. But how did Charles act? With the
     utmost courage, and caution, and presence of mind, he crept down, and, at the risk of his life,
     dragged the bleating,
     <pb n="22"/>unreluctant creature up again; it really seemed as if the ungrateful poor dumb
     brute recognised its humane friend, and suffered him to rescue it without a struggle or a
     motion that might have endangered both.</p>
    <p>Again: a burly costermonger was belabouring his donkey, and the wretched beast fell beneath
     his cudgel: strange to say, Julian and Charles were walking together that time; and the same
     sight affected each so differently, that the one sided with the cruel man, and the other with
     his suffering victim: Charles, in momentary indignation, rushed up to the fellow, wrested the
     cudgel from his hand, and flung it over the cliff; while Julian was so base, so cowardly, as to
     reward such generous interference, by holding his weaker brother's arms, and inviting the
     wrathful costermonger to expend the remainder of his phrensy on unlucky Charles. Yes, and when
     at home Mrs. Tracy heard all this, she was silly enough, wicked enough, to receive her truly
     noble son with ridicule, and her other one, the child of her disgrace, with approval.</p>
    <p>"It will teach you, Master Charles, not to meddle with common people and their donkeys; and
     you may thank your brother Julian for giving you a lesson how a gentleman should behave."</p>
    <p>Poor Charles! but poorer Julian, and poorest Mrs. Tracy!</p>
    <p>It would be easy, if need were, to enumerate multiplied examples tending towards the same
     end—a large, masculine-featured mother's foolish preference of the loud, bold, worldly animal,
     before the meek, kind, noble, spiritual. And the results of all these many matters were, that
     now, at twenty years of age, Charles found himself, as it were, alone in a strange land, with
     many common friends indeed abroad, but at home no nearer, dearer ties to string his heart's
     dank lyre withal; neither mother nor brother, nor any other kind familiar face, to look upon
     his gentleness in love, or to sympathize with his affections, unapprehended, unappreciated:
     so—while Mrs. Tracy was the showy, gay, and vapid thing she ever had been, and Julian the same
     impetuous mother's son which his very nurse could say she knew him—Charles grew up a shy and
     silent youth, necessarily reserved, for lack of some one to understand him; necessarily
     chilled, for want of somebody to love him.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <pb n="23"/>
    <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
    <head>THE ARRIVAL.</head>
    <p>The young men were thus situated as regards both the world and one another, and Mrs. Tracy
     had almost entirely forgotten the fact, that she possessed a piece of goods so supererogatory
     as her husband (a property too which her children had never quite realized), when all on a
     sudden, one ordinary morning, the postman's-knock brought to her breakfast-table at
     Burleigh-Singleton the following epistle:</p>
    <p>"British Channel, Thursday, March 11th, 1842.</p>
    <p>"The Sir William Elphinston, E.I.M.</p>
    <p>"DEAR JANE: You will be surprised to find that you are to see me so soon, I dare say,
     especially as it is now some years since you will have heard from me. The reason is, I have
     been long in an out-of-the-way part of India, where there is little communication with Europe,
     and so you will excuse my not writing. We hope to find ourselves to-night in Plymouth roads,
     where I shall get into a pilot-boat, and so shall see you to-morrow. You may, therefore, now
     expect your affectionate husband,</p>
    <p>"J.G.J. TRACY, General H.E.I.C.S.</p>
    <p>"P.S.1.—Remember me to our boy, or boys—which is it?</p>
    <p>"P.S.2.—I bring with me the daughter of a friend in India, who is come over for a year or
     two's polish at a first-rate school. Of course you will be glad to receive her as our
     guest.</p>
    <p>"J.G.J.T."</p>
    <p>This loving letter was the most startling event that had ever attempted to unnerve Mrs.
     Tracy; and she accordingly managed, for effect and propriety's sake, to grow very faint upon
     the spot, whether for joy, or sorrow, or fear of lost liberty, or hope of a restored lord, doth
     not appear; she had so long been satisfied with receiving quarterly pay from the India agents,
     that she forgot it was an evidence of her husband's existence; and, lo! here he was returning a
     general, doubtlessly a magnificent moustachioed individual, and she was to be Mrs. General! so
     that when she came completely to herself, after that feint of a faint, she was thinking of
     nothing but court-plumes, oriental pearls, and her gallant Tracy's uniform.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="24"/>The postscripts also had their influence: Charles, naturally affectionate, and
     willing to love a hitherto unseen father, felt hurt, as well he might, at the "boy, or boys;"
     while Julian, who ridiculed his brother's sentimentality, was already fancying that the
     "daughter of a friend" might be a pleasant addition to the dullness of Burleigh-Singleton.</p>
    <p>Preparations vast were made at once for the general's reception; from attic to kitchen was
     sounded the tocsin of his coming. Julian was all bustle and excitement, to his mother's joy and
     pride; while Charles merited her wrath by too much of his habitual and paternal quietude,
     particularly when he withdrew his forces altogether from the loud domestic fray, by retreating
     up-stairs to cogitate and muse, perhaps to make a calming prayer or two about all these matters
     of importance. As for Mrs. Tracy herself, she was even now, within the first hour of that news,
     busily engaged in collecting cosmetics, trinkets, blonde lace, and other female finery,
     resolved to trick herself out like Jezebel, and win her lord once more; whilst the pernicious
     old aunt, who still lived on, notwithstanding all those twenty years of patience, as vivacious
     as before, grumbled and scolded so much at this upsetting of her house, that there was really
     some risk of her altering the will at last, and cutting out Jane Tracy after all.</p>
    <p>And the morrow morning came, as if it were no more than an ordinary Friday, and with it came
     expectancy; and noon succeeded, and with it spirits alternately elated and depressed; and
     evening drew in, with heart-sickness and chagrin at hopes or prophecies deferred; and night,
     and next morning, and still the general came not. So, much weeping at that vexing
     disappointment, after so many pains to please, Mrs. Tracy put aside her numerous aids and
     appliances, and lay slatternly a-bed, to nurse a head-ache until noon; and all had well nigh
     forgotten the probable arrival, when, to every body's dismay, a dusty chaise and four suddenly
     rattled up the terrace, and stopped at our identical number seven.</p>
    <p>Then was there scuffling up, and getting down, and making preparation in hot haste; and a
     stout gentleman with a gamboge face descended from the chaise, exploding wrath like a
     bomb-shell, that so important an approach had made such slight appearance of expectancy: it was
     disrespectful to his rank, and he took care to prove he was somebody, by blowing up the very
     innocent post-boys. This accomplished, he gallantly handed out after him a pretty-looking miss
     in her teens. Poor Mrs. Tracy, <hi>en papillotes</hi>, looked out at the casement like any one
     but Jezebel attired for bewitching, and could have cried for vexation; in
     <pb n="25"/>fact, she did, and passed it off for feeling. Aunt Green, whom the general at first
     lovingly saluted as his wife (for the poor man had entirely forgotten the uxorial appearance),
     was all in a pucker for deafness, blindness, and evident misapprehension of all things in
     general, though clearly pleased, and flattered at her gallant nephew's salutation. Julian, with
     what grace of manner he could muster, was already playing the agreeable to that pretty ward,
     after having, to the general's great surprise, introduced himself to him as his son; while
     Charles, who had rushed into the room, warm-heartedly to fling himself into his father's arms,
     was repelled on the spot for his affection: General Tracy, with a military air, excused himself
     from the embrace, extending a finger to the unknown gentleman, with somewhat of offended
     dignity.</p>
    <p>At last, down came the wife: our general at once perceived himself mistaken in the matter of
     Mrs. Green; and, coldly bowing to the bedizened dame, acknowledged her pretensions with a
     courteous—</p>
    <p>"Mrs. General Tracy, allow me to introduce to you Miss Emily Warren, the daughter of a very
     particular friend of mine:—Miss Warren, Mrs. Tracy."</p>
    <p>For other welcomings, mutual astonishment at each other's fat, some little sorrowful talk of
     the twenty years ago, and some dull paternal jest about this dozen feet of sons, made up the
     chilly meeting: and the slender thread of sentimentals, which might possibly survive it, was
     soon snapt by paying post-boys, orders after luggage, and devouring tiffin.</p>
    <p>The only persons who felt any thing at all, were Mrs. Tracy, vexed at her dishabille, and
     mortified at so cool a reception of, what she hoped, her still unsullied beauties; and Charles,
     poor fellow, who ran up to his studious retreat, and soothed his grief, as best he might, with
     philosophic fancies: it was so cold, so heartless, so unkind a greeting. Romantic youth! how
     should the father have known him for a son?</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
    <head>THE GENERAL AND HIS WARD.</head>
    <p>It is surprising what a change twenty years of a tropical sun can make in the human
     constitution. The captain went forth a good-looking, good-tempered man, destitute neither of
     kind feelings nor masculine
     <pb n="26"/>beauty: the general returned bloated, bilious, irascible, entirely selfish, and
     decidedly ill-favoured. Such affections as he ever had seemed to have been left behind in
     India—that new world, around which now all his associations and remembrances revolved; and the
     reserve (clearly rëproduced in Charles), the habit of silence whereof we took due notice in the
     spring-tide of his life, had now grown, perhaps from some oppressive secret, into a settled,
     moody, continuous taciturnity, which made his curious wife more vexed at him than ever; for,
     notwithstanding all the news he must have had to tell her, the company of John George Julian
     Tracy proved to his long-expectant Jane any thing but cheering or instructive. His past life,
     and present feelings, to say nothing of his future prospects, might all be but a blank, for any
     thing the general seemed to care: brandy and tobacco, an easy chair, and an ordnance map of
     India, with Emily beside him to talk about old times, these were all for which he lived: and
     even the female curiosity of a wife, duly authorized to ask questions, could extract from him
     astonishingly little of his Indian experiences. As to his wealth, indeed, Mrs. Tracy boldly
     made direct inquiry; for Julian set her on to beg for a commission, and Charles also was
     anxious for a year or two at college; but the general divulged not much: albeit he vouchsafed
     to both his sons a liberally increased allowance. It was only when his wife, piqued at such
     reserve, pettishly remarked,</p>
    <p>"At any rate, sir, I may be permitted to hope, that Miss Warren's friends are kind enough to
     pay her expenses;"</p>
    <p>That the veteran, in high dudgeon at any imputation on his Indian acquaintances, sternly
     answered,</p>
    <p>"You need not be apprehensive, madam; Emily Warren is amply provided for." Words which sank
     deep into the prudent mother's mind.</p>
    <p>But we must not too long let dock-leaves hide a violet; it is high time, and barely courteous
     now, to introduce that beautiful exotic, Emily Warren. Her own history, as she will tell it to
     Charles hereafter, was so obscure, that she knew little of it certainly herself, and could
     barely gather probabilities from scattered fragments. At present, we have only to survey
     results in a superficial manner: in their due season, we will dig up all the roots.</p>
    <p>No heroine can probably engage our interest or sympathy who possesses the infirmity of
     ugliness: it is not in human nature to admire her, and human nature is a thing very much to be
     consulted. Moreover, no one ever yet saw an amiable personage, who was not so far pleasing,
     <pb n="27"/>or, in other parlance, so far pretty. I cannot help the common course of things;
     and however hackneyed be the thought, however common-place the phrase, it is true,
     nevertheless, that beauty, singular beauty, would be the first idea of any rational creature,
     who caught but a glimpse of Emily Warren; and I should account it little wonder if, upon a
     calmer gaze, that beauty were found to have its deepest, clearest fountain in those large dark
     eyes of heir's.</p>
    <p>Aware as I may be, that "large dark eyes" are no novelty in tales like this; and famous for
     rare originality as my pen (not to say genius) would become, if an attempt were herein made to
     interest the world in a pink-eyed heroine, still I prefer plodding on in the well-worn path of
     pleasant beauty; and so long as Nature's bounty continues to supply so well the world we live
     in with large dark eyes, and other feminine perfections, our Emily, at any rate, remains in
     fashion; and if she has many pretty peers, let us at least not peevishly complain of them. A
     graceful shape is, luckily, almost the common prerogative of female youthfulness; a dimpled
     smile, a cheerful, winning manner, regular features, and a mass of luxuriant brown hair—these
     all heroines have—and so has our's.</p>
    <p>But no heroine ever had yet Emily Warren's eyes; not identically only, which few can well
     deny; but similarly also, which the many must be good enough to grant: and very few heroes,
     indeed, ever saw their equal; though, if any hereabouts object, I will not be so cruel or
     unreasonable as to hope they will admit it. At first, full of soft light, gentle and alluring,
     they brighten up to blaze upon you lustrously, and fascinate the gazer's dazzled glance: there
     are depths in them that tell of the unfathomable soul, heights in them that speak of the
     spirit's aspirations. It is gentleness and purity, no less than sensibility and passion, that
     look forth in such strange power from those windows of the mind: it is not the mere beautiful
     machine, fair form, and pleasing colours, but the heaven-born light of tenderness and truth,
     streaming through the lens, that takes the fond heart captive. Charles, for one, could not help
     looking long and keenly into Emily Warren's eyes; they magnetized him, so that he might not
     turn away from them: entranced him, that he would not break their charm, had he been able: and
     then the long tufted eyelashes droop so softly over those blazing suns—that I do not in the
     least wonder at Charles's impolite, perhaps, but still natural involuntary stare, and his mute
     abstracted admiration: the poor youth is caught at once, a most willing captive—the moth has
     <pb n="28"/>burnt its wings, and flutters still happily around that pleasant warming radiance.
     How his heart yearned for something to love, some being worthy of his own most pure affections:
     and lo! these beauteous eyes, true witnesses of this sweet mind, have filled him for ever and a
     day with love at first sight.</p>
    <p>But gentle Charles was not the only conquest: the fiery Julian, too, acknowledged her
     supremacy, bowed his stubborn neck, and yoked himself at once, another and more rugged captive,
     to the chariot of her charms. It was Caliban, as well as Ferdinand, courting fair Miranda. In
     his lower grade, he loved—fiercely, coarsely: and the same passion, which filled his brother's
     heart with happiest aspirations, and pure unselfish tenderness towards the beauteous stranger,
     burnt him up as an inward and consuming fire: Charles sunned himself in heaven's genial beams,
     while Julian was hot with the lava-current of his own bad heart's volcano.</p>
    <p>It will save much trouble, and do away with no little useless mystery, to declare, at the
     outset, which of these opposite twin-brothers our dark-eyed Emily preferred. She was only
     seventeen in years; but an Indian sky had ripened her to full maturity, both of form and
     feelings: and having never had any one whom she cared to think upon, and let her heart delight
     in, till Charles looked first upon her beauty wonderingly, it is no marvel if she unconsciously
     reciprocated his young heart's thought—before ever he had breathed it to himself. Julian's
     admiration she entirely overlooked; she never thought him more than civil—barely that,
     perhaps—however he might flatter himself: but her heart and eyes were full of his fair
     contrast, the light seen brighter against darkness; Charles all the dearer for a Julian.
     Intensely did she love him, as only tropic blood can love; intently did she gaze on him, when
     any while he could not see her face, as only those dark eyes could gaze: and her mind, all too
     ignorant but greedy of instruction, no less than her heart, rich in sympathies and covetous of
     love, went forth, and fed deliciously on the intellectual brow, and delicate flushing cheek of
     her noble-minded Charles. Not all in a day, nor a week, nor a month, did their loves thus ripen
     together. Emily was a simple child of nature, who had every thing to learn; she scarcely knew
     her Maker's name, till Charles instructed her in God's great love: the stars were to her only
     shining studs of gold, and the world one mighty plain, and men and women soulless creatures of
     a day, and the wisdom of creation unconsidered, and the book of natural knowledge close sealed
     up, till
     <pb n="29"/> Charles set out before his eager student the mysteries of earth and heaven. Oh,
     those blessed hours of sweet teaching! when he led her quick delighted steps up the many
     avenues of science to the central throne of God! Oh, those happy moments, never to return, when
     her eyes in gentle thankfulness for some new truth laid open to them, flashed upon her youthful
     Mentor, love and intelligence, and pleased admiring wonder! Sweet spring-tide of their loves,
     who scarcely knew they loved, yet thought of nothing but each other; who walked hand in hand,
     as brother and sister, in the flowery ways of mutual blessing, mutual dependence: alas, alas!
     how brief a space can love, that guest from heaven, dwell on earth unsullied!</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
    <head>JEALOUSY.</head>
    <p>For Julian soon perceived that Charles was no despicable rival. At first, self-flattery, and
     the habitual contempt wherewith he regarded his brother, blinded him to Emily's attachment:
     moreover, in the scenes of gayety and the common social circle, she never gave him cause to
     complain of undue preferences; readily she leant upon his arm, cheerfully accompanied him in
     morning-visits, noon-day walks, and evening parties; and if pale Charles (in addition to the
     more regular masters, dancing and music, and other pieces of accomplishment) thought proper to
     bore her with his books for sundry hours every day, Julian found no fault with that;—the girl
     was getting more a woman of the world, and all for him: she would like her play-time all the
     better for such schoolings, and him to be the truant at her side.</p>
    <p>But when, from ordinary civilities, the coarse loud lover proceeded to particular attentions;
     when he affected to press her delicate hand, and ventured to look what he called love into her
     eyes, and to breathe silly nothings in her ear—he could deceive himself no longer,
     notwithstanding all his vanity; as legibly as looks could write it, he read disgust upon her
     face, and from that day forth she shunned him with undisguised abhorrence. Poor innocent maid!
     she little knew the man's black mind, who thus dared to reach up to the height of her
     affections; but she saw
     <pb n="30"/>enough of character in his swart scowling face, and loud assuming manners, to make
     her dread his very presence, as a thunder-cloud across her summer sky.</p>
    <p>Then did the baffled Julian begin to look around him, and took notice of her deepening love
     of Charles; nay, even purposely, she seemed now to make a difference between them, as if to
     check presumption and encourage merit. And he watched their stolen glances, how tremblingly
     they met each other's gaze; and he would often-times roughly break in upon their studies, to
     look on their confused disquietude with the pallid frowns of envy: he would insult poor Charles
     before her, in hope to humble him in her esteem; but mild and Christian patience made her see
     him as a martyr: he would even cast rude slights on her whom he professed to love, with the
     view of raising his brother's chastened wrath, but was forced to quail and sneak away beneath
     her quick indignant glance, ere her more philosophical lover had time to expostulate with the
     cowardly savage.</p>
    <p>Meanwhile, what were the parents about? The general had given out, indeed, that he had
     brought Emily over for schooling; but he seemed so fond of her (in fact, she was the only thing
     to prove he wore a heart), that he never could resolve upon sending her away from, what she now
     might well call, home. Often, in some strange dialect of Hindostan, did they converse together,
     of old times and distant shores; none but Emily might read him to sleep—none but Emily wake him
     in the morning with a kiss—none but Emily dare approach him in his gouty torments—none but
     Emily had any thing like intimate acquaintance with that moody iron-hearted man.</p>
    <p>As to his sons, or the two young men he might presume to be his sons, he neither knew them,
     nor cared to know. Bare civilities, as between man and man, constituted all which their
     intercourse amounted to: what were those young fellows, stout or slim, to him? mere accidents
     of a soldier's gallantries and of an ill-assorted marriage. He neither had, nor wished to have,
     any sympathies with them: Julian might be as bad as he pleased, and Charles as good, for any
     thing the general seemed to heed: they could not dive with him into the past, and the sports of
     Hindostan: they reminded him, simply, of his wife, for pleasures of Memory; of the grave, for
     pleasures of Hope: he was older when he looked at them: and they seemed to him only living
     witnesses of his folly as lieutenant, in the choice of Mrs. Tracy. I will not take upon myself
     to say, that he had any occasion to congratulate himself on the latter reminiscence.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="31"/>So he quickly acquiesced in Julian's wish for a commission, and entirely approved
     of Charles's college schemes. After next September, the funds should be forthcoming: not but
     that he was rich enough, and to spare, any month in the year: but he would be vastly richer
     then, from prize-money, or some such luck. It was more prudent to delay until September.</p>
    <p>With reference to Emily—no, no—I could see at once that General Tracy never had any serious
     intention to part with Emily; but she had all manner of masters at home, and soon made
     extraordinary progress. As for the matter of his sons falling in love with her, attractive in
     all beauty though she were, he never once had given it a thought: for, first, he was too much a
     man of the world to believe in such ideal trash as love: and next, he totally forgot that his
     "boy, or boys," had human feelings. So, when his wife one day gave him a gentle and triumphant
     hint of the state of affairs, it came upon him overwhelmingly, like an avalanche: his yellow
     face turned flake-white, he trembled as he stood, and really seemed to take so natural a
     probability to heart as the most serious of evils.</p>
    <p>"My son Julian in love with Emily! and if not he, at any rate Charles! What the devil, madam,
     can you mean by this dreadful piece of intelligence?—It's impossible, ma'am; nonsense! it can't
     be true; it shan't, ma'am."</p>
    <p>And the general, having issued his military mandates, wrapped himself in secresy once more;
     satisfied that both of those troublesome sons were to leave home after the next quarter, and
     the prize-money at Hancock's.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
    <head>THE CONFIDANTE.</head>
    <p>But Mrs. Tracy had the best reason for believing her intelligence was true, and she could see
     very little cause for regarding it as dreadful. True, one son would have been enough for this
     wealthy Indian heiress—but still it was no harm to have two strings to her bow. Julian was her
     favourite, and should have the girl if she could manage it; but if Emily
     <pb n="32"/> Warren would not hear of such a husband, why Charles Tracy may far better get her
     money than any body else.</p>
    <p>That she possessed great wealth was evident: such jewellery, such Trinchinopoli chains, such
     a blaze of diamonds <hi>en suite</hi>, such a multitude of armlets, and circlets, and
     ear-rings, and other oriental finery, had never shone on Devonshire before: at the Eyemouth
     ball, men worshipped her, radiant in beauty, and gorgeously apparelled. Moreover, money
     overflowed her purse, her work-box, and her jewel-case: Charles's village school, and many
     other well-considered charities, rejoiced in the streams of her munificence. The general had
     given her a banker's book of signed blank checks, and she filled up sums at pleasure: such
     unbounded confidence had he in her own prudence and her far-off father's liberality. The few
     hints her husband deigned to give, encouraged Mrs. Tracy to conclude, that she would be a catch
     for either of her sons; and, as for the girl herself, she had clearly been brought up to order
     about a multitude of servants, to command the use of splendid equipages, and to spend money
     with unsparing hand.</p>
    <p>Accordingly, one day when Julian was alone with his mother, their conversation ran as
     follows:</p>
    <p>"Well, Julian dear, and what do you think of Emily Warren?"</p>
    <p>"Think, mother? why—that she's deuced pretty, and dresses like an empress: but where did the
     general pick her up, eh?—who is she?"</p>
    <p>"Why, as to who she is—I know no more than you; she is Emily Warren: but as to the great
     question of what she is, I know that she is rolling in riches, and would make one of my boys a
     very good wife."</p>
    <p>"Oh, as to wife, mother, one isn't going to be fool enough to marry for love now-a-days:
     things are easier managed hereabouts, than that: but money makes it quite another thing. So,
     this pretty minx is rich, is she?"</p>
    <p>"A great heiress, I assure you, Julian."</p>
    <p>"Bravo, bravo-o! but how to make the girl look sweet upon me, mother? There's that
     white-livered fellow, Charles—"</p>
    <p>"Never mind him, boy; do you suppose he would have the heart to make love to such a splendid
     creature as Miss Warren: fy, Julian, for a faint heart: Charles is well enough as a
     Sabbath-school teacher, but I hope he will not bear away the palm of a ladye-love from my fine
     high-spirited Julian." Poor Mrs. Tracy was as flighty and romantic at forty-five as she had
     been at fifteen.</p>
    <p>The fine high-spirited Julian answered not a word, but looked excessively cross; for he knew
     full well that Charles's chance was to his in the ratio of a million to nothing.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="33"/>"What, boy," went on the prudent mother, "still silent! I am afraid Emily's good
     looks have been thrown away upon you, and that your heart has not found out how to love
     her."</p>
    <p>"Love her, mother? Curses! would you drive me mad? I think and dream of nothing but that
     girl: morning, noon, and night, her eyes persecute me: go where I will, and do what I will, her
     image haunts me: d——n it, mother' don't I love the girl?"</p>
    <p>[Oh love, love! thou much-slandered monosyllable, how desperately do bad men malign
     thee!]</p>
    <p>"Hush, Julian; pray be more guarded in your language; I am glad to see though that your heart
     is in the right place: suppose now that I aid your suit a little? I dare say I could do a great
     deal for you, my son; and nothing could be more delightful to your mother than to try and make
     her Julian happy."</p>
    <p>True, Mrs. Tracy; you were always theatrically given, and played the coquette in youth; so in
     age the character of go-between befits you still: dearly do you love to dabble in, what you are
     pleased to call, "<hi>une affaire du cœur</hi>."</p>
    <p>"Mother," after a pause, replied her hopeful progeny, "if the girl had been only pretty, I
     shouldn't have asked any body's help; for marriage was never to my liking, and folks may have
     their will of prouder beauties than this Emily, without going to church for it; but money makes
     it quite another matter: and I may as well have the benefit of your assistance in this matter
     o' money, eh mother? matrimony, you know: an heiress and a beauty may be worth the
     wedding-ring; besides, when my commission comes, I can follow the good example that my parents
     set me, you know; and, after a three months' honey-mooning, can turn bachelor again for twenty
     years or so, as our governor-general did, and so leave wifey at home, till she becomes a Mrs.
     General like you."</p>
    <p>Now, strange to say, this heartless bit of villany was any thing but unpleasing to the
     foolish, flattered heart of Mrs. Tracy; he was a chip of the old block, no better than his
     father: so she thanked "dear Julian" for his confidence, with admiration and emotion; and
     looking upwards, after the fashion of a Covent Garden martyr, blessed him.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <pb n="34"/>
    <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
    <head>THE COURSE OF TRUE LOVE, ETC.</head>
    <p>"<hi>Emily</hi>, my dear, take Julian's arm: here, Charles, come and change with me; I should
     like a walk with you to Oxton, to see how your little scholars get on." So spake the intriguing
     mother.</p>
    <p>"Why, that is just what I was going to do with Charles," said Emily, "and if Julian will
     excuse me—"</p>
    <p>"Oh, never mind me, Miss Warren, pray; come along with me, will you, mother?"</p>
    <p>So they paired off in more well-matched couples (for Julian luckily took huff), and went
     their different ways: with those went hatred, envy, worldly scheming, and that lowest sort of
     love that ill deserves the name; with these remain all things pure, affectionate,
     benevolent.</p>
    <p>"Charles, dear," (they were just like brother and sister, innocent and loving), "how kind it
     is of you to take me with you; if you only knew how I dreaded Julian!"</p>
    <p>"Why, Emmy? can he have offended you in any way?"</p>
    <p>"Oh, Charles, he is so rude, and says such silly things, and—I am quite afraid to be alone
     with him."</p>
    <p>"What—what—what does he say to you, Emily?" hurriedly urged her half-avowed lover.</p>
    <p>"Oh, don't ask me, Charles—pray drop the subject;" and, as she blushed, tears stood in her
     eyes.</p>
    <p>Charles bit his lip and clenched his fist involuntarily; but an instant word of prayer drove
     away the spirit of hatred, and set up love triumphant in its place.</p>
    <p>"My Emily—oh, what have I said? may I—may I call you my Emily? dearest, dearest girl!"
     escaped his lips, and he trembled at his own presumption. It was a presumptuous speech indeed;
     but it burst from the well of his affections, and he could not help it.</p>
    <p>Her answer was not in words, and yet his heart-strings thrilled beneath the melody; for her
     eyes shed on him a blaze of love that made him almost faint before them. In an instant, they
     understood, without a word, the happy truth, that each one loved the other.</p>
    <p>"Precious, precious Emily!" They were now far away from Burleigh, in the fields; and he
     seized her hand, and covered it with kisses.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="35"/>What more they said I was not by to hear, and if I had been would not have divulged
     it. There are holy secrets of affection, which those who can remember their first love—and
     first love is the only love worth mentioning—may think of for themselves. Well, far better than
     my feeble pencilling can picture, will they fill up this slight sketch. That walk to Oxton,
     that visit to the village school, was full of generous affections unrepressed, the out-pourings
     of two deep-welled hearts, flowing forth in sympathetic ecstasy. The trees, and fields, and
     cottages were bathed in heavenly light, and the lovers, happy in each other's trust, called
     upon the all-seeing God to bless the best affections of His children.</p>
    <p>And what a change these mutual confessions made in both their minds! Doubt was gone; they
     <hi>were</hi> beloved; oh, richest treasure of joy! Fear was gone; they dared declare their
     love; oh, purest river of all sublunary pleasures! No longer pale, anxious, thoughtful, worn by
     the corroding care of "Does she—does she love?"—Charles was, from that moment, a buoyant,
     cheerful, exhilarated being—a new character; he put on manliness, and fortitude, and somewhat
     of involuntary pride; whilst Emily felt, that enriched by the affections of him whom she
     regarded as her wisest, kindest earthly friend, by the acquisition of his love, who had led her
     heart to higher good than this world at its best can give her, she was elevated and ennobled
     from the simple Indian child, into the loved and honoured Christian woman. They went on that
     important walk to Oxton feeble, divided, unsatisfied in heart: they returned as two united
     spirits, one in faith, one in hope, one in love; both heavenly and earthly.</p>
    <p>But the happy hour is past too soon; and, home again, they mixed once more with those
     conflicting elements of hatred and contention.</p>
    <p>"Emily," asked the general, in a very unusual stretch of curiosity, "where have you been to
     with Charles Tracy? You look flushed, my dear; what's the matter?"</p>
    <p>Of course "nothing" was the matter: and the general was answered wisely, for love was nothing
     in his average estimate of men and women.</p>
    <p>"Charles, what can have come to you? I never saw you look so happy in my life," was the
     mother's troublesome inquiry; "why, our staid youth positively looks cheerful."</p>
    <p>Charles's walk had refreshed him, taken away his head-ache, put him in spirits, and all
     manner of glib reasons for rejoicing.</p>
    <p>"You were right, Julian," whispered Mrs. Tracy, "and we'll soon put the stopper on all this
     sort of thing."</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="36"/>So, then, the moment our guiltless pair of lovers had severally stolen away to
     their own rooms, there to feast on well-remembered looks, and words, and hopes—there to lay
     before that heavenly Friend, whom both had learned to trust, all their present joys, as
     aforetime all their cares—Mrs. Tracy looked significantly at Julian, and thus addressed her
     ever stern-eyed lord:</p>
    <p>"So, general, the old song's coming true to us, I find, as to other folks, who once were
     young together: </p><p>
     <l>"'And when with envy Time, transported, seeks to rob us of our joys,</l>
     <l> You'll in your girls again be courted, and I'll go wooing in my boys.'"</l></p>
    <p>So said or sung the flighty Mrs. Tracy. It was as simple and innocent a quotation as could
     possibly be made; I suppose most couples, who ever heard the stanza, and have grown-up
     children, have thought upon its dear domestic beauty: but it strangely affected the irascible
     old general. He fumed and frowned, and looked the picture of horror; then, with a fierce oath
     at his wife and sons, he firmly said—</p>
    <p>"Woman, hold your fool's tongue: begone, and send Emily to me this minute: stop, Mr.
     Julian—no—run up for your brother Charles, and come you all to me in the study. Instantly, sir!
     do as I bid you, without a word."</p>
    <p>Julian would gladly have fought it out with his imperative father; but, nevertheless, it was
     a comfort to have to fetch pale Charles for a jobation; so he went at once. And the three young
     people, two of them trembling with affections overstrained, and the third indurated in
     effrontery, stood before that stern old man.</p>
    <p>"Emily, child,"—and he added something in Hindostanee, "have I been kind to you—and do you
     owe me any love?"</p>
    <p>"Dear, dear sir, how can you ask me that?" said the warm-affectioned girl, falling on her
     knees in tears.</p>
    <p>"Get up, sweet child, and hear me: you see those boys; as you love me, and yourself, and
     happiness, and honour—dare not to think of either, one moment, as your husband."</p>
    <p>Emily fainted; Charles staggered to assist her, though he well-nigh swooned himself; and
     Julian folded his arms with a resolute air, as waiting to hear what next.</p>
    <p>But the general disappointed him: he had said his say: and, as volatile salts, a lady's maid,
     and all that sort of rëinvigoration, seemed essential to Emily's recovery, he rang the bell
     forthwith: so the pleasant family party broke up without another word.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <pb n="37"/>
    <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
    <head>THE MYSTERY.</head>
    <p>Our lovers would not have been praiseworthy, perhaps not human, had they not met in secret
     once and again. True, their regularly concerted studies were forbidden, and they never now
     might openly walk out unaccompanied: but love (who has not found this out?) is both daring and
     ingenious; and notwithstanding all that Emily purposed about doing as the general so strangely
     bade her, they had many happy meetings, rich with many happy words: all the happier no doubt
     for their stolen sweetness.</p>
    <p>There was one great and engrossing subject which often had employed their curiosity; who and
     what was Emily Warren? for the poor girl did not know herself. All she could guess, she told
     Charles, as he zealously cross-questioned her from time to time: and the result of his
     inquiries would appear to be as follows:</p>
    <p>Emily's earliest recollections were of great barbaric pomp; huge elephants richly
     caparisoned, mighty fans of peacock's tails, lines of matchlock men, tribes of jewelled
     servants, a gilded palace, with its gardens and fountains: plenty of rare gems to play with,
     and a splendid queenly woman, whom she called by the Hindoo name for mother. The general, too,
     was there among her first associations, as the gallant Captain Tracy, with his company of
     native troops.</p>
    <p>Then an era happened in her life; a tearful leave-taking with that proud princess, who
     scarcely would part with her for sorrow; but the captain swore it should be so: and an old
     Scotch-woman, her nurse, she could remember, who told her as a child, but whether religiously
     or not she could not tell, "Darling, come to me when you wish to know who made you;" and then
     Mrs. Mackie went and spoke to the princess, and soothed her, that she let the child depart
     peacefully. Most of her gorgeous jewellery dated from that earliest time of inexplicable
     oriental splendour.</p>
    <p>After those infantine seven years, the captain took her with him to his station up the
     country, where she lived she knew not how long, in a strong hill-fort, one Puttymuddyfudgepoor,
     where there was a great deal of fighting, and besieging, and storming, and cannonading; but it
     ceased
     <pb n="38"/>at last, and the captain, who then soon successively became both major and colonel,
     always kept her in his own quarters, making her his little pet; and, after the fighting was all
     over, his brother-officers would take her out hunting in their howdahs, and she had plenty of
     palanquin-bearers, sepoys, and servants at command; and, what was more, good nurse Mackie was
     her constant friend and attendant.</p>
    <p>Time wore on, and many little incidents of Indian life occurred, which varied every day
     indeed, but still left nothing consequential behind them: there were tiger-hunts, and
     incursions of Scindian tribes, and Pindarree chieftains taken captive, and wounded soldiers
     brought into the hospital; and often had she and good nurse Mackie tended at the sick bed-side.
     And the colonel had the jungle fever, and would not let her go from his sight; so she caught
     the fever too, and through Heaven's mercy was recovered. And the colonel was fonder of her now
     than ever, calling her his darling little child, and was proud to display her early budding
     beauty to his military friends—pleasant sort of gentlemen, who gave her pretty presents.</p>
    <p>Then she grew up into womanhood, and saw more than one fine uniform at her feet, but she did
     not comprehend those kindnesses: and the general (he was general now) got into great passions
     with them, and stormed, and swore, and drove them all away. Nurse Mackie grew to be old, and
     sometimes asked her, "Can you keep a secret, child?—no, no, I dare not trust you yet: wait a
     wee, wait a wee, my bonnie, bonnie bairn."</p>
    <p>And now speedily came the end. The general resolved on returning to his own old shores:
     chiefly, as it seemed, to avoid the troublesome pertinacity of sundry suitors, who sought of
     him the hand of Emily Warren for, by this name she was beginning to be called: in her earliest
     recollection she was Amina; then at the hill-fort, Emily—Emily—nothing for years but Emily: and
     as she grew to womanhood, the general bade her sign her name to notes, and leave her card at
     houses, as Emily Warren: why, or by what right, she never thought of asking. But nurse Mackie
     had hinted she might have had "a better name and a truer;" and therefore, she herself had asked
     the general what this hint might mean; and he was so angry that he discharged nurse Mackie at
     Madras, directly he arrived there to take ship for England.</p>
    <p>Then, just before embarking, poor nurse Mackie came to her secretly, and said, "Child, I will
     trust you with a word; you are not what he thinks you." And she cried a great deal, and longed
     to come to Eng
     <pb n="39"/>land; but the general would not hear of it; so he pensioned her off, and left her
     at Madras, giving somebody strict orders not to let her follow him.</p>
    <p>Nevertheless, just as they were getting into the boat to cross the surf, the affectionate old
     soul ran out upon the strand, and called to her "Amy Stuart! Amy Stuart!" to the general's
     great amazement as clearly as her own; and she held up a packet in her hand as they were
     pushing off, and shouted after her, "Child—child! if you would have your rights, remember
     Jeanie Mackie!"</p>
    <p>After that, succeeded the monotony of a long sea voyage. The general at first seemed vexed
     about Mrs. Mackie, and often wished that he had asked her what she meant; however, his brow
     soon cleared, for he reflected that a discarded servant always tells falsehoods, if only to
     make her master mischief.</p>
    <p>"The voyage over, Charles, with all its cards, quadrilles, doubling the cape, crossing the
     line, and the wearisome routine of sky and sea, the quarter-deck and cabin, we found ourselves
     at length in Plymouth Sound; left the Indiaman to go up the channel; and I suppose the
     post-chaise may be consigned to your imagination."</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
    <head>HOW TO CLEAR IT UP.</head>
    <p>In all this there was mystery enough for a dozen lovers to have crazed their brains about.
     Emily might be a queen of the East, defrauded of hereditary glories, and at any rate deserved
     such rank, if Charles was to be judge; but what was more important, if the general had any
     reason at all for his arbitrary mandate prohibiting their love, it was very possible that
     reason was a false one.</p>
    <p>Meantime, Charles had little now to live for, except his dear forbidden Emily, any more than
     she for him. And to peace of mind in both, the elucidation of that mystery which hung about her
     birth, grew more needful day by day. At last, one summer evening, when they had managed a quiet
     walk upon the sands under the Beacon cliff, Charles said abruptly, after some moments of
     abstraction, "Dearest, I am resolved."</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="40"/>"Resolved, Charles! what about?" and she felt quite alarmed; for her lover looked
     so stern, that she could not tell what was going to happen next.</p>
    <p>"I'll clear it up, that I will; I only wish I had the money."</p>
    <p>"Why, Charles, what in the world are you dreaming about? you frighten me, dearest; are you
     ill? don't look so serious, pray."</p>
    <p>"Yes, Emily, I will; at once too. I'm off to Madras by next packet; or, that is to say,
     would, if I could get my passage free."</p>
    <p>"My noble Charles, if that were the only objection, I would get you all the means; for the
     kind—kind general suffers me to have whatever sums I choose to ask for. Only, Charles, indeed I
     cannot spare you; do not—do not go away and leave me; there's Julian, too—don't leave me—and
     you might never come back, and—and—" all the remainder was lost in sobbing.</p>
    <p>"No, my Emmy, we must not use the general's gold in doing what he might not wish; it would be
     ungenerous. I will try to get somebody to lend me what I want—say Mrs. Sainsbury, or the
     Tamworths. And as for leaving you, my love, have no fears for me or for yourself; situated as
     we are, I take it as a duty to go, and make you happier, setting you in rights, whatever these
     may be; and for the rest, I leave you in His holy keeping who can preserve you alike in body,
     as in soul, from all things that would hurt you, and whose mercy will protect me in all perils,
     and bring me back to you in safety. This is my trust, Emmy."</p>
    <p>"Dear Charles, you are always wiser and better than I am: let it be so then, my best of
     friends. Seek out good nurse Mackie, I can give you many clues, hear what she has to say; and
     may the God of your own poor fatherless Emily speed your holy mission! Yet there is one thing,
     Charles; ought you not to ask your parents for their leave to go? You are better skilled to
     judge than I can be, though."</p>
    <p>"Emmy, whom have I to ask? my father? he cares not whither I go nor what becomes of me; I
     hardly know him, and for twenty years of my short life of twenty-one, scarcely believed in his
     existence; or should I ask my mother? alas—love! I wish I could persuade myself that she would
     wish me back again if I were gone; moreover, how can I respect her judgment, or be guided by
     her counsel, whose constant aim has been to thwart my feeble efforts after truth and wisdom,
     and to pamper all ill growths in my unhappy brother Julian? No, Emily; I am a man now, and take
     my own advice. If a parent forbade me, indeed, and reasonably, it would be fit to acquiesce;
     but knowing, as I
     <pb n="41"/>have sad cause to know, that none but you, my love, will be sorry for my absence,
     as for your sake alone that absence is designed, I need take counsel only of us who are here
     present—your own sweet eyes, myself, and God who seeth us."</p>
    <p>"True—most true, dear Charles; I knew that you judged rightly."</p>
    <p>"Moreover, Emmy, secresy is needful for the due fulfilment of my purpose." (Charles little
     thought how congenial to his nature was that same secresy.) "None but you must know where I am,
     or whither I am gone. For if there really is any mystery which the general would conceal from
     us, be assured he both could and would frustrate all my efforts if he knew of my design. The
     same ship that carried me out would convey an emissary from him, and nurse Mackie never could
     be found by me. I must go then secretly, and, for our peace sake, soon; how dear to me that
     embassy will be, entirely undertaken in my darling Emmy's cause!"</p>
    <p>"But—but, Charles, what if Julian, in your absence—"</p>
    <p>"Hark, my own betrothed! while I am near you—and I say it not of threat, but as in the sight
     of One who has privileged me to be your protector—you are safe from any serious vexation; and
     the moment I am gone, fly to my father, tell him openly your fears, and he will scatter
     Julian's insolence to the winds of heaven."</p>
    <p>"Thank you—thank you, wise dear Charles; you have lifted a load from my poor, weak, woman's
     heart, that had weighed it down too heavily. I will trust in God more, and dread Julian less.
     Oh! how I will pray for you when far away."</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
    <head>AUNT GREEN'S LEGACY.</head>
    <p>At last—at last, Mrs. Green fell ill, and, hard upon the over-ripe age of eighty-seven,
     seemed likely to drop into the grave—to the unspeakable delight of her expectant relatives.
     Sooth to say, niece Jane, the soured and long-waiting legatee, had now for years been treating
     the poor old woman very scurvily: she had lived too long, and had grown to be a burden;
     notwithstanding that her ample income still kept on the
     <pb n="42"/>house, and enabled the general to nurse his own East India Bonds right comfortably.
     But still the old aunt would not die, and as they sought not her, nor heir's (quite contrary to
     St. Paul's disinterestedness), she was looked upon in the light of an incumbrance, on her own
     property and in her own house. Mrs. Tracy longed to throw off the yoke of dependance, and made
     small secret of the hatred of the fetter: for the old woman grew so deaf and blind, that there
     could be no risk at all, either in speaking one's mind, or in thoroughly neglecting her.</p>
    <p>However, now that the harvest of hope appeared so near, the legatee renewed her old
     attentions: Death was a guest so very welcome to the house, that it is no wonder that his
     arrival was hourly expected with buoyant cheerfulness, and a something in the mask of
     kindliness: but I suspect that lamb-skin concealed a very wolf. So, Mrs. Tracy tenderly
     inquired of the doctor, and the doctor shook his head; and other doctors came to help, and
     shook their heads together. The patient still grew worse—O, brightening prospect!—though, now
     and then, a cordial draught seemed to revive her so alarmingly, that Mrs. Tracy affectionately
     urging that the stimulants would be too exciting for the poor dear sufferer's nerves, induced
     Dr. Graves to discontinue them. Then those fearful scintillations in her lamp of life grew
     fortunately duller, and the nurse was by her bed-side night and day; and the old aunt became
     more and more peevish, and was more and more spoken of by the Tracy family—in her possible
     hearing, as "that dear old soul"—out of it, "that vile old witch."</p>
    <p>Charles, to be sure, was an exception in all this, as he ever was: for he took on him the
     Christian office of reading many prayers to the poor decaying creature, and (only that his
     father would not hear of such a thing) desired to have the vicar to assist him. Emily also,
     full of sympathy, and disinterested care, would watch the fretful patient, hour after hour, in
     those long, dull nights of pain; and the poor, old, perishing sinner loved her coming, for she
     spoke to her the words of hope and resignation. Whether that sweet missionary, scarcely yet a
     convert from her own dark creed—(Alas! the Amina had offered unto Juggernaut, and Emily of the
     strong hill-fort had scarcely heard of any truer God; and the fair girl was a woman-grown
     before, in her first earthly love, she also came to know the mercies Heaven has in store for
     us)—whether unto any lasting use she prayed and reasoned with that hard, dried heart, none but
     the Omniscient can tell. Let us hope: let us hope; for the fretful voice was stilled, and the
     cloudy forehead brightened, and the hag
     <pb n="43"/>gard eyes looked cheerfully to meet the inevitable stroke of death. Thus in wisdom
     and in charity, in patience and in faith, that gentle pair of lovers comforted the dying
     soul.</p>
    <p>However, days rolled away, and Aunt Green lingered on still, tenaciously clinging unto life:
     until one morning early, she felt so much better, that she insisted on being propped up by
     pillows, and seeing all the household round her bed to speak to them. So up came every one, in
     no small hope of legacies, and what the lawyers call "<hi>donationes mortis causâ</hi>."</p>
    <p>The general was at her bed's-head, with, I am ashamed to say, perhaps unconsciously, a
     countenance more ridiculous than lugubrious; though he tried to subdue the buoyancy of hope and
     to put on looks of decent mourning; on the other side, the long-expectant legatee, Niece Jane,
     prudently concealed her questionable grief behind a scented pocket-handkerchief. Julian held
     somewhat aloof, for the scene was too depressing for his taste: so he affected to read a
     prayer-book, wrong way up, with his tongue in his cheek: Charles, deeply solemnized at the near
     approach of death, knelt at the poor invalid's bedside; and Emily stood by, leaning over her,
     suffused in tears. At the further corners of the bed, might be seen an old servant or two; and
     Mrs. Green's butler and coachman, each a forty years' fixture, presented their gray heads at
     the bottom of the room, and really looked exceedingly concerned.</p>
    <p>Mrs. Green addressed them first, in her feeble broken manner: "Grant—and John—good and
     faithful—thank you—thank you both; and you too, kind Mrs. Lloyd, and Sally, and
     nurse—what's-your-name: give them the packets, nurse—all marked—first drawer, desk:
     there—there—God bless you—good—faithful."</p>
    <p>The old servants, full of sorrow at her approaching loss, were comforted too: for a kind
     word, and a hundred pound note a-piece, made amends for much bereavement: the sick-nurse found
     her gift was just a tithe of their's, and recognised the difference both just and kind.</p>
    <p>"Niece Jane—you've waited—long—for—this day: my will—rewards you."</p>
    <p>"O dear—dear aunt, pray don't talk so; you'll recover yet, pray—pray don't:" she pretended to
     drown the rest in sorrow, but winked at her husband over the handkerchief.</p>
    <p>"Julian!" (the precious youth attempted to look miserable, and came as called,) "you will
     find—I have remembered—you, Julian." So he winked, too, at his mother, and tried to blubber a
     "thank you."</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="44"/>"Charles—where's Charles? give me your hand, Charles dear—let me feel your face:
     here, Charles—a little pocket-book—good lad—good lad. There's Emily, too—dear child, she
     came—too late—I forgot her—I forgot her! general give her half—half—if you love—love—Emi—"</p>
    <p>All at once her jaw dropped; her eyes, which had till now been preternaturally bright, filmed
     over; her head fell back upon the pillow; and the rich old aunt was dead.</p>
    <p>Julian gave a shout that might have scared the parting spirit!</p>
    <p>Really, the general was shocked, and Mrs. Tracy too; and the servants murmured "shame—shame!"
     poor Charles hid his face; Emily looked up indignantly; but Julian asked, with an oath,
     "Where's the good of being hypocrites?" and then added, "now, mother, let us find the
     will."</p>
    <p>Then the nurse went to close the dim glazed eyes; and the other sorrowing domestics slunk
     away; and Charles led Emily out of the chamber of death, saddened and shocked at such indecent
     haste.</p>
    <p>Meanwhile, the hopeful trio rummaged every drawer—tumbled out the mingled contents of boxes,
     desk, and escritoire—still, no will—no will: and at last the nurse, who more than once had
     muttered, "Shame on you all," beneath her breath, said,</p>
    <p>"If you want the will, it's under her pillow: but don't disturb her yet, poor thing!"</p>
    <p>Julian's rude hand had already thrust aside the lifeless, yielding head, and clutched the
     will: the father and mother—though humbled and wonder-stricken at his daring—gathered round
     him; and he read aloud, boldly and steadily to the end, though with scowling brow, and many
     curses interjectional:</p>
    <p>"<hi>In</hi> the name of God, Amen. I, Constance Green, make this my last will and testament.
     Forasmuch as my niece, Jane Tracy, has watched and waited for my death these two-and-twenty
     years, I leave her all the shoes, slippers, and goloshes, whereof I may happen to die
     possessed: item, I leave Julian, her son, my '<hi>Whole Duty of Man</hi>,' convinced that he is
     deficient in it all: item, I confirm all the gifts which I intend to make upon my death-bed:
     item, forasmuch as General Tracy, my niece's husband, on his return from abroad, greeted me
     with much affection, I bequeath and give to him five thousand pounds' worth of Exchequer bills,
     now in my banker's hands; and appoint him my sole executor. As to my landed property, it will
     all go, in course of law, to my heir,
     <pb n="45"/>Samuel Hayley, and may he and his long enjoy it. And as to the remainder of my
     personal effects, including nine thousand pounds bank stock, my Dutch fives, and other matters,
     whereof I may die possessed (seeing that my relatives are rich enough without my help), I give
     and bequeath the same, subject as hereinbefore stated, to the trustees, for the time being, of
     the Westminster Lying-in Hospital, in trust, for the purposes of that charitable institution.
     In witness whereof, I have hereunto set my hand and seal this 13th day of May, 1840.</p>
    <p>"<hi>Constance Green.</hi>"</p>
    <p>"Duly signed, sealed, and delivered! d——nation!" was Julian's brief epilogue—"General, let's
     burn it."</p>
    <p>"You can if you please, Mr. Julian," interposed the nurse, who had secretly enjoyed all this,
     "and if you like to take the consequences; but, as each of the three witnesses has the will
     sealed up in copy, and the poor deceased there took pains to sign them all, perhaps—"</p>
    <p>This settled the affair: and the discomfited expectants made a precipitate retreat. As the
     general, however, got vastly more than he expected, for his individual merits; and seeing that
     he loved Emily as much as he hated both Julian and his wife, he really felt well-pleased upon
     the whole, and took on him the duties of executor with cheerfulness. So they buried Aunt Green
     as soon as might be.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XI.</head>
    <head>PREPARATIONS AND DEPARTURE.</head>
    <p>Charles's pocket-book was full of clean bank notes, fifteen hundred pounds' worth: it
     contained also a diamond ring, and a lock of silvery hair; the latter a proof of affectionate
     sentiment in the kind old soul, that touched him at the heart.</p>
    <p>"And now, my Emmy, the way is clear to us; Providence has sent me this, that I may right you,
     dearest: and it will be wise in us to say nothing of our plans. Avoid inquiries—for I did not
     say conceal or falsify facts: but, while none but you, love, heed of my departure, and while I
     go for our sakes alone, we need not invite disappointment by open-
     <pb n="46"/>mouthed publicity. To those who love me, Emmy, I am frank and free; but with those
     who love us not, there is a wisdom and a justice in concealment. They do not deserve
     confidence, who will not extend to us their sympathy. None but yourself must know whither I am
     bound; and, after some little search for curiosity's sake, when a week is past and gone, no
     soul will care for me of those at home. With you, I will manage to communicate by post,
     directing my letters to Mrs. Sainsbury, at Oxton: I will prepare her for it. She knows my love
     for you, and how they try to thwart us; but even she, however trustworthy, need not be told my
     destination yet awhile, until 'India' appears upon the post-mark. How glad will you be, dearest
     one, how happy in our secret—to read my heart's own thoughts, when I am far away—far away,
     clearing up mine Emmy's cares, and telling her how blessed I feel in ministering to her
     happiness!"</p>
    <p>Such was the substance of their talk, while counting out the pocket-book.</p>
    <p>Charles's remaining preparations were simple enough, now his purse was flush of money: he
     resolved upon taking from his home no luggage whatever: preferring to order down, from an
     outfitting house in London, a regular kit of cadet's necessaries, to wait for him at the Europe
     Hotel, Plymouth, on a certain day in the ensuing week. So that, burdened only with his Emmy's
     miniature, and his pocket-book of bank notes, he might depart quietly some evening, get to
     Plymouth in a prëconcerted way, by chaise or coach, before the morrow morning; thence, a boat
     to meet the ship off-shore, and then—hey, for the Indies!</p>
    <p>It was as well-devised a scheme as could possibly be planned; though its secresy, especially
     with a mother in the case, may be a moot point as to the abstract moral thereof: nevertheless,
     concretely, the only heart his so mysterious absence would have pained, was made aware of all:
     then, again, secresy had been the atmosphere of his daily life, the breath of his education;
     and he too sorely knew his mother would rejoice at the departure, and Julian, too—all the more
     certainly, as both brothers were now rivals professed for the hand of Emily Warren: as to the
     general, he might, or he might not, smoke an extra cheroot in the excitement of his wonder; and
     if he cared about it anyways more tragically than tobacco might betray, Emily knew how to
     comfort him.</p>
    <p>With respect to other arrangements, Emmy furnished Charles with letters to certain useful
     people at Madras, and in particular to the "somebody" who looked after Mrs. Mackie: so, the
     mystery was easy of access, and he doubted not of overcoming, on the spot, every unseen dif
     <pb n="47"/>ficulty. The plan of leaving all luggage behind, a capital idea, would enable him
     to go forth freely and unshackled, with an ordinary air, in hat and great-coat, as for an
     evening's walk; and was quite in keeping with the natural reserve of his whole character—a bad
     habit of secresy, which he probably inherited from his father, the lieutenant of old times. And
     yet, for all the wisdom, and mystery, and shrewd settling of the plan, its accomplishment was
     as nearly as possible most fatally defeated.</p>
    <p>The important evening arrived; for the Indiaman—it was our old friend Sir William
     Elphinston—would be off Plymouth, next morning: the goods had been, for a day or two, safely
     deposited at the Europe, as per invoice, all paid: the lovers, in this last, this happiest, yet
     by far the saddest of their stolen interviews, had exchanged vows and kisses, and upon the
     beach, beneath those friendly cliffs, had commended one another to their Father in heaven. They
     had returned to the unsocial circle of home; all was fixed; the clock struck nine: and Charles,
     accidentally squeezing Emily's hand, rose to leave the tea-table.</p>
    <p>"Where are you going, Mr. Charles?"</p>
    <p>"I am going out, Julian."</p>
    <p>"Thank you, sir! I knew that, but whither? General, I say, here's Charles going to serenade
     somebody by moonlight."</p>
    <p>The brandy-sodden parent, scarcely conscious, said something about his infernal majesty; and,
     "What then?—let him go, can't you?"</p>
    <p>"Well, Julian dear, perhaps your brother will not mind your going with him; particularly as
     Emily stays at home with me."</p>
    <p>This Mrs. Tracy spoke archly, intended as a hint to induce Julian to remain: but he had other
     thoughts—and simply said, in an ill-tempered tone of voice, "Done, Charles."</p>
    <p>It was a dilemma for our escaping hero; but glancing a last look at Emily, he departed, and
     walked on some way as quietly as might be with Julian by his side: thinking, perhaps, he would
     soon be tired; and suffering him to fancy, if he would, that Charles was bound either on some
     amorous pilgrimage, or some charitable mission. But they left Burleigh behind them—and got upon
     the common—and passed it by, far out of sight and out of hearing—and were skirting the high
     banks of the darkly-flowing Mullet—and still there was Julian sullenly beside him. In vain
     Charles had tried, by many gentle words, to draw him into common conversation: Julian would not
     speak, or only gave utterance to some hinted phrase of insult: his brow was even darker than
     usual, and night was coming on apace, and he still tramped steadily
     <pb n="48"/>along beside his brother, digging his sturdy stick into the clay, for very spite's
     sake. At length, as they yet walked along the river's side in that unfrequented place, Julian
     said, on a sudden, in a low strange tone, as if keeping down some rising rage within him,</p>
    <p>"Mr. Charles, you love Emily Warren."</p>
    <p>"Well, Julian, and who can help loving her?"</p>
    <p>It was innocently said; but still a maddening answer, for he loved her too.</p>
    <p>"And, sirrah," the brother hoarsely added, "she—she does not—does not—hate you, sir, as I
     do."</p>
    <p>"My good Julian, pray do not be so violent; I cannot help it if the dear girl loves me."</p>
    <p>"But I can, though!" roared Julian, with an oath, and lifted up his stick—it was nearer like
     a club—to strike his brother.</p>
    <p>"Julian, Julian, what are you about? Good Heavens! you would not—you dare not—give
     over—unhand me, brother; what have I done, that you should strike me? Oh! leave me—leave
     me—pray."</p>
    <p>"Leave you? I will leave you!" the villain almost shouted, and smote him to the ground with
     his lead-loaded stick. It was a blow that must have killed him, but for the interposing hat,
     now battered down upon his bleeding head. Charles, at length thoroughly aroused, though his foe
     must be a brother, struggled with unusual strength in self-preserving instinct, wrested the
     club from Julian's hand, and stood on the defensive.</p>
    <p>Julian was staggered: and, after a moment's irresolution, drawing a pistol from his pocket,
     said, in a terribly calm voice,</p>
    <p>"Now, sir! I have looked for such a meeting many days—alone, by night, with you! I would not
     willingly draw trigger, for the noise might bring down other folks upon us, out of Oxton
     yonder: but, drop that stick, or I fire."</p>
    <p>Charles was noble enough, without another word, to fling the club into the river: it was not
     fear of harm, but fear of sin, that made him trust himself defenceless to a brother, a
     twin-brother, in the dark: he could not be so base, a murderer, a fratricide! Oh! most
     unhallowed thought! Save him from this crime, good God! Then, instantaneously reflecting, and
     believing he decided for the best, when he saw the ruffian glaring on him with exulting looks,
     as upon an unarmed rival at his mercy, with no man near to stay the deed, and none but God to
     see it, Charles resolved to seek safety from so terrible a death in flight.</p>
    <p>Oxton was within one mile; and, clearly, this was not like flying from
     <pb n="49"/>danger as a coward, but fleeing from attempted crime, as a brother and a Christian.
     Julian snatched at him to catch him as he passed: and, failing in this, rushed after him. It
     was a race for life! and they went like the wind, for two hundred yards, along that muddy
     high-banked walk.</p>
    <p>Suddenly, Charles slipped upon the clay, that he fell; and Julian, with a savage howl, leapt
     upon him heavily.</p>
    <p>Poor youth, he knew that death was nigh, and only uttered, "God forgive you, brother! oh,
     spare me—or, if not me, spare yourself—Julian, Julian!"</p>
    <p>But the monster was determined. Exerting the whole force of his herculean frame, he seized
     his scarce-resisting victim as he lay, and, lifting him up like a child, flung his own
     twin-brother head foremost into that darkly-flowing current!</p>
    <p>There was one piercing cry—a splash—a struggle; and again nothing broke upon the silent
     night, but the murmur of that swingeing tide, as the Mullet hurried eddying to the sea.</p>
    <p>Julian listened a minute or two, flung some stones at random into the river, and then hastily
     ran back to Burleigh, feeling like a Cain.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XII.</head>
    <head>THE ESCAPE.</head>
    <p>But the overruling hand of Him whose aid that victim had invoked, was now stretched forth to
     save! and the strong-flowing tide, that ran too rapidly for Charles to sink in it, was
     commissioned from on High to carry him into an angle of that tortuous stream, where he clung by
     instinct to the bushes. Silence was his wisdom, while the murderer was near: and so long as
     Julian's footsteps echoed on the banks, Charles stirred not, spoke not, but only silently
     thanked God for his wonderful deliverance. However, the footsteps quickly died away, though
     heard far off clattering amid the still and listening night; and Charles, thankfully, no less
     than cautiously, drew himself out of the stream, very little harmed beyond a drenching: for the
     waters had recovered him at once from the effects of that desperate blow.</p>
    <p>It was with a sense of exultation, freedom, independence, that he now
     <pb n="50"/>hastened scatheless on his way; dripping garments mattered nothing, nor mud, nor
     the loss of his demolished hat: the pocket-book was safe, and Emmy's portrait, (how he kissed
     it, then!) and luckily a travelling cap was in his great-coat pocket: so with a most buoyant
     feeling of animal delight, as well as of religious gratitude, he sped merrily once more upon
     his secret expedition. Thank Heaven! Emmy could not know the peril he had past: and wretched
     Julian would now have dreadful reason of his own for this mysterious absence: and it was a
     pleasant thing to trudge along so freely in the starlight, on the private embassy of love.
     Happy Charles! I know not if ever more exhilarated feelings blessed the youth; they made him
     trip along the silent road, in a gush of joyfulness, at the rate of some six miles an hour; I
     know not if ever such delicious thoughts of Emily's attachment, and those gorgeous mysteries in
     India, of adventure, enterprise, escape, had heretofore caused his heart to bound so
     lightsomely within him, like some elastic spring. I know not if ever strong reliance upon
     Providential care, more earnest prayers, praises, intercessions (for poor Julian, too,) were
     offered on the altar of his soul. Happy Charles!</p>
    <p>So he went on and on—long past Oxton, and Eyemouth, and Surbiton, and over the ferry, and
     through the sleeping turnpikes, and past the bridge, and along the broad high-road, until gray
     of morning's dawn revealed the suburbs of Plymouth.</p>
    <p>Of course he missed the mail by which he intended to have gone—for Julian's dread act delayed
     him.</p>
    <p>Long before his journey's end, his clothes were thoroughly dried, and violent exercise had
     shaken off all possible rheumatic consequence of that fearful plunge beneath the waters:
     five-and-twenty miles in four hours and three-quarters, is a tolerable recipe for those who
     have tumbled into rivers. We must recollect that he had gone as quick as he could, for fear of
     being late, now the coach had passed. At a little country inn, he brushed, and washed, and made
     toilet as well as he was able, took a glass of good Cognac, both hot and strong; and felt more
     of a man than ever.</p>
    <p>Then, having loitered awhile, and well-remembered Emily in his prayers, at about eight in the
     morning he presented himself among his luggage at the Europe in gentlemanly trim, and soon got
     all on board the pilot boat, to meet the Indiaman just outside the breakwater. We may safely
     leave him there, happy, hopeful Charles! Sanguine for the future, exulting in the present, and
     thankful for the past: already has
     <pb n="51"/>he poured out all his joys before that Friend who loves her too, and invoked His
     blessing on a scheme so well designed, so providentially accomplished.</p>
    <p>I had almost forgotten Julian: wretched, hardened man, and how fared he? The moment he had
     flung his brother into that dark stream, and the waters closed above him greedily that he was
     gone—gone for ever, he first threw in stones to make a noise like life upon the stream, but
     that cheatery was only for an instant: he was alone—a murderer, alone! the horrors of silence,
     solitude, and guilt, seized upon him like three furies: so his quick retreating walk became a
     running; and the running soon was wild and swift for fear; and ever as he ran, that piercing
     scream came upon the wind behind, and hooted him: his head swam, his eyes saw terrible sights,
     his ears heard terrible sounds—and he scoured into quiet, sleeping Burleigh like a madman.
     However, by some strange good luck, not even did the slumbering watchman see him: so he got
     in-doors as usual with the latch-key (it was not the first time he had been out at night),
     crept up quietly, and hid himself in his own chamber.</p>
    <p>And how did he spend those hours of guilty solitude? in terrors? in remorse? in misery? Not
     he: Julian was too wise to sit and think, and in the dark too; but he lit both reading lamps to
     keep away the gloom, and smoked and drank till morning's dawn to stupify his conscience.</p>
    <p>Then, to make it seem all right, he went down to breakfast as usual, though any thing but
     sober, and met unflinchingly his mother's natural question—</p>
    <p>"Good morning, Julian—where's Charles?"</p>
    <p>"How should I know, mother; isn't he up yet?"</p>
    <p>"No, my dear; and what is more, I doubt if he came home last night."</p>
    <p>"Hollo, Master Charles! pretty doings these, Mr. Sabbath-teacher! so he slept out, eh,
     mother?"</p>
    <p>"I don't know—but where did you leave him, Julian?"</p>
    <p>"Who! I? did I go out with him? Oh! yes, now I recollect: let's see, we strolled together
     midway to Oxton, and, as he was going somewhat further, there I left him?"</p>
    <p>How true the words, and yet how terribly false their meaning!</p>
    <p>"Dear me, that's very odd—isn't it, general?"</p>
    <p>"Not at all, ma'am—not at all; leave the lad alone, he'll be back by dinner-time: I didn't
     think the boy had so much spirit."</p>
    <p>Emily, to whom the general's hint was Greek, looked up cheerfully and in her own glad mind
     chuckled at her Charles's bold adventure.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="52"/>But the day passed, off, and they sent out men to seek for him: and another—and all
     Burleigh was a-stir: and another—and the coast-guards from Lyme to Plymouth Sound searched
     every hole and corner: and another—when his mother wept five minutes: and another—when the
     wonder was forgotten.</p>
    <p>However, they did not put on mourning for the truant: he might turn up yet: perhaps he was at
     Oxford.</p>
    <p>Emily had not much to do in comforting the general for his dear son's loss; it clearly was a
     gain to him, and he felt far freer than when wisdom's eye was on him. Charles had been too keen
     for father, mother, and brother; too good, too amiable: he saw their ill, condemned it by his
     life, and showed their dark too black against his brightness. The unnatural deficiency of
     mother's love had not been overrated: Julian had all her heart; and she felt only obliged to
     the decamping Charles for leaving Emily so free and clear to his delightful brother. She never
     thought him dead: death was a repulsive notion at all times to her: no doubt he would turn up
     again some day. And Julian joked with her about that musty proverb "a bad penny."</p>
    <p>As to our dear heroine, she never felt so happy in all her life before as now, even when her
     Charles had been beside her; for within a day of his departure he had written her a note full
     of affection, hope, and gladness; assuring her of his health, and wealth, and safe arrival on
     board the Indiaman. The noble-hearted youth never said one single word about his brother's
     crime: but he did warn his Emmy to keep close beside the general. This note she got through
     Mrs. Sainsbury; that invalid lady at Oxton, who never troubled herself to ask or hear one word
     beyond her own little world—a certain physic-corner cupboard.</p>
    <p>And thou—poor miserable man—thou fratricide in mind—and to thy best belief in act, how drags
     on now the burden of thy life? For a day or two, spirits and segars muddled his brain, and so
     kept thoughts away: but within a while they came on him too piercingly, and Julian writhed
     beneath those scorpion stings of hot and keen remorse: and when the coast-guards dragged the
     Mullet, how that caitiff trembled! and when nothing could be found, how he wondered fearingly!
     The only thing the wretched man could do, was to loiter, day after day, and all day long, upon
     the same high path which skirts the tortuous stream. Fascinated there by hideous recollections,
     he could not leave the spot for hours: and his soft-headed, romantic mother, noticing these
     deep abstractions, blessed him—for her Julian was now in love with Emily.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <pb n="53"/>
    <head>CHAPTER XIII.</head>
    <head>NEWS OF CHARLES.</head>
    <p>Ay—in love with Emily! Fiercely now did Julian pour his thoughts that way; if only hoping to
     forget murder in another strong excitement. Julian listened to his mother's counsels; and that
     silly, cheated woman playfully would lean upon his arm, like a huge, coy confidante, and fill
     his greedy ears (that heard her gladly for very holiday's sake from fearful apprehensions),
     with lover's hopes, lover's themes, his Emily's perfection. Delighted mother—how proud and
     pleased was she! quite in her own element, fanning dear Julian's most sentimental flame, and
     scheming for him interviews with Emily.</p>
    <p>It required all her skill—for the girl clung closely to her guardian: he, unconscious Argus,
     never tired of her company; and she, remembering dear Charles's hint, and dreading to be left
     alone with Julian, would persist to sit day after day at her books, music, or needle-work in
     the study, charming General Tracy by her pretty Hindoo songs. With him she walked out, and with
     him she came in; she would read to him for hours, whether he snored or listened; and, really,
     both mother and son were several long weeks before their scheming could come to any thing. A
     <hi>tête-à-tête</hi> between Julian and Emily appeared as impossible to manage, as collision
     between Jupiter and Vesta.</p>
    <p>However, after some six weeks of this sort of mining and counter-mining (for Emily divined
     their wishes), all on a sudden one morning the general received a letter that demanded his
     immediate presence for a day or two in town; something about prize-money at
     Puttymuddyfudgepoor. Emily was too high-spirited, too delicate in mind, to tell her guardian of
     fears which never might be realized; and so, with some forebodings, but a cheerful trust, too,
     in a Providence above her, she saw the general off without a word, though not without a tear;
     he too, that stern, close man, was moved: it was strange to see them love each other so.</p>
    <p>The moment he was gone, she discreetly kept her chamber for the day, on plea of sickness; she
     had cried very heartily to see him leave her—he had never yet left her once since she could
     recollect—and thus she really had a head-ache, and a bad one.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="55"/>Julian Tracy gave such a start, that he knocked off a cheffonier of rare china and
     glass standing at his elbow; and the smash of mandarins and porcelain gods would have been
     enough, at any other time, to have driven his mother crazy.</p>
    <p>"Charles alive?" shouted he.</p>
    <p>"Yes, Julian—why not? You saw him off, you know: cannot you remember?"</p>
    <p>Now to that guilty wretch's mind the fearful notion instantaneously occurred, that Emily
     Warren was in some strange, wild way bantering him; she knew his dreadful secret—"he
     <hi>had</hi> seen him off." He trembled like an aspen as she looked on him.</p>
    <p>"Oh yes, he remembered, certainly; but—but where was her letter?"</p>
    <p>"Never mind that, Julian; you surely would not read another person's letters, Monsieur le
     Chevalier Bayard?"</p>
    <p>Emily was as gay at heart that morning as a sky-lark, and her innocent pleasantry proved her
     strongest shield. Julian dared not ask to see the letter—scarcely dared to hope she had one,
     and yet did not know what to think. As to any love scene now, it was quite out of the question,
     notwithstanding all his mother's hints and management; a new exciting thought entirely filled
     him: was he a Cain, a fratricide, or not? was Charles alive after all? And, for once in his
     life, Julian had some repentant feelings; for thrilling hope was nigh to cheer his gloom.</p>
    <p>It really seemed as if Emily, sweet innocent, could read his inmost thoughts. "At any rate,"
     observed she, playfully, "Bayard may take the postman's privilege, and see the outside."</p>
    <p>With that, she produced the ship-letter that had put her in such spirits, legibly dated some
     twenty-two days ago. Yes, Charles's hand, sure enough! Julian could swear to it among a
     thousand. And he fainted dead away.</p>
    <p>What an astonishing event! how Mrs. Tracy praised her noble-spirited boy! How the bells rang!
     and hot water, and cold water, and salts, and rubbings, and <hi>eau de Cologne</hi>, and all
     manner of delicate attentions, long sustained, at length contributed to Julian's restoration.
     Moreover, even Emily was agreeably surprised; she had never seen him in so amiable a light
     before; this was all feeling, all affection for his brother—her dear—dear Charles. And when
     Mrs. Tracy heard what Emily said of Julian's feeling heart, she became positively triumphant;
     not half so much at Charles's safety, and all that, as at Julian's burst of feeling. She was
     quite right, after all; he was worthy to be her favour
     <pb n="56"/>ite, and she felt both flattered and obliged to him for fainting dead away.
     "Yes—yes, my dear Miss Warren, depend upon it Julian has fine feelings, and a good heart." And
     Emily began to condemn both Charles and herself for lack of charity, and to think so too.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XIV.</head>
    <head>THE TETE-A-TETE.</head>
    <p>No sooner had "dear Julian" recovered, which he really had not quite accomplished until the
     day had begun to wear away (so great a shock had that intelligence of Charles been to his
     guilty mind), than the gratified and prudent mother fancied this a famous opportunity to leave
     the young couple to themselves. It was after dinner, when they had retired to the drawing-room;
     and I will say that Emily had never seemed so favourably disposed towards that rough, but
     generous, heart before. So then, on some significant pretence, well satisfied her favourite was
     himself again, as bold, and black, and boisterous as ever, the masculine mother kissed her hand
     to them, as a fat fairy might be supposed to do, and operatically tripped away, coyly bidding
     Emily "take care of Julian till she should come back again."</p>
    <p>The momentary gleam of good which glanced across that bad man's heart has faded away hours
     ago; his repentant thoughts had been occasioned more from the sudden relief he experienced at
     running now no risks for having murdered, than for any better feeling towards his brother, or
     any humbler notions of himself. Nay, a strong rëaction occurred in his ideas the moment he had
     seen his brother's writing; and when he fainted, he fainted from the struggle in his mind of
     manifold exciting causes, such as these:—hatred, jealousy, what he called love, though a lower
     name befitted it, and vexation that his brother was—not dead. Oh mother, mother! if your poor
     weak head had but been wise enough to read that heart, would you still have loved it as you do?
     Alas—it is a deep lesson in human nature this—she would! for Mrs. General Tracy was one of
     those obstinate, yet superficial characters, whom no reason can convince that they are wrong,
     no power can oblige to confess themselves mistaken. She rejoiced to hear him called "her
     <pb n="57"/>very image;" and predominant vanity in the large coquette extended to herself at
     second-hand; self was her idol substance, and its delightful shadow was this mother's son.</p>
    <p>The moment Mrs. Tracy left the room, Julian perceived his opportunity: Charles, detested
     rival, far away at sea; the guardian gone to London; Emily in an unusual flow of affability and
     kindness, and he—alone with her. Rashly did he bask his soul in her delicious beauty,
     deliberately drinking deep of that intoxicating draught. Giving the rein to passion, he
     suffered that tumultuous steed to hurry him whither it would, in mad unbridled course. He sat
     so long silently gazing at her with the lack-lustre eyes of low and dull desire, that Emily,
     quite thrown off her guard by that amiable fainting for his brother, addressed him in her
     innocent kind-heartedness,</p>
    <p>"Are you not recovered yet, dear Julian?"</p>
    <p>The effect was instantaneous: scarcely crediting his ears that heard her call him "dear," his
     eyes, that saw her winning smile upon him, he started from his chair, and trembling with
     agitation, flung himself at her feet, to Emily's unqualified astonishment.</p>
    <p>"Why, Julian, what's the matter?—unhand me, sir! let go!" (for he had got hold of her
     wrist.)</p>
    <p>The passionate youth seized her hand—that one with Charles's ring upon it—and would have
     kissed it wildly with polluting lips, had she not shrieked suddenly "Help! help!"</p>
    <p>Instantly his other hand was roughly dashed upon her mouth—so roughly that it almost knocked
     her backwards—and the blood flowed from her wounded lip; but by a preternatural effort, the
     indignant Indian queen hurled the ruffian from her, flew to the bell, and kept on ringing
     violently.</p>
    <p>In less than half a minute all the household was around her, headed by the startled Mrs.
     Tracy, who had all the while been listening in the other drawing-room: butler, footmen,
     house-maids, ladies'-maids, cook, scullions, and all rushed in, thinking the house was on
     fire.</p>
    <p>No need to explain by a word. Emily, radiant in imperial charms, stood, like inspired
     Cassandra, flashing indignation from her eyes at the cowering caitiff on the floor. The mother,
     turning all manner of colours, dropped on her knees to "poor Julian's" assistance, affecting to
     believe him taken ill. But Emily Warren, whose insulted pride vouchsafed not a word to that
     guilty couple, soon undeceived all parties, by addressing the butler in a voice tremulous and
     broken—</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="58"/>"Mr. Saunders—be so good—as to go—to Sir Abraham Tamworth's—in the square—and
     request of him—a night's—protection—for a poor—defenceless, insulted woman!"</p>
    <p>She could hardly utter the last words for choking tears: but immediately battling down her
     feelings, added, with the calmness of a heroine—</p>
    <p>"You are a father, Mr. Saunders—set all this before Sir Abraham strongly, but delicately.</p>
    <p>"Footmen! so long as that wretch is in the room, protect me, as you are men."</p>
    <p>And the stately beauty placed herself between the two liveried lacqueys, as Zenobia in the
     middle of her guards.</p>
    <p>"Marguerite!"—the pretty little Française tripped up to her—"wipe this blood from my
     face."</p>
    <p>Beautiful, insulted creature! I thought that I looked upon some wounded Boadicea, with her
     daughters extracting the arrow from her cheek.</p>
    <p>"And now, kind Charlotte, fetch my cloak; and follow me to Prospect House, with what I may
     require for the night. Till the general's return, I stay not here one minute."</p>
    <p>Then, without a syllable, or a look of leave-taking, the wise and noble girl—doubtless
     unconsciously remembering her early Hindoo braveries, the lines of matchlock men, the bowing
     slaves, the processions, and her jewelled state of old—marched away in magnificent beauty,
     accompanied in silence by the whole astonished household.</p>
    <p>Mrs. Tracy and her son were left alone: the silly, silly mother thought him "hardly used."
     Julian, whose natural effrontery had entirely deserted him, looked like what he was—a guilty
     coward: and the mother, who had pampered up her "fine high-spirited son" to his full-grown
     criminality by a foolish education, really—when she had time to think of any thing but him—was
     excessively frightened. The general would be back to-morrow, and then—and then!—she dreaded to
     picture that explosion of his wrath.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <pb n="59"/>
    <head>CHAPTER XV.</head>
    <head>SATISFACTION.</head>
    <p>Sir Abraham Tamworth, G.C.B.—a fine old Admiral of the White, who somewhat looked down upon
     the rank of General, H.E.I.C.S.—was astonished, as well he might be, at Mr. Saunders, and his
     message: and, of course, most gladly acquiesced in acting as poor Emily's protector.
     Accordingly, however jealous Lady Tamworth and her daughters might heretofore have felt of that
     bright beauty at the balls, they were now all genuine sympathy, indignation, and affection.
     Emily, I need hardly say, went straight up stairs to have her cry out.</p>
    <p>"Whom are you writing to, George, in such a hurry?" asked the admiral, of a fine moustachioed
     son, George St. Vincent Tamworth, of the Royal Horse Guards, who had just got six months' leave
     of absence for the sake of marriage with his cousin.</p>
    <p>The gallant soldier tossed a billet to his father, who mounted his spectacles, and quietly
     read it at the lamp.</p>
    <p>"Captain Tamworth desires Mr. Julian Tracy's company to-morrow morning, at seven o'clock, in
     the third meadow on the Oxton road. The captain brings a friend with him; also pistols and a
     surgeon; and he desires Mr. Tracy to do the like: Prospect House, Thursday evening."</p>
    <p>"So, George, you consider him a gentleman, do you? I am afraid it's a poor compliment to our
     fair young friend." And he quietly crumpled up the challenge in his iron hand.</p>
    <p>"Really, sir!—you surprise me;—pardon me, but I will send that note: mustn't I chastise the
     fellow for this insufferable outrage?"</p>
    <p>"No doubt, George, no doubt of it at all: when a lady is insulted, and a man (not to say a
     queen's officer) stands by without taking notice of it, he deserves whipping at the
     cart's-tail, and Coventry for life. I've no patience, boy, with such mean meekness, as putting
     up with bullying insolence when a woman's in the case. Let a man show moral courage, if he can
     and will, in his own affront; I honour him who turns on his heel from common personal insult,
     and only wish my own old blood was cool enough to do so: but the mother, wife, and sister, ay,
     George, and the poor defenceless one, be she lady, peasant, or menial, who comes to us for
     safety in a woman's dress, we must take up their quarrel, or we are not men!—"</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="60"/>"Don't interrupt him, George," uxoriously suggested Lady Tamworth, "your father
     hasn't done talking yet." For George was getting terribly impatient; he knew, from sad
     experience, how much the admiral was given to prosing. However, the oration soon proceeded to
     our captain's entire satisfaction, after his progenitor had paused awhile for breath's sake in
     his eloquence.</p>
    <p>"—Take up their quarrel, or we are not men. Nevertheless, boy, I cannot see the need of
     pistols. The only conceivable case for violent redress, is woman's wrong: and he who wrongs a
     woman, cannot be a gentleman; therefore, ought not to be met on equal terms. For other causes
     of duello, as hot-headed speeches, rudenesses, or slights, forgive, forbear to fan the flame,
     and never be above apologizing: but in an outrage such as this, let a fine-built fellow, such
     as you are, George (and the women should show wisdom in their choice of champions), let a man,
     and a queen's officer as you are, treat this brute, Julian Tracy, as a martinet huntsman would
     a hound thrown out. As for me, boy, I'm going to call on Mrs. Tracy at eleven o'clock to-morrow
     morning—and, without presuming to advise a six foot two of a son, I think—I think, if I were
     you, I would be dutiful enough to say—'Father, I will accompany you—and take a horsewhip with
     me.'"</p>
    <p>"Agreed, agreed, sir!" replied the well-pleased son, and her ladyship too vouchsafed her
     approbation.</p>
    <p>Emily had gone to bed long ago, or rather to her chamber; where the three Misses Tamworth had
     been all kindness, curiosity, and consolation. So, Sir Abraham and his lady, now the speech was
     finished, followed their example of retirement: and the captain newly blood-knotted his
     hunting-whip, <hi>con amore</hi>, not to say <hi>con spirito</hi>, overnight.</p>
    <p>Nobody will wonder to hear, that when the gallant representatives of army and navy called
     next morning at number seven, Mrs. Tracy and her son were "not at home:" and of course it would
     be far too Julian-like a proceeding, for true gentleman to think of forcing their company on
     the probably ensconced in-dwellers. Accordingly, they marched away, without having deigned to
     leave a card; the captain taking on himself the duty of perambulating sentinel, while his
     father proceeded to the library as usual. Judge of the glad surprise, when, within ten minutes,
     our vindictive George perceived the admiral coming back again, full-sail, with the mother and
     son in tow, creeping amicably enough up the terrace. Sir Abraham had given her his arm, and
     precious Mr. Julian was a little in the rear: for the old folks were talking
     confidentially.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="61"/>George St. Vincent, placing his whip in the well-known position of "Cane, a
     mystery," advanced to meet them; and, just after passing his father, with whom he exchanged a
     very comfortable glance, discovered that the heroic Julian, who had caught a glimpse of the
     ill-concealed weapon, was slinking quickly round a corner to avoid him. It was certainly
     undignified to run, but the gallant captain did run, nevertheless and soon caught the coward by
     the collar.</p>
    <p>Then, at arm's length, was the hunting-whip applied, full-swing; up the terrace, and down the
     parade, and through High-street, and Smith-street, and Oxton-road, and aristocratical
     Pacton-square, and the well-thronged plebeian market-place; lash, lash, lash, in furious and
     fast succession on the writhing roaring culprit; to the universal excoriation of Mr. Julian
     Tracy, and the amazement of an admiring and soon-collected crowd—the rank, beauty, and
     fashion—of Burleigh Singleton. Julian was strong indeed, and a coal-heaver in build, but
     conscience had unnerved him; and the coarse noisy bully always is a coward: therefore, it was a
     pleasant thing to see how easy came the captain's work to him—he had nothing to do but to lash,
     lash, lash, double-thonged, like a slave-driver: and, except that he made the caitiff move
     along, to be a spectacle to man and woman, up and down the town, he might as well, for any
     difficulty in the deed, have been employed in scarifying a gate-post.</p>
    <p>At last, thoroughly exhausted with having inflicted as much punishment as any three drummers
     at a soldier's whipping-match, and spying out his "tiger" in the throng, our gallant Avenging
     Childe tossed the heavy whip to the trim cockaded little man, that he might carry home that
     instrument of vengeance, deliberately wiped his wet mustachios, and giving Julian one last
     kick, let the fellow part in peace.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XVI.</head>
    <head>HOW CHARLES FARED.</head>
    <p>Having thus found protectors for poor Emily, and disposed of her assailant to the entire
     satisfaction of all mankind, let us turn seawards, and take a look at Charles.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="62"/>Now, "no earthly power,"—as a certain ex-chancellor protested—shall induce me to do
     so mean a thing as to open Charles's letters, and spread them forth before the public gaze.
     Doubtless, they were all things tender, warm, and eloquent; doubtless, they were tinted rosy
     hue, with love's own blushes, and made glorious with the golden light of unaffected piety. I
     only read them myself in a reflected way, by looking into Emily's eyes; and I saw, from their
     ever-changing radiance, how feelingly he told of his affections; how fervently he poured out
     all his heart upon the page; how evidently tears and kisses had made many words illegible; how
     wise, sanguine, happy, and religious, was her own devoted Charles.</p>
    <p>Of the trivial incidents of voyaging, his letters said not much: though cheerful and
     agreeable in his floating prison, with the various exported marrying-maidens and transported
     civil officers, who constitute the average bulk of Indian cargoes outward bound, Charles mixed
     but little in their society, seldom danced, seldom smoked, seldom took a hand at whist, or
     engaged in the conflicts of backgammon. Sharks, storms, water-spouts; the meeting divers
     vessels, and exchanging post-bags; tar-barrelled Neptune of the line, Cape Town with its
     mountain and the Table-cloth, long-rolling seas; and similar common-places, Charles did not
     think proper to enlarge upon: no more do I. Life is far too short for all such petty details:
     and, more pointedly, a wire-drawn book is the just abhorrence of a generous public.</p>
    <p>The letters came frequently: for Charles did little else all day but write to Emmy, so as
     always to be ready with a budget for the next piece of luck—a home-bound ship. He had many
     things to teach her yet, sweet student; and it was a beautiful sight to see how her mind
     expanded as an opening flower before the sun of tenderness and wisdom. Each letter, both in
     writing and in reading, was the child of many prayers: and even the loveliness of Emily grew
     more soft, more elevated, "as it had been the face of an angel," when feeding in solitary joy
     on those effusions of her lover's heart.</p>
    <p>Of course, he could not hear from her, until the overland mail might haply bring him letters
     at Madras: so that, as our Irish friends would say, with all her will to tell him of her love,
     "the reciprocity must needs be all on one side." But Emily did write too; earnestly, happily:
     and poured her very heart out in those eloquent burning words. I dare say Charles will get the
     letter now within a day or two: for the roaring surf of Madras is on the horizon, almost within
     sight.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="63"/>Nevertheless, before he gets there, and can read those letters—precious, precious
     manuscripts—it will be my painful duty, as a chronicler of (what might well be) truth, to put
     the reader in possession of one little hint, which seemed likeliest to wreck the happiness of
     these two children of affection.</p>
    <p>I am Emily's invisible friend: and as the dear girl ran to me one morning, with tears in her
     eyes, to ask me what I thought of a certain mysterious paragraph, I need not scruple to lay it
     straight before the reader.</p>
    <p>At the end of a voluminous love-letter, which I really did not think of prying into, occurred
     the following postscript, evidently written at the last moment of haste.</p>
    <p>"Oh! my precious Emmy, I have just heard the most fearful rumour of ill that could possibly
     befall us: the captain of our ship—you will remember Captain Forbes, he knew you and the
     general well, he said—has just assured me that—that—! I dare not, cannot write the awful words.
     Oh! my own Emmy—Heaven grant you be my own!—pray, pray, as I will night and day, that rumour be
     not true: for if it be, my love, both God and man forbid us ever to meet again! How I wish I
     could explain it all, or that I had never heard so much, or never written it here, and told it
     you, though thus obscurely: for I can't destroy this letter now, the ships are just parting
     company, and there is no time to write another. Yet will I hope, love, against hope. Who knows?
     through God's good mercy, it may all be cleared up still. If not—if not—strive to forget for
     ever, your unhappy</p>
    <p>"<hi>Charles.</hi></p>
    <p>"Perhaps—O, glorious thought!—Nurse Mackie may know better than the captain, after all; and
     yet, he seems so positive: if he is right, there is nothing for us both but Wo! Wo! Wo!"</p>
    <p>Now, to say plain truth, when Emily showed me this, I looked very blank upon it. That Charles
     had heard some meddlesome report, which (if true) was to be an insuperable barrier to their
     future union, struck me at a glimpse. But I had not the heart to hint it to her; and only
     encouraged hope—hope, in God's help, through the means of Mrs. Mackie and her papers.</p>
    <p>As for the poor girl herself, she asked me, in much humility, and with many sobs, if I did
     not fear that her Hindoo mystery was this:—she was the vilest of the vile, a Pariah, an
     outcast, whose very presence is contamination!</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="64"/>Beautiful, loving, heavenly-hearted creature! so humble in the midst of her
     majestic loveliness! how touching was the thought, that she thus readily acquiesced in any the
     deepest humiliation holy Providence had seen fit to send her; and though the sentence would
     have crushed her happiness for ever, till the day of death, that she could still look up and
     say, "Be it to thine handmaid even as thou wilt."</p>
    <p>As I had no better method of explaining the matter, and as her infantine reminiscences and
     prejudices about caste were strong, I even let her think so, if she would: it was a far better
     alternative than my own sad thoughts about the business: and, however painful was the process,
     it was something consolatory to observe, that this voluntary humiliation mellowed and chastened
     her own character, subduing tropical fires, and tempering the virgin gold by meekness.</p>
    <p>Oh! Charles, Charles, my poor fellow, "who have cast your all upon a die, and must abide the
     issue of the throw," I most fervently hope that gossiping Captain Forbes spoke falsely: it is a
     comfort to reflect that the world is often very liberal in attributing the honours of paternity
     to some who really do not deserve them. And if a rich old bachelor looks kindly on a foundling,
     is it not pure malice on that sole account of charity to hail him father? Besides—there's Nurse
     Mackie.—Speed to Madras, poor youth, and keep your courage up.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XVII.</head>
    <head>THE GENERAL'S RETURN.</head>
    <p>In a most unwonted flow of animal spirits, and an entire affability which restored him at
     once to the rank of a communicative creature, General Tracy came back on Friday night. He had
     met with marvellous prosperity; for Hancock's had been paying off the prize-money; and his own
     lion's share, as general, in the easy process of dethroning half a dozen diamond-hilted rajahs
     and nabobs, amounted to something like four lacs of rupees, nearly half a crore! Such a flush
     of wealth, and he was rich already without it, exhilarated the bilious old gentleman so
     strangely, that positive peonies were blooming in his cheeks; and, as if this was not miracle
     enough, he had brought his wife as a
     <pb n="65"/>present Maurice's '<hi>Antiquities of India</hi>,' gloriously bound, and had even
     been so superfluous as to purchase a new pair of double-barrelled pistols for Julian: the lad
     was a fine young fellow after all, and ought to be encouraged in snuffing out a candle; as for
     Emily's <hi>petit cadeau</hi>, it was a fifty guinea set of cameos, the choicest in their way
     that Howell and James's had to show him. Moreover, he had sent a Bow-street officer to Oxford,
     to make inquiries after Charles: actually, good fortune had made him at once humanized and
     happy.</p>
    <p>So the chaise rattled up, and the general bounded out, and flew into the arms of his
     wondering wife, as Paris might have flown to Helen, or Leander to his heroine—the only feminine
     Hero, whom grammar recognises. It was past eleven at night: therefore he did not think to ask
     for Julian; no doubt the boy was gone to bed.</p>
    <p>Indeed, he had; and was tossing his wealed body, full of pains, and aches, and bruises, as
     softly as he could upon the feather-bed: he had need of poultices all over, and a quart of
     Friar's Balsam would have done him little good: after his well-merited thrashing, the flogged
     hound had slunk to his kennel, and locked himself sullenly in, without even speaking to his
     mother. Tobacco-fumes exuded from the key-hole, and I doubt not other creature-comforts lent
     the muddled man their aid.</p>
    <p>However, after the first rush of news to Mrs. Tracy, her lord, who had every moment been
     expecting the door to fly open, and Emily to fall into his arms—for strangely did they love
     each other—suddenly asked,</p>
    <p>"But, where's Emmy all this time! she knows I'm here?—not got to bed, is she?—knew I was
     coming?—"</p>
    <p>"Oh! general, I'll tell you all about it to-morrow morning."</p>
    <p>"About what, madam? Great God! has any harm befallen the child? Speak—speak, woman!"</p>
    <p>"Dear—dear—Oh! what shall I say?" sobbed the silly mother. "Emily—Emily, poor dear
     Julian—"</p>
    <p>"What the devil, ma'am, of Julian?" The general turned white as a sheet, and rang the bell,
     in singular calmness; probably for a dram of brandy. Saunders answered it so instantly, that I
     rather suspect he was waiting just outside.</p>
    <p>The moment Mrs. Tracy saw the gray-headed butler, anticipating all that he might say, she
     brushed past him, and hurriedly ran up-stairs.</p>
    <p>"What's all this, Mr. Saunders? where's Miss Warren?" And the poor old guardian seemed ready
     to faint at his reply: but he heard it out patiently.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="66"/>"I am very sorry to say, general, that Miss Emily has been forced to take refuge at
     Sir Abraham Tamworth's: but she's well, sir, and safe, sir; quite well and safe," the good man
     hastened to say, "only I'm afraid that Mr. Julian had been taking liberties with—"</p>
    <p>I dare not write the general's imprecation: then, as he clenched the arms of his easy-chair,
     as with the grasp of the dying, he asked, in a quick wild way—</p>
    <p>"But what was it?—what happened?"</p>
    <p>"Nothing to fear, sir—nothing at all, general;—I am thankful to say, that all I saw, and all
     we all saw, was Miss Emily pulling at the bell-rope with blood upon her face, and Mr. Julian on
     the floor: but I took the young lady to Sir Abraham's immediately, general, at her own
     desire."</p>
    <p>The father arose sternly; his first feeling was to kill Julian; but the second, a far better
     one, predominated—he must go and see Emily at once.</p>
    <p>So, faintly leaning on the butler's arm, the poor old man (whom a moiety of ten minutes, with
     its crowding fears, had made to look some ten years older,) proceeded to the square, and
     knocked up Sir Abraham at midnight, and the admiral came down, half asleep, in dressing-gown
     and slippers, vexed at having been knocked up from his warm berth so uncomfortably: it put him
     sorely in remembrance of his hardships as a middy.</p>
    <p>"Kind neighbour, thank you, thank you; where's Emmy? take me to my Emmy;" and the
     iron-hearted veteran wept like a driveller.</p>
    <p>Sir Abraham looked at him queerly: and then, in a cheerful, friendly way, replied—</p>
    <p>"Dear general, do not be so moved: the girl's quite safe with us; you'll see her to-morrow
     morning. All's right; she was only frightened, and George has given the fellow a proper good
     licking: and the girl's a-bed, you know; and, eh? what?"—</p>
    <p>For the poor old man, like one bereaved, said, supplicatingly—</p>
    <p>"In mercy take me to her—precious child!"</p>
    <p>"My dear sir—pray consider—it's impossible; fine girl, you know;—Lady Tamworth, too—can't be,
     can't be, you know, general."</p>
    <p>And the mystified Sir Abraham looked to Saunders for an explanation—</p>
    <p>"Was his master drunk?"</p>
    <p>"I must speak to her, neighbour; I must, must, and will—dear, dear child: come up with me,
     sir, come; do not trifle with a breaking heart, neighbour!"</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="67"/>There was a heart still in that hard-baked old East Indian.</p>
    <p>It was impossible to resist such an appeal: so the two elders crept up stairs, and knocked
     softly at her chamber-door. Clearly, the girl was asleep: she had sobbed herself to sleep; the
     general had been looked for all day long, and she was worn with watching; he could hardly come
     at midnight; so the dear affectionate child had sobbed herself to sleep.</p>
    <p>"Allow me, Sir Abraham." And General Tracy whispered something at the key-hole in a strange
     tongue.</p>
    <p>Not Aladdin's "open Sesame" could have been more magical. In a moment, roused up suddenly
     from sleep, and forgetting every thing but those tender recollections of gentle care in
     infancy, and kindness all through life, the child of nature startled out of bed, drew the bolt,
     and in beauteous disarray, fell into that old man's arms!</p>
    <p>It was enough; he had seen her eye to eye—she lived: and the white-haired veteran, suffered
     himself to be led away directly from the landing, like a child, by his sympathizing
     neighbour.</p>
    <p>"My heart is lighter now, Sir Abraham: but I am a poor weak old man, and owe you an
     explanation for this outburst; some day—some day, not now. O, if you could guess how I have
     nursed that pretty babe when alone in distant lands; how I have doated on her little winning
     ways, and been gladdened by the music of her prattle; how I have exulted to behold her
     loveliness gradually expanding, as she was ever at my side, in peril as in peace, in camp as in
     quarters, in sickness as in health, still—still, the blessed angel of a bad man's life—a
     wicked, hard old man, kind neighbour—if you knew more—more, than for her sake I dare tell
     you—and if you could conceive the love my Emmy bears for me, you would not think it
     strange—think it strange—" He could not say a syllable more; and the admiral, with Mr.
     Saunders, too, who joined them in the study, looked very little able to console that poor old
     man. For they all had hearts, and trickling eyes to tell them.</p>
    <p>Then having arranged a shake-down for his master in Sir Abraham's study—for the guardian
     would not leave his dear one ever again—Saunders went home, purposing to attend with razors in
     the morning.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <pb n="68"/>
    <head>CHAPTER XVIII.</head>
    <head>INTERCALARY.</head>
    <p>The Tamworths did not altogether live at Burleigh Singleton—it was far too petty a place for
     them; dullness all the year round (however pleasant for a month or so, as a holiday from
     toilsome pleasures) would never have done for Lady Tamworth and her daughters: but they
     regularly took Prospect House for six weeks in the summer season, when tired of Portland Place,
     and Huntover, their fine estate in Cheshire: and so, from constant annual immigration, came as
     much to be regarded Burleighites, as swifts and swallows to be ranked as British birds. I only
     hint at this piece of information, for fear any should think it unlikely, that grandees of Sir
     Abraham's condition could exist for ever in a place where the day-before-yesterday's
     '<hi>Times</hi>' is first intelligence.</p>
    <p>Moreover, as another interjectional touch, it is only due to my life-likenesses to record,
     that Mrs. Green's, although a terrace-house, and ranked as humble number seven, was,
     nevertheless, a tolerably spacious mansion, well suited for the dignity of a butler to repose
     in: for Mrs. Green had added an entire dwelling on the inland side, as, like most maritime
     inhabitants, she was thoroughly sick of the sea, and never cared to look at it, though living
     there still, from mere disinclination to stir: so, then, it was quite a double house, both
     spacious and convenient. As for the inglorious incident of Julian's latch-key, I should not
     wonder if many wide street-doors to many marble halls are conscious of similar convenient
     fastenings, if gentlemen of Julian's nocturnal tastes happen to be therein dwelling. Another
     little matter is worth one word. The house had been Mrs. Green's, a freehold, and was,
     therefore, now her heir's; but the general, as an executor, remained there still, until his
     business was finished; in fact, he took his year's liberty.</p>
    <p>He had returned from India rolling in gold; for some great princess or other—I think they
     called her a Begum or a Glumdrum, or other such like Gulliverian appellative—had been
     singularly fond of him, and had loaded him in early life with favours—not only kisses, and so
     forth, but jewellery and gold pagodas. And lately, as we know, Puttymuddyfudgepoor, with its
     radiating rajahs and nabobs, had proved a mine of wealth: for a crore is ten lacs, and a lac of
     rupees is any thing but a
     <pb n="69"/>lack of money—although rupees be money, and the "middle is distributed;" in spite
     of logic, then, a lack means about twelve thousand pounds: and four of them, according to
     Cocker, some fifty thousand. It would appear then, that with the produce of the Begum's
     diamonds, converted into money long ago, and some of them as big as linnet's eggs—and not to
     take account of Mrs. Green's trifling pinch of the five Exchequer bills, all handed over at
     once to Emily—the General's present fortune was exactly one hundred and twenty-three thousand
     pounds.</p>
    <p>Of course, <hi>he</hi> wasn't going to bury himself at Burleigh Singleton much longer; and
     yet, for all that stout intention of houses and lands, and carriages and horses, in almost any
     other county or country, it is as true as any thing in this book, that he was a resident still,
     a lease-holder of Aunt Green's house, long after the <hi>dénouement</hi> of this story; in many
     things an altered man, but still identical in one; the unchangeable resolve (though never to be
     executed) of leaving Burleigh at farthest by next Michaelmas. Most folks who talk much, do
     little; and taciturn as the general now is, and has been ever throughout life, it will surprise
     nobody who has learned from hard experience how silly and harmful a thing is secresy
     (exceptionables excepted), to find that he grew to be a garrulous old man, gossipping for ever
     of past, present, future, and, not least, about his deeds at Puttymuddyfudgepoor.</p>
    <p>General Tracy is by this time awake again; if ever indeed he slept on that uncomfortable
     shakedown; and, after Mr. Saunders and the razor-strop, has greeted brightly-beaming Emily with
     more than usual tenderness. Her account of the transaction made his very blood boil; especially
     as her pretty pouting lips were lacerated cruelly inside: that rude blow on the mouth had
     almost driven the teeth through them. How confidingly she told her artless tale; how gently did
     her fond protector kiss that poor pale cheek; and how sternly did he vow full vengeance on the
     caitiff! Not even Emily's intercession could avail to turn his wrath aside. He could hardly
     help flying off at once to do something dreadful; but common courtesy to all the Tamworth
     family obliged him to defer for an hour all the terrible things he meant to do. So he began to
     bolt his breakfast fiercely as a cannibal, and saluted Lady Tamworth and her daughters with
     such savage looks, that the captain considerately suggested:</p>
    <p>"Here, general," (handing him a most formidable carving-knife,) "charge that boar's head,
     grinning defiance at us on the side-board; it will do you good to hew his brawny neck. My
     mother, I am sure, for
     <pb n="70"/>one, will thank you to do the honours there instead of me. Isn't it a comfort now,
     to know that I broke the handle of my hunting-whip across the fellow's back, and wore all the
     whip-cord into skeins. Come, I say, general, don't eat us all round; and pray have mercy on
     that poor, flogged, miserable sinner."</p>
    <p>This banter did him good, especially as he saw Emily smiling; so he relaxed his knit brow,
     condescended to look less like Giant Blunderbore, soon became marvellous chatty, and ate up two
     French rolls, an egg, some anchovies, a round of toast, and a mighty slice of brawn; these,
     washed down with a couple of cups of tea, soothed him into something like complacency.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XIX.</head>
    <head>JULIAN'S DEPARTURE.</head>
    <p>Long before the general got home, still in exalted dudgeon (indeed soon after the general had
     left home over night), the bird had flown; for the better part of valour suggested to our evil
     hero, that it would be discreet to render himself a scarce commodity for a season; and as soon
     as ever his mother had run up to his room-door to tell him of his danger, when her lord was
     cross-questioning the butler, he resolved upon instant flight. Accordingly, though sore and
     stiff, he hurried up, dressed again, watched his father out, and tumbling over Mrs. Tracy, who
     was sobbing on the stairs, ran for one moment to the general's room; there he seized a
     well-remembered cash-box, and instinctively possessed himself of those new, neat,
     double-barrelled pistols: a bully never goes unarmed. These brief arrangements made, off he
     set, before his father could have time to return from Pacton Square.</p>
    <p>Therefore, when the general called, we need not marvel that he found him not; no one but the
     foolish mother (so neglected of her son, yet still excusing him) stood by to meet his wrath. He
     would not waste it on her; so long as Julian was gone, his errand seemed accomplished; for all
     he came to do was to expel him from the house. So, as far as regarded Mrs. Tracy, her husband,
     wotting well how much she was to blame, merely commanded her to change her sleeping-room, and
     occupy Mr. Julian's in future.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="71"/>The silly woman was even glad to do it; and comforted herself from time to time
     with prying into her own boy's exemplary manuscripts, memoranda of moralities, and so forth;
     with weeping, like Lady Constance, over his empty "unpuffed" clothes; with reading ever and
     anon his choice collection of standard works, among which '<hi>Don Juan</hi>' and Mr. Thomas
     Paine were by far the most presentable; and with tasting, till it grew to be a habit, his
     private store of spirituous liquors. Thus did she mourn many days for long-lost Julian.</p>
    <p>I am quite aware what became of him. The wretched youth, mad for Emily's love, and tortured
     by the tyranny of passion, had nothing else to live for or to die for. He accordingly took
     refuge in the hovel of a smuggler, an old friend of his, not many miles away, disguised himself
     in fisherman's costume, and bode his opportunity.</p>
    <p>Beauteous girl! how often have I watched thee with straining eyes and aching heart, as thou
     wentest on thy summer's walk so oftentimes to Oxton, there to exercise thy bountiful
     benevolence in comforting the sick, gladdening the wretched, and lingering, with love's own
     look, in Charles's village school; how often have I prayed, that guardian angels might be about
     thy path as about thy bed! For the prowling tiger was on thy track, poor innocent one, and
     many, many times nothing but one of God's seeming accidents hath saved thee. Who was that
     strange man so often in the way? At one time a wounded Spanish legionist, with head bound up;
     at another, an old beggar upon crutches; at another, a floury miller with a donkey and a sack;
     at another, a black looking man, in slouching sailor's hat and fishing-boots?</p>
    <p>Fair, pure creature! thou hast often dropped a shilling in that beggar's hand, and pitied
     that poor maimed soldier; once, too, a huge gipsy woman would have had thee step aside, and
     hear thy fortunes. Heaven guarded thee then, sweet Emily; for both girl and lover though thou
     art, thou would'st not listen to the serpent's voice, however fair might be the promises. And
     Heaven guarded thee ever, bidding some one pass along the path just as the ruffian might have
     gagged thy smiling mouth, and hurried thee away amongst his fellows; and more than once,
     especially, those school children, bursting out of Charles's school at dusk, have unconsciously
     escorted thee in safety from the perils of that tiger on thy track.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <pb n="72"/>
    <head>CHAPTER XX.</head>
    <head>ENLIGHTENMENT.</head>
    <p>The general could not now be kept in ignorance of Charles's expedition; in fact, he had found
     his heart, and began resolutely to use it. So, the very day on which he had lost Julian, he
     intended very eagerly to seek out Charles; for the Oxford search had failed, and no wonder.
     Now, though Emily had told, as we well know, to both mother and son her secret, the father was
     not likely to be any the wiser; for he now never spoke to his wife, and could not well speak to
     his son. However, one day, an hour after an overland letter, a very exhilarating one, dated
     Madras, whereof we shall hear anon, fair Emily, in the fullness of her heart, could not help
     saying,</p>
    <p>"Dearest sir, you are often thinking of poor lost Charles, I know; and you are very anxious
     about him too, though nobody but myself, who am always with you, can perceive it: what if you
     heard he was safe and well?"</p>
    <p>"Have you heard any tidings of my poor boy, Emmy?"</p>
    <p>She looked up archly, and said, "Why not?" her beautiful eyes adding, as plainly as eyes
     could speak, "I love him, and you know it; of course I have heard frequently from dear, dear
     Charles."</p>
    <p>But the guardian met her looks with a keen and chilling answer: "Why not! why not! Does he
     dare to write to you, and you to love him? Oh, that I had told them both a year ago! But where
     is he now, child? Don't cry, I will not speak so angrily again, my Emmy."</p>
    <p>"I hardly dare to tell you, dearest sir: you have always been as a father to me, and I never
     knew any other; but there are things I cannot explain to myself, and I was very wretched; and
     so, kind guardian, Charles—Charles was so good—"</p>
    <p>"What has he done?—where has he gone?" hastily asked his father.</p>
    <p>"Oh, don't, don't be angry with us; in a word, he is gone to Madras, to find out Nurse
     Mackie, and to tell me who I am."</p>
    <p>The poor old man, who had treasured up so long some mystery, probably a very diaphanous one,
     for Emily's own dear sake in the world's esteem, and from the long bad habit of reserve, fell
     back into his chair as if he had been shot; but he did not faint, nor gasp, nor utter a sound;
     he only looked at her so long and sorrowfully, that she ran to him, and covered his pale face
     with her own brown curls, kissing him, and wiping from his cheek her starting tears.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="73"/>"Emmy, dear—I can tell you—and I—no, no, not now, not now; if he comes
     back—then—then; poor children! Oh, the sin of secresy!"</p>
    <p>"But, dearest sir, do not be so sad; Charles has happy news, he says."</p>
    <p>"Happy, child? Good Heaven! would it could be so!"</p>
    <p>"Indeed, indeed, a week ago he was as miserable as any could be, and so was I; for he heard
     something terrible about me—I don't know what—but I feared I was a—Pariah! However, now he is
     all joy, and coming home again as soon as possible."</p>
    <p>The general shook, his head mournfully, as physicians do when hope is gone; but still he
     looked perplexed and thoughtful.</p>
    <p>"You will show me the letters, dear, I dare say: but I do not command you, Emmy; do as you
     like."</p>
    <p>"Certainly, my own kindest guardian—all, all, and instantly."</p>
    <p>And flying up to her room, she returned with as much closely-written manuscript as would have
     taken any but a lover's eye a full week to decipher. The general, not much given to literary
     matters, looked quite scared at such a prospect.</p>
    <p>"Wait, Emmy; not all, not all; show me the last."</p>
    <p>I dare say Emily will forgive me if I get it set up legibly in print. May I, dear?</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XXI.</head>
    <head>CHARLES AT MADRAS.</head>
    <p>Luckily enough for all mankind in general, and our lovers in particular, Charles's last
     letter was very unlike some that had preceded it; for instead of the usual "Oh, my love"'s,
     "sweet, sweet eyes," "darling"'s, and all manner of such chicken-hearted nonsense, it was
     positively sensible, rational, not to say utilitarian: though I must acknowledge that here and
     there it degenerates into the affectionate, or Stromboli-vein of letter-writing, at opening
     especially; and really now and then I shall take leave to indicate omitted inflammations by a
     *.</p>
    <p>"<hi>Dearest, Dearest Emmy</hi>,</p>
    <p>* * * * * * * *</p>
    <p>[and so forth, a very galaxy of stars to the bottom of this page; enough to put the
     compositor out of his terrestrial senses.]</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="74"/>"You see I have recovered my spirits, dearest, and am not now afraid to tell you
     how I love you. Oh, that detestable Captain Forbes! let him not cross my path, gossiping
     blockhead! on pain of carrying about 'til deth,' in the middle of his face, a nose two inches
     longer. I heartily wish I had never listened for an instant to such vile insinuations; and when
     I look at this red right hand of mine, that dared to pen the trash in that black postscript, I
     look at it as Cranmer did, and (but that it is yours, Emmy, not mine), could wish it burnt. But
     no fears now, my girl, huzza, huzza! I believe every one about me thinks me daft; and so I am
     for very joyfulness; notwithstanding, let me be didactic, or you will say so too. I really will
     endeavour to rein in, and go along in the regular hackney trot, that you may partly comprehend
     me. Well, then, here goes; try your paces, Dobbin.</p>
    <p>"On the morning of Sunday, April 11th, 1842, the good ship Elphinston—(that's the way to
     begin, I suppose, as per ledger, log-book, and midshipman's epistles to mamma)—in fact, dear,
     we cast anchor just outside a furious wall of surf, which makes Madras a very formidable place
     for landing; and every one who dares to do so certain of a watering. There lay the city, most
     invitingly to storm-tost tars, with its white palaces, green groves, and yellow belt of sand,
     blue hills in the distance, and all else <hi>coleur de rose</hi>. But—but, Emmy, there was no
     getting at this paradise, except by struggling through a couple of miles of raging foam, that
     would have made mince-meat of the Spanish Armada, and have smashed Sir William Elphinston to
     pieces. How, then, did we manage to survive it? for, thank God always, here I am to tell the
     tale. Listen, Emmy dear, and I will try not to be tedious.</p>
    <p>"We were bundled out of the rolling ship into some huge flat-bottomed boats, like
     coal-barges, and even so, were grated and ground several times by the churning waves on the
     ragged reefs beneath us: and, just as I was enjoying the see-saw, and trying to comfort two
     poor drenched women-kind who were terribly afraid of sharks, a huge, cream-coloured breaker
     came bustling alongside of us, and roaring out 'Charles Tracy,' gobbled me up bodily. Well,
     dearest, it wasn't the first time I had floundered in the waters [noble Charles! noble Charles!
     he had long forgiven Julian]; so I was battling on as well as I could, with a stout heart and a
     steady arm, when—don't be afraid—a <hi>Catamaran</hi> caught me! If you haven't fainted (bless
     those pretty eyes of your's, my Emmy!) read on; and you will find that this alarming sort of
     animal is neither an albatross nor an alligator, but simply—a life-boat with a
     <pb n="75"/> Triton in the stern. Yes, God's messenger of life to me and happiness to you, my
     girl, came in the shape of a kindly, chattering, blue-skinned, human creature, who dragged me
     out of the surf, landed me safely, and, I need not say, got paid with more than hearty thanks.
     So, I scuffled to the custom-house to look after my traps and fellow-passengers, like a
     dripping merman.</p>
    <p>"'Who is that miserable old woman, bothering every body?' asked I of a very civil searcher,
     profuse in his salaams.</p>
    <p>"'Oh, Sahib, you will know for yourself, presently: she's always hanging about here, to get
     news of somebody in England, I believe—and to try to find a charitable captain who will take
     her all the way for nothing: rather too much of a good thing, you know, Sahib.'</p>
    <p>[We really cannot undertake to scribble broken English: so we will translate any thing that
     may mysteriously have been chatted by havildars, and coolies; and all manner of strange
     names.]</p>
    <p>"'Poor old soul—she looks very wretched: what's her name?' asked I, carelessly.</p>
    <p>"'Oh, I never troubled to inquire, Sahib: I believe she was an old servant left behind as
     lumber, and she pesters every one, day by day, about some 'bonnie bonnie bairn.''</p>
    <p>"In a moment, Emmy, I had seized on dear nurse Mackie!</p>
    <p>"Very old, very deaf, very infirm—she fancied I was driving her away, as many others might
     have done; and, with a truly piteous face, pleaded—</p>
    <p>"'Gude sir, have mercy on a puir auld soul—and let her ask for her sweet young mistress, only
     once, sir—only once more.'</p>
    <p>"'Emily Warren?' said I.</p>
    <p>"Her wrinkled face brightened over as with glory—and she answered—</p>
    <p>"'Bless the mouth that spake it, and these ears that hear her name! yes—yes—yes—they call her
     so; where is she? how is she? have you seen her? is she yet alive?'</p>
    <p>"Leading away the affectionate old soul from the crowd that was collecting round us, I left
     orders about luggage as a traveller should, and then told her all I knew: and I know you pretty
     well, I think, my Emmy.</p>
    <p>"Her joy was like a mad woman's: the dear old Hecate pranced, and danced, and sung, and
     shouted like nothing but a mother when she finds her long-lost child: not that she's your
     mother, Emmy dear. No—no—matters are better than that: all she vouchsafes, though, to tell me
     is,
     <pb n="76"/>that you are a lady born and bred, and—for I cannot find the words to inform your
     pure mind clearer—that 'you are not what he thinks you.'"</p>
    <p>[Here followeth another twinkling universe of stars;</p>
    <p>* * * * * * * *</p>
    <p>and thereafter our cavalier condescendeth again to matters of fact.]</p>
    <p>"Nurse Mackie of course comes back with me next packet; this letter goes by the overland mail
     more quickly than we can; gladly would I go too, but the old woman, whose life is essential to
     your rights, would die of fatigue by the way; as it is, I am obliged to coddle her, and feed
     her, and ptisan her, like a sick baby, bless her dear old heart that loves my darling Emmy! She
     has a pack of papers with her, which she will not open, till the general is by her side: if she
     unfortunately dies before we can return, I am to have them, and all will be right. But the old
     soul is so afraid of being left behind (as you throw away the orange-peel after you have
     squeezed it), that she will not tell me a word about them yet; so, I only gather what I can
     from her cautious garrulity, hints about a Begum and a captain, and the Stuarts, and a
     Putty-what-d'ye-call-it. And it is all in document, as well as <hi>viva-voce</hi> (this means
     'gossip,' dear). So now you may be expecting us, as soon as ever we can get to you. Tell the
     general all this, and give him my best love, next after your's Emmy; for he is my father still,
     and my very heart yearns after him: O, that he were kinder with me as I see he is with you,
     dear, and more open with us all! Also, kiss, if she will let you, my mother for me, and I hope
     you will have hinted to her long ago, that I am only playing truant. How is poor—poor Julian?
     he will understand me, if you tell him I forgive him, and will never say one word about our
     little tiff. And now dearest Emmy—"</p>
    <p>[The remainder of this letter must, believe me, be as starry as before.]</p>
    <p>* * * * * * * *</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XXII.</head>
    <head>REVELATIONS.</head>
    <p>General Tracy gave a long-drawn sigh: and tears—tears of true affection—stood in those most
     fish-like eyes, as he mournfully said, "Bless him, bless dear Charles, almost as much as you,
     my own sweet
     <pb n="77"/> Emmy. Heaven send it be true—for Heaven can work miracles. But without a miracle,
     Emily, in sober sadness I declare it, you must forget—<hi>your brother Charles, my
     daughter</hi>!"</p>
    <p>Emily fell flat upon her face, so cold, so white, that he believed her dead.</p>
    <p>Oh! that he had never—never said that word: or better still, poor father, that you had never
     kept the dreadful secret from them. The adultery, indeed, was sin; but years of ill-concealings
     have multiplied its punishment. Wretched father—wretched children! that must bear an erring
     father's curse.</p>
    <p>Oh! that Jeanie Mackie may have reasons, proofs; and be not an impostor after all, dressing
     up a tale that over-sanguine Charles may bring her back again to Scotland. Well—well! I am full
     of sadness and perplexities: but we shall hear it out anon. Heaven help them!</p>
    <p>Emily was taken very ill, and had a long fit of sickness. Day and night—night and day, did
     her poor wasting anxious father watch by her bed-side, gentle as the gentlest nurse—tender as
     the tenderest of mothers. And, indeed, the Lord of Life and Wisdom was gracious to them both;
     raising up the poor weak child again; and teaching that old man, through this daughter of his
     shame and sin in youth, that religion is a cure for all things. Ay, "the blessed angel of a bad
     man's life," indeed—indeed was she; and he humbly knelt, as little children kneel, that hard
     and dried old man; and his eyes caught the ray of Heaven's mercy, looking up in joy to read
     forgiveness; and his heart was bathed in penitence—the rock flowed out amain; and his mind was
     quickened into faith—he lived, he breathed "a new-born babe," that poor and bad old man, given
     to the prayers of his own daughter!</p>
    <p>All this while, Mrs. Tracy, thrown upon her own resources, has been continually tasting dear
     Julian's store, and finding out excuses for his trivial peccadilloes. And when, from the
     recesses of his desk, she had routed out (in company with sundry more, rather contrasting with
     a mother's pure advice) a few of her own letters, which had not yet been destroyed, she would
     doat by the hour on these proofs of his affection. And then, her spirits were so low; and his
     choice smuggled Hollands so requisite to screw them up to par again; and no sooner had they
     rallied, than they would once more begin to droop; so she cried a good deal, and kept her bed;
     and very often did not remember exactly, whether she was lying down there, or figuring on the
     Esplanade with Julian, and—all that sort of thing: accordingly, it is not to be wondered at if, in
     <pb n="78"/> Aunt Green's double-house, the general and Emily saw very little of her, and
     during all this illness, had almost forgotten her existence. Nevertheless, she was alive still,
     and as vast as ever—though a course of strong waters had shattered her nerves considerably;
     even more so, than her real mother's grief at Julian's protracted absence.</p>
    <p>Never had he been heard of since he left, hard heart; though he might have guessed a mother's
     sorrow, and was not far away, and often lingered near the house in strange disguises. It would
     have been easy for him, in some clever way or other, latch-key and all, to have gained access
     to her, and comforted her, and given her some real proof, that all the love she had shed on him
     had not been utterly thrown away; but he didn't—he didn't; and I know not of a darker trait in
     Julian's whole career; he was insensible to love—a mother's love.</p>
    <p>For love is the weapon which Omnipotence reserved to conquer rebel man; when all the rest had
     failed. Reason he parries; Fear he answers blow to blow; future interest he meets with present
     pleasure; but Love, that sun against whose melting beams the Winter cannot stand, that
     soft-subduing slumber which wrestles down the giant, there is not one human creature in a
     million—not a thousand men in all earth's huge quintillion, whose clay-heart is hardened
     against love.</p>
    <p>Yet was Julian one of those select ones; an awful instance of that possible, that actual,
     though happily that scarcest of all characters, a man,</p>
    <quote>
     <l>"Black, with <hi>no</hi> virtue, and a thousand crimes."</l> </quote>
    <p>The amiable villain—one whose generosity redeems his guilt, whose kindliness outweighs his
     folly, or whose beauty charms the eye to overlook his baseness—this too common hero is an
     object, an example fraught with perilous interest. Charles Duval, the polite; Paul Clifford,
     the handsome; Richard Turpin, brave and true; Jack Sheppard, no ignoble mind and loving still
     his mother; these, and such as these, with Schiller's '<hi>Robbers</hi>' and the like, are
     dangerous to gaze on, as Germany, if not England too, remembers well. But, not more true to
     life, though far less common to be met with, is Julian's incorrigible mind: one, in whose life
     are no white days; one, on whose heart are no bright spots; when Heaven's pity spoke to him, he
     ridiculed; as, when His threatenings thundered, he defied. Of this world only, and tending to a
     worse appetite was all he lived for: and the core of appetite is iron selfishness.</p>
    <p>The filched cash-box proved to be too well-filled for him to trouble himself with thinking of
     his mother yet awhile: and his smuggling
     <pb n="79"/>acquaintances, a rough-featured, blasphemous crew, set him as their chief, so long
     as he swore loudest, drank deepest, and had money at command. He hid the money, that they
     should not secretly steal from him that to which he owed his bad supremacy; and his
     double-barrels, shotted to the muzzle, were far too formidable for any hope of getting at it by
     open brute force. Nevertheless, they were "fine high-spirited" fellows those, bold, dark men,
     of Julian's own kidney; who toasted in their cups each other's crimes, and the ghost or two
     that ought to have been haunting them.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XXIII.</head>
    <head>CONVALESCENCE.</head>
    <p>Very slowly did Emily recover, for the blow had been more than she could bear: nothing but
     religion gave her any chance at all: and the phials, blisterings, bleedings, would have been in
     vain, in vain—she must have died long ago—had it not been for the remembrance of God's love,
     resignation to His will, and trust in the wisdom of his Providence. But these specific remedies
     gradually brought her round, while the kind-eyed doctors praised their own prescriptions: and
     after many rallyings and relapses, delirious ramblings, and intervals of hallowed Christian
     peace, the eye of Love's meek martyr brightened up once more, and health flushed again upon her
     cheek.</p>
    <p>She recovered, God be praised! for her death would have been poor Charles's too; and the same
     grave that yawned for her and him would have closed upon their father also. Even as it was,
     when she arose from off the weary bed of sickness, it was to be a nurse herself, and watch
     beside that patient, weak old man. He could not bear her out of his sight all the fever
     through; but eagerly would listen to her hymns and prayers, joining in them faintly like a
     dying saint. With the saddening secret, which had so long pressed upon his mind, he seemed to
     have thrown off his old nature, as a cast skin: and now he was all frankness for reserve, all
     piety for profaneness, all peacefulness for blusterings and wrath.</p>
    <p>He remembered then poor Julian and his mother: taking blame to himself, justly, deeply, for
     neglected duties, chilling lack of sympathy,
     <pb n="80"/>and that dull domestic sin, that still continued evil of unnatural omissions—stern
     reserve. And he would gladly have seen Julian by his bedside, to have freely forgiven the lad,
     and welcomed him home again, and begun once more, in openness and charity, all things fair and
     new: but Julian was not to be found, though rewards were offered, and placards posted up, and
     emissaries from the Detective Police-force sought him far and wide. Alas! the bold bad man had
     heard with scorn of his father's penitence, and knew that he would gladly have received
     him;—but what cared he for kindnesses or pardons? He only lived to waylay Emily.</p>
    <p>As for Mrs. Tracy, she was seldom in a state to appear; but one day she managed to refrain a
     little, and came to see her husband, almost sober. I was, authorially speaking, behind the
     door, and saw and heard as follows:</p>
    <p>The old man, worn and emaciate, was weakly sitting up in bed, and Emma by his side, with the
     Bible in her lap: she casually shut it as the mother entered.</p>
    <p>"Well, Miss Warren, there's a time for all things; but this is neither morning, noon, nor
     night: nor Sunday either, nor holiday, that I know of; it's eleven o'clock on Tuesday, Miss—and
     I think you might as well leave the general at peace, without troubling him for ever with your
     prayer-books and your Bibles."</p>
    <p>"Jane, my dear, I requested it of Emily; come and sit by me, and take my hand, wife."</p>
    <p>"Thank you, sir, you are very obliging: not while that young woman is in the room.—You ought
     to be ashamed of yourself, General Tracy."</p>
    <p>Poor Emmy ran away to weep. It seems that, in her delirium, she had spoken many things, and
     the servants blabbed them out to Mrs. Tracy.</p>
    <p>"Ah, my poor wife, indeed I am: both ashamed and sorry—heartily sorry. But God forgives me,
     Jenny, and I hope that you will too."</p>
    <p>"Upon, my word, general, you carry it off with a high hand: and, not content, sir, with
     insulting me in my own home by bringing here your other women's children, you have expelled
     poor dear, dear Julian."</p>
    <p>"Jane, if you will remember, he ran away himself; and you know that now I gladly would
     receive him: we are all prodigal sons together, and if God can bear with us, Jane, we ought to
     look kindly on each other."</p>
    <p>"Ha! that's always the way with old sinners like you—canting hypocrites! Be a man, General
     Tracy, if you can, and talk sense. I never
     <pb n="81"/>did any harm or sin in all my life yet, and don't intend to: and my poor boy
     Julian's well enough, if they'd only let him alone; but nobody understands his heart but me.
     Good boy, I'm sure there's virtue enough left in him, if he loves his mother."—<hi>If</hi> he
     loves his mother.</p>
    <p>"Jane, dear, I sent for you to kiss you; for I could not die in peace, nor live in peace
     (whichever God may please), without your pardon, Jane, for a thousand unkindnesses—but,
     especially for the sin that gave me Emily. Forgive me this, my wife."</p>
    <p>"Never, sir!" rejoined that miserable mind; and fancied that she was acting virtuously. She
     thrust aside the kindly proffered hand; scowled at him with darkened brow; drew up her
     commanding height; and, calling Mrs. Siddons to remembrance, brushed away in the indignant
     attitude of a tragedy queen.</p>
    <p>Emmy ran again to her father, and the vain bad mother to her bottle; we must leave them to
     their various avocations.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XXIV.</head>
    <head>CHARLES DELAYED.</head>
    <p>Few things could well be more unlikely than that Emily should hear of Charles again before
     she saw him: for, having left Madras as speedily as might be, now that his mission was so
     easily, yet so naturally, accomplished—having posted, as we know, his overland letter—and
     having got on board the fast-sailing ship Samarang, Captain Trueman, Charles, in the probable
     course of things, if he wrote at all, must have been his own postman. But the Fates—(our
     Christianity can afford to wink now and then at Clotho, Lachesis, and Atropos; for, at any
     rate, they are as reasonable creatures as Chance, Luck, and Accident,)—the Fates willed it
     otherwise: and, accordingly, it is in my power to lay before the reader another genuine
     lucubration of Charles Tracy.</p>
    <p>A change had come over the spirit of their dream, those youthful lovers: and agonizing doubt
     must rack their hearts, threatening to rend them both asunder. It is evident to me that
     Charles's letter (which Emily showed to me with a melancholy face) was on principle less warm,
     less dottable with stars, and more conversant with things of this
     <pb n="82"/>world; high, firm, honourable principle; intending very gently, very gradually, to
     wean her from him, if he could; for his faith in Jeanie Mackie had been shaken, and—but let us
     hear him tell us of it all himself.</p>
    <p>"I.E.M. Samarang. St. Helena.</p>
    <p>"You will wonder, my dear Emily, to hear again before you see me: but I am glad of this
     providential opportunity, as it may serve to prepare us both. Naturally enough you will ask,
     why Charles cannot accompany this letter? I will tell you, dear, in one word—Mrs. Mackie is now
     lying very ill on shore; and, as far as our poor ship is concerned, you shall hear about it all
     anon. Several of the passengers, who were in a hurry to get home, have left us, and gone in the
     packet-boat that takes you this letter: gladly, as you know, would I have accompanied them, for
     I long to see you, poor dear girl; but it was impossible to leave the old woman, upon whom
     alone, under God, our hopes of earthly happiness depend: if, alas! we still can dream about
     such hopes.</p>
    <p>"Oh, Emily—I heartily wish that, having finished my embassage by that instantaneous finding
     of the old Scotch nurse, I had never been so superfluous as to have left those letters of
     introduction, wherewith you kindly supplied me, in an innocent wish to help our cause. But I
     felt solitary too, waiting at Madras for the next ship to England; and in my folly, forgetful
     of the single aim with which I had come, Jeanie Mackie, to wit, I thought I might as well use
     my present opportunities, and see what I could of the place and its inhabitants.</p>
    <p>"With that view, I left my letters at Government House, at Mr. Clarkson's, Colonel Bunting's,
     Mrs. Castleton's, and elsewhere, according to direction; and immediately found answer in a
     crowd of invitations. I need not vex you nor myself, Emmy, writing as I do with a heavy, heavy
     heart, by describing gayeties in which I felt no pleasure, even when amongst them, for my Emmy
     was not there: splendour, prodigality, and red-hot rooms, only made endurable by perpetually
     fanning punkahs: pompous counsellors, authorities, and other men in office, and a glut of
     military uniforms: vulgar wealth, transparent match-making, and predominating dullness: along
     with some few of the charities and kindnesses of life (Mrs. Bunting, in particular, is an
     amiable, motherly, good-hearted woman), all these you will readily fancy for yourself.</p>
    <p>"My trouble is deeper than any thing so slight as the common satiations of <hi>ennui</hi>:
     for I have heard in these circles in which your—my—the general, I mean, chiefly mixed, so much
     of that ill-rumour that it
     <pb n="83"/>cannot all be false: they knew it all, and were certain of it all, too well, Emily,
     dear. And I have been pestering Nurse Mackie night and day; but the old woman is so afraid of
     being left behind any where, or thrown overboard, or dropped, upon some desert rock, that she
     is quite cross, and won't say a single word in answer, even when I tell her all these terrible
     tales. Her resolution is, not to reveal one syllable more, until she sets foot on England; and
     several people at Madras annoyed me exceedingly by saying, that this kind of thing is an old
     trick with people who wish to be sent home again. She has hidden away her papers somewhere; not
     that I was going to steal them: but it shows how little trust she puts in any thing, or any
     one, except the keeping of her own secret. However, she does adhere obstinately, and hopefully
     for us, to her original hint, 'you are not what he thinks you;' although she will not
     condescend to any single proof, or explanation, against the mighty mass of evidence, which
     probabilities, and common rumour, and the general's own belief, have heaped together. When I
     call you Emmy, too—the old soul, in her broad Scotch way, always corrects me, and invokes a
     blessing upon 'A-amy:' so there is a mystery somewhere: at least, I fervently hope there is:
     and, if the old woman has been playing us false, let us resign ourselves to God, my girl; for
     our fate will be that matters are as people say they are—and then my old black postscript ends
     too truly with a wo, wo, wo—!</p>
    <p>"But I must shake off all this lethargy of gloom, dearest, dearest girl—how can I dare to
     call you so? Let me, therefore, rush for comfort into other thoughts; and tell you at once of
     the fearful dangers we have now mercifully escaped; for the Samarang lies like a log in this
     friendly port, dismasted, and next to a wreck.</p>
    <p>"I proceed to show you about it; perhaps I shall be tedious—but I do it as a little rest, my
     own soul's love, from anxious, earnest, heart-distracting prayers continually, continually,
     that the sorrow which I spoke of be not true. Sometimes, a light breaks in, and I rejoice in
     the most sanguine hope: at others, gloom—</p>
    <p>"But a truce to all this, I say. Here shall follow didactically the cause why the good ship
     Samarang is not by this time in the Docks.</p>
    <p>"We were lying somewhere about the tropical belt, Capricorn you know, (O, those tender
     lessons in geography, my Emmy!) quite becalmed; the sea like glass, and the sky like brass, and
     the air in a most stagnant heat: our good ship motionless, dead in a dead blue sea it was</p>
    <p>'Idle as a painted ship upon a painted ocean.'</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="84"/>"The sails were hanging loosely in the shrouds: every one set, from sky-scraper to
     stud-sail, in hopes to catch a breath of wind. My fellow-passengers and the crew, almost
     melted, were lying about, as weak as parboiled eels: it was high-noon, all things silent and
     subdued by that intolerable blaze; for the vertical sun, over our multiplied awnings and
     umbrellas, burnt us up, fierce as a furnace.</p>
    <p>"I was leaning over the gangway, looking wistfully at the cool, clear, deep sea, wherefrom
     the sailors were trying to persuade a shark to come on board us, when, all at once, in the
     south-east quarter, I noticed a little round black cloud, thrown up from the horizon like a
     cricket-ball. As any thing is attractive in such sameness as perpetual sea and sky, my
     discovery was soon made known, and among the first to our captain.</p>
    <p>"Calling for his Dolland, and bidding his second lieutenant run quick to the cabin and look
     at the barometer, he viewed the little cloud in evident anxiety, and shook his head with a
     solemn air: more than one light-hearted woman thinking he was quizzing them.</p>
    <p>"Up came Lieutenant Joyce, looking as if he had seen a ghost in the cabin.</p>
    <p>"'The mercury, sir, is falling just as rapidly as it would rise if you plunged it into
     boiling water: an inch a minute or so!"</p>
    <p>"Our captain saw the danger instantly, and, brave as Trueman is, I never saw a man look
     paler.</p>
    <p>"To drive all the passengers below, and pen them in with closed hatches and storm-shutters,
     (so hot, Emmy, that the black-hole of Calcutta must have been an ice-house to it: how the
     foolish people abused our wise skipper, and more than one pompous old Indian threatened him
     with an action for false imprisonment!) this huddling away was the first effort; and
     simultaneously with it, the crew were all over the rigging, furling sails, hurriedly,
     hurriedly.</p>
    <p>"Meanwhile (for I was last on deck), that little cloud seemed whirling within itself, and
     many others gathered round it, all dancing about on the horizon, as if sheaves of mischief
     tossed about by devils: I don't wish to be poetical, Emmy, for my heart is very, very sad; but
     if ever the powers of the air sow the wind and reap the whirlwind, they were gathering in their
     harvest at that door. Underneath the skipping clouds, which came on quickly, leaping over each
     other, as when the wain is loaded by a score of hands, I noticed a sea approaching, such as
     Pharaoh must have seen, when the wall of waters fell upon him; and premonitory winds came
     whistling by, and two or three sails were flapping in them still, and I was hurried down stairs
     after all the rest of us.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="85"/></p>
    <p>"Then, on a sudden, it appeared not winds, nor waves, nor thunder, but as if the squadroned
     cavalry of heaven had charged across the seas, and crushed our battered ship beneath their
     horse-hoofs! We were flung down flat on our beam ends; and the two or three unfurled sails,
     bursting with the noise of a cannon, were scattered miles away to lee-ward as if they had been
     paper. As for the poor fellows in the rigging, the spirit of the storm had already made them
     his: twenty of our men were swept away by that tornado.</p>
    <p>"Then there was hewing and cleaving on deck, the clatter of many axes and hatchets: for we
     were in imminent danger of being capsized, keel uppermost, and our only chance was to cut away
     the masts.</p>
    <p>"The muscles of courage were tried then, my Emmy, and the strength which religion gives a
     man. I felt sensibly held up by the Everlasting Arms: I could listen to the still small Voice
     in the midst of a crash which might have been the end of all things: though in darkness, God
     had given me light; though in uttermost peril, my peace was never calmer in our little village
     school.</p>
    <p>"And the billows were knocking at the poor ship's side like sledge hammers; and the
     lightnings fell around us scorchingly, with forked bolts, as arrows from the hand of a giant;
     the thunders overhead, close overhead, crashing from a concave cloud that hung about us
     heavily—a dense, black, suffocating curtain—roared and raved as nothing earthly can, but
     thunder in the tropics; the rain was as a cataract, literally rushing in a mass: the winds
     appeared not winds, nor whirlwinds, but legions of emancipated demons shrieking horribly, and
     flapping their wide wings; a flock of night-birds flying from the dawn; and all else was
     darkness, confusion, rolling and rocking about, the screams of women, the shouts of men, curses
     and prayers, agony, despair, and—peace, deep peace.</p>
    <p>"On a sudden, to our great astonishment, all was silent again, oppressively silent; and, but
     for the swell upon the seas, all still. The tornado had rushed by: that troop of Tartar horse,
     having sacked the village, are departed, now in full retreat: the blackness and the fury are
     beheld on our lee, hastening across the broad Atlantic to Cuba or Jamaica: and behold, a
     tranquil temperate sky, a kindly rolling sea, a favouring breeze, and—not a sail, but some
     slight jury-rig, to catch it.</p>
    <p>"Many days we drifted like a log upon the wave; provisions running short, and water—water
     under tropical suns—scantily dealt out in tea-cups. Then, poor old Mackie's health gave way;
     and I dreaded for her
     <pb n="86"/>death: one living witness is worth a cart-load of cold documents. So I nursed and
     watched her constantly: till the foolish folks on board began to say I was her son: ah! me, for
     your sake I wish it had been so.</p>
    <p>"And at length, just as some among the sailors were hinting at a mutiny for spirits, and our
     last case of Gamble's meat was opened for the sick, our look-out on the jury-mast gave the
     welcome note of 'Land!' and soon, to us on deck, the heights of St. Helena rose above the sea.
     Towed in by friendly aid, here we are, then, precious Emily, refitting: and, as it must be a
     week yet before we can be ready, I have taken my old woman to a lodging upon land, and rejoice
     (what have I to do with joy?) to see her speedily recovering."</p>
    <p>The remainder of Charles's long letter is so stupid, so gloomy, so loving, and so little to
     the purpose, that I take an editor's privilege, and omit it altogether. Of course he was coming
     home again, as soon as the Samarang and Jeanie Mackie would permit.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XXV.</head>
    <head>TRIALS.</head>
    <p>The general recovered; as slowly, indeed, as Emily had, but it is gratifying to add, as
     surely. And now that loving couple might be seen, weakly creeping out together, when the day
     was finest: tottering white December leaning on a sickly fragile May. There were no
     concealments now between them, no reservings, and heart-stricken Emily heard from her repentant
     father's lips the story of her birth: she was, he said, his own daughter by a native princess,
     the Begum Dowlia Burruckjutli.</p>
    <p>A bitter—bitter truth was that: the destruction of all her hopes, pleasures, and affections.
     It had now become to her a sin to love that dearest one of all things lovely on this earth:
     duty, paramount and stern, commanded her, without a shadow of reprieve, to execute on herself
     immediately the terrible sentence of banishing her own betrothed: nay, more, she must forget
     him, erase his precious image from her heart, and never, never see that brother more. And
     Charles must feel the same, and do
     <pb n="87"/>the like; oh! sorrow, passing words! and their two commingled souls must be
     violently wrenched apart; for such love in them were crime.</p>
    <p>Dear children of affection—it is a dreadful lesson this for both of you; but most wise, most
     needful—or the hand that guideth all things, never would have sent it. Know ye not for comfort,
     that ye are of those to whom all things work together for good? Know ye not for counsel, that
     the excess of love is an idolatry that must be blighted? It is well, children, it is well, that
     ye should thus carry your wounded hearts for balm to the altar of God; it is well that ye
     should bow in meekness to His will, in readiness to His wisdom. Ye are learning the lesson
     speedily, as docile children should; and be assured of high reward from the Teacher who hath
     set it you. Poor Charles! white and wan, thy cheek is grown transparent with anxiety, and thy
     blue eye dim with hope deferred: poor Emmy, sick and weak, thou weariest Heaven with thy
     prayers, and waterest thy couch with thy tears. Yet, a little while; this discipline is good:
     storm and wind, frost and rushing rains, are as needful to the forest-tree as sun and gentle
     shower; the root is strengthening, and its fibres spreading out: and loving still each other
     with the best of human love, ye justly now have found out how to anchor all your strongest
     hopes, and deepest thoughts, on Him who made you for himself. Who knoweth? wisely acquiescing
     in His will, humbly trusting to His mercy, and bringing the holocaust of your inflamed
     affections as an offering of duty to your God—who knoweth? Cannot He interpose? will He not
     befriend you? For His arm is power, and His heart is love.</p>
    <p>Days rolled on in dull monotony, and grew to weeks more slowly than before; earthly hopes had
     been levelled with the dust; life had forgotten to be joyous: there was, indeed, the calm, the
     peace, the resignation, the heavenly ante-past, and the soul-entrancing prayer; but human life
     to Emily was flat, wearisome, and void; she felt like a nun, immolated as to this world: even
     as Charles, too, had resolved to be an anchorite, a stern, hard, mortified man, who once had
     feelings and affections. The rëaction in both those fond young hearts had even overstept the
     golden mean: and Mercy interposed to make all right, and to bless them in each other once
     again.</p>
    <p>Only look at this <hi>billet-doux</hi> from Charles, just come in, and dated Plymouth:</p>
    <p>"Huzzah—for Emily and England: huzzah for the land of freedom! no secrets now—dear, dear old
     Jeanie Mackie has given me proofs posi
     <pb n="88"/>tive: all I have to wish is that she could move: but she is very ill; so, as we
     touched here on the voyage up channel, I landed her and myself, thinking to kiss, within a day,
     my darling Emmy. But I cannot get her out of bed this morning, and dare not leave her: though
     an hour's delay seems almost insupportable. If I possibly can manage it, I will bring the dear
     old faithful creature, wrapped in blankets, by chaise to-morrow. Tell my father all this: and
     say to him—he will understand, perhaps, though you may not, my blessed girl—say to him, that
     'he is mistaken, and all are mistaken—you are not what they think you.' A thousand kisses.
     Expect, then, on bright to-morrow to see your happy, happy</p>
    <p>"<hi>Charles.</hi>"</p>
    <p>"P.S. Hip! hip! hip!—huzzah!"</p>
    <p>Dearest Emily had taken up the note with fears and trembling: she laid it down, as they that
     reap in joy; and I never in my life saw any thing so beautiful as her eyes at that glad minute;
     the smile through the tear, the light through the gloom, the verdure of high summer springing
     through the Alpine snows, the mild and lustrous moon emerging from a baffled thunder-cloud.</p>
    <p>And, although the general mournfully shook his head, distrustfully and despondingly; though
     he only uttered, "Poor children—dear children—would to Heaven that it could be so;"—and he, for
     one, was evidently innoculated, as before, with all the old thoughts of gloom, sadness, and
     anxiety;—still Emily hoped—for Charles hoped—and Jeanie Mackie was so certain.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XXVI.</head>
    <head>JULIAN.</head>
    <p>Next day, a fine summer afternoon, when our feeble convalescents had gone out together, they
     found the fresh air so invigorating, and themselves so much stronger, that they prolonged their
     walk half-way to Oxton. The pasture-meadows, rich and rank, were alive with flocks and herds;
     the blue sea lazily beat time, as, ticking out the seconds, it melodiously broke upon the
     sleeping shore; the darkly-flowing Mullet swept sounding to the sea between its tortuous banks;
     and upon that
     <pb n="89"/>old high foot-path skirting the stream, now shady with hazels, and now flowery with
     meadow-sweet, crept our chastened pair.</p>
    <p>Just as they were nearing a short angle in the river, the spot where Charles had been
     preserved, they noticed for the first time a rough-looking fisherman, who, unseen, had tracked
     their steps some hundred yards; he had a tarpaulin over his shoulder, very unnecessarily, as it
     would seem, on so fine and warm a day; and a slouching sou'-wester, worn askew, flapped across
     the strange man's face.</p>
    <p>He came on quickly, though cautiously, looking right and left; and Emily trembled on her
     guardian's feeble arm. Yes—she is right; the fisherman approaches—she detects him through it
     all: and now he scorns disguise; flinging off his cap and the tarpaulin, stands before
     them—Julian!</p>
    <p>"So, sir—you tremble now, do you, gallant general: give me the girl." And he levelled at his
     father one of those double-barrelled pistols, full-cock.</p>
    <p>"Julian, my son, I forgive you, Julian; take my hand, boy."</p>
    <p>"What—coward? now you can cringe, and fawn, eh? back with you!—the girl, I say." For poor
     Emily, wild with fear, was clinging to that weak old man.</p>
    <p>Julian levelled again; indeed, indeed it was only as a threat; but his hand shook with
     passion—the weapon was full-cock, hair-triggered—shotted heavily as always—hark, hark!—And his
     father fell upon the turf, covered with blood!</p>
    <p>When a wicked man tampers with unintended crime, even accident falls out against him. Many a
     one has richly merited death for many other sins, than that isolated, haply accidental one
     which he has hanged for.</p>
    <p>Julian, horror-stricken, pale and trembling, flew instinctively to help his father: but Emily
     has circled him already with her arms; and listen, Julian—your dying father speaks to you.</p>
    <p>"Boy, I forgive—I forgive: but—Emily, no, no, cannot, cannot be—Julian—she—she is your
     <hi>sister</hi>!" and the old man swooned away, from loss of blood and the excitement of that
     awful scene.</p>
    <p>Not a word in reply said that poor sinner, maddened with his life-long crimes, the fratricide
     in will, the parricide in deed, and all for—a sister. But growing whiter as he stood, a marble
     man with bristling hair, he slowly drew the other pistol from his pocket, put the muzzle to his
     mouth, and, firing as he fell, leapt into the darkly-flowing Mullet!</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="90"/>The current, all too violent to sink in, and uncommissioned now to save, hurried
     its black burden to the sea; and a crimson streak of gore marked the track of the suicide.</p>
    <p>The old man was not dead; but a brace of bullets taking effect upon his feeble frame—one
     through the shoulder, and another which had grazed his head—had been quite enough to make him
     seem so. Forgetful of all but that dear sufferer, and totally ignorant of Julian's fate—for she
     neither saw nor heard any thing, nor feared even for her own imminent peril, while her father
     lay dying on the grass—Emily had torn off her scarf, and bound up, as well as she could, the
     ghastly scored head and broken shoulder. She succeeded in staunching the blood—for no great
     vessel had been severed—and so simple an application as grass dipped in water, proved to be a
     good specific. Then, to her exceeding joy, those eyes opened again, and that dear tongue
     faintly whispered—"Bless you."</p>
    <p>Oh, that blessing! for it fell upon her heart: and fervently she knelt down there, and
     thanked the Great Preserver.</p>
    <p>And now, for friendly help; there is no one near: and it is growing dusk; and she dared not
     leave him there alone one minute—for Julian—dreaded Julian, may return, and kill him. What
     shall she do? How to get him home? Alas, alas! he may die where he is lying.</p>
    <p>Hark, Emmy, hark! The shouts of happy children bursting out of school! See, dearest—see: here
     they come homewards merrily from Oxton.</p>
    <p>Thus, rewarded through the instrumentality of her own benevolence, help was speedily
     obtained; and Mrs. Sainsbury's invalid-chair, hurried to the spot by an escort of indignant
     rustics, soon conveyed the recovering patient to the comforts of his own home, and the
     appliances of medical assistance.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XXVII.</head>
    <head>CHARLES'S RETURN; AND MRS. MACKIE'S EXPLANATION.</head>
    <p>And now the happy day was come at length; that day formerly so hoped-for, latterly so feared,
     but last of all, hailed with the joy that trembles at its own intensity. The very morning after
     the sad occurrence it
     <pb n="91"/>has just been my lot to chronicle—while the general was having his wounds dressed,
     slight ones, happily, but still he was not safe, as inflammation might ensue—while Mrs. Tracy
     was indulging in her third tumbler, mixed to whet her appetite for shrimps—and while Emily was
     deciphering, for the forty thousandth time, Charles's sanguine <hi>billet-doux</hi>—lo! a dusty
     chaise and smoking posters, and a sun-burnt young fellow springing out, and just upon the
     stairs—they were locked in each other's arms!</p>
    <p>Oh, the rapture of that instant! it can but happen once within a life. Ye that have loved,
     remember such a meeting; and ye that never loved, conceive it if you can; for my pen hath
     little skill to paint so bright a pleasure. It is to be all heart, all pulse, all sympathy, all
     spirit—but the warm soft kiss, that rarified bloom of the Material.</p>
    <p>How the sick old nurse got out, cased in many blankets; how she was bundled up stairs, and
     deposited safely on a sofa, no poet is alive to sing: to those who would record the payment of
     postillions, let me leave so sweet a theme.</p>
    <p>The first fond greeting over, and those tumults of affection sobered down, Charles rejoiced
     to find how lovingly the general met him; the kind and good old man fell upon his neck, as the
     father in the parable. Many things were then to be made known: and many questions answered, as
     best might be, about a mother and a brother; but well aware of all things ourselves, let us be
     satisfied that Charles heard in due time all they had to tell him; though neither Emily nor the
     general could explain what had become of Julian after that terrible encounter. In their belief,
     he had fled for very life, thinking he had killed his father. Poor wretched man, thought
     Charles—on that same spot, too, where he would have murdered me! And for his mother—why came
     she not down eagerly and happily, as mothers ever do, to greet her long-lost son? Do not ask,
     Charles; do not press the question. Think her ill, dying, dead—any thing but—drunken. He ran to
     her room-door; but it was locked—luckily.</p>
    <p>Now, Charles—now speedily to business; happy business that, if I may trust the lover's
     flushing cheek, and Emily's radiant eyes; but a mournful one too, and a fearful, if I turn my
     glance to that poor old man, wounded in body and stricken in mind—who waits to hear, in more
     despondency than hope, what he knows to be the bitter truth—the truth that must be told, to the
     misery of those dear children.</p>
    <p>Faint and weak though she appeared, Jeanie Mackie's waning life
     <pb n="92"/>spirited up for the occasion; her dim eye kindled; her feeble frame was straight
     and strong; energy nerved her as she spoke; this hour is the errand of her being.</p>
    <p>Long she spoke, and loudly, in her broad Scotch way; and the general objected many things,
     but was answered to them all; and there was close cross-questioning, slow-caution, keen
     examination of documents and letters: catechisms, solecisms, Scottisms; reminiscences rubbed
     up, mistakes corrected; and the grand result of all, Emily a Stuart, and the general not her
     father! I am only enabled to give a brief account of that important colloquy.</p>
    <p>It appears, that when Captain Tracy's company was quartered to the west of the Gwalior, sent
     thither to guard the Begum Dowlia against sundry of her disaffected subjects, a certain
     Lieutenant James Stuart was one among those welcome brave allies. That our gallant Tracy was
     the beautiful Begum's favourite soon became notorious to all; and not less so, that the Begum
     herself was precisely in the same interesting situation as Mrs. James Stuart. The two ladies,
     Pagan and Christian, were, technically speaking, running a race together. Well, just as times
     drew nigh, poor Lieutenant Stuart was unfortunately killed in an insurrection headed by some
     fanatics, who disapproved of foreign friends, and perhaps of their princess's situation. His
     death proved fatal also to that kind and faithful wife of his—a dark Italian lady of high
     family, whose love for James had led her to follow him even into Central Hindoostan: she died
     in giving birth to a babe; and Jeanie Mackie, the lieutenant's own foster-mother, who waited on
     his wife through all their travels, assisted the poor orphan into this bleak world, and loved
     it as her own.</p>
    <p>Two days after all this, the Begum herself had need of Mrs. Mackie: for it was prudent to
     conceal some things, if she could, from certain Brahmins, who were to her what John Knox had
     erstwhile been to Mary: and Jeanie Mackie, burdened with her little Amy Stuart, aided in the
     birth of a female Tracy-Begum. So, the nurse tended both babes; and more than once had
     marvelled at their general resemblance; Amy's mother looked out again from those dark eyes;
     there was not a shade between the children.</p>
    <p>Now, Mrs. Mackie perceived, in a very little while, how fond both Christian and Pagan
     appeared of their own child; and how little notice was taken by any body of the poor Scotch
     gentleman's orphan. Accordingly, with a view to give her favourite all worldly advantages, she
     adroitly
     <pb n="93"/>changed the children; and, while she was still kind and motherly to the little
     Tracy-Begum, she had the satisfaction to see her pet supposititiously brought up in all the
     splendours of an Eastern court.</p>
    <p>Years wore away, for Captain Tracy was quite happy, the Begum being a fine showy woman, and
     the pretty child his playmate and pastime: so he never cared to stir from his rich quarters,
     till the company's orders forced him: and then Puttymuddyfudgepoor hailed him accumulatively
     both major and colonel.</p>
    <p>When he found that he must go, he insisted on carrying off the child; and the Begum was as
     resolute against it. Then Mrs. Mackie, eager to expedite little Stuart in her escape, went to
     the princess, told her how that, in anticipation of this day, she had changed the children, and
     got great rewards for thus restoring to the mother her own offspring.</p>
    <p>The remainder of that old Scotch nurse's very prosy tale may be left to be imagined: for all
     that was essential has been stated: and the documents in proof of all were these—</p>
    <p>First: The marriage certificates of James Stuart and Ami di Romagna, duly attested, both in
     the Protestant and Romanist forms.</p>
    <p>Secondly: Divers letters to Lieutenant Stewart from his friends at Glenmuir; others to Mrs.
     Stuart, from her father, the old Marquis di Romagna, at Naples: several trinkets, locks of
     hair, the wedding-ring, etc.</p>
    <p>Thirdly: A grant written in the Hindoostanee character, from the Begum Dowlia, promising the
     pension of thirty rupees a month to Jeanie Mackie, for having so cleverly preserved to her the
     child: together with a regular judicial acknowledgement, both from several of Tracy's own
     sepoys, and from the Begum herself, that the girl, whom Captain Tracy was so fond of, was, to
     the best of their belief, Amy Stuart.</p>
    <p>Fourthly: A miniature of Mrs. James Stuart, exactly portraying the features of her
     daughter—this bright, beautiful, dark-eyed face—our own beloved Emily Warren.</p>
    <p>And to all that accumulated evidence, Jeanie Mackie bore her living testimony; clearly,
     unhesitatingly, and well assured, in the face of God and man.</p>
    <p>Doubt was at an end; fear was at an end; hope was come, and joy. Happy were the lovers, happy
     Jeanie Mackie, but happiest of all appeared the general himself. For now she might be his
     daughter indeed, sweet Emmy Tracy still, dear Charles's loving wife. And he blessed them as
     they knelt, and gave them to each other; well-rewarded children of affection, who had prayed in
     their distress!</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <pb n="94"/>
    <head>CHAPTER XXVIII.</head>
    <head>JULIAN TURNS UP: AND THERE'S AN END OF MRS. TRACY.</head>
    <p>There is a muddy sort of sand-bank, acting as a delta to the Mullet, just where it spreads
     from deep to shallow, and falls into the sea. Strange wild fowl abound there, coming from the
     upper clouds in flocks; and at high water, very little else but rushes can be seen, to testify
     its sub-marine existence.</p>
    <p>A knot of fishermen, idling on the beach, have noticed an uncommon flight of Royston crows
     gathered at the island, with the object, as it would appear, of battening on a dead porpoise,
     or some such body, just discernible among the rushes. Stop—that black heap may be kegs of
     whiskey;—where's the glass?</p>
    <p>Every one looked: it warn't barrels—and it warn't a porpoise: what was it, then? they had
     universally nothing on earth to do, so they pushed off in company to see.</p>
    <p>I watched the party off, and they poked among the rushes, and heaved out what seemed to me a
     seal: so I ran down to the beach to look at the strange creature they had captured. Something
     wrapped in a sail; no doubt for exhibition at per head.</p>
    <p>But they brought out that black burden solemnly, laying it on the beach at Burleigh: a crowd
     quickly collected round them, that I could not see the creature: and some ran for a magistrate,
     and some for a parson. Then men in office came—made a way through the crowd, and I got near: so
     near, that my foolish curiosity lifted up the sail, and I beheld—what had been Julian.</p>
    <p>O, sickening sight: for all which the pistol had spared of that swart and hairy face, had
     been preyed upon by birds and fishes!</p>
    <p>There was a hurried inquest: the poor general and Emily deposed to what they knew, and the
     rustics, who escorted him from Oxton. The verdict could be only one—self-murder.</p>
    <p>So, by night, on that same swampy island, when the tide was low, they buried him, deeply
     staked into the soil, lest the waves should disinter him, without a parting prayer. Such is the
     end of the wicked.</p>
    <p>In a day or two, I noticed that a rude wooden cross had been set over the spot: and it
     gratified me much to hear that a rough-looking crew of smugglers had boldly come and fixed it
     there, to hallow, if they could, a comrade's grave.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="95"/>However, these poor fellows had been cheated hours before: Charles's brotherly care
     had secured the poor remains, and the vicar winked a blind permission: so Charles buried them
     by night in the church-yard corner, under the yew, reading many prayers above them.</p>
    <p>Two fierce-looking strange men went to that burial with reverent looks, as it were chief
     mourners; and when all the rites were done, I heard them gruffly say to Charles, "God bless
     you, sir, for this!"</p>
    <p>When the mother heard those tidings of her son, she was sobered on the instant, and ran about
     the house with all a mother's grief, shrieking like a mad woman. But all her shrieks and tears
     could not bring back poor Julian; deep, deep in the silent grave, she cannot wake him—cannot
     kiss him now. Ah well! ah well!</p>
    <p>Then did she return to his dear room, desperate for him—and Hollands once, twice, thrice, she
     poured out a full tumbler of the burning fluid, and drank it off like water; and it maddened
     her brain: her mind was in a phrensy of delirium, while her body shook as with a palsy.</p>
    <p>Let us draw the curtain; for she died that night.</p>
    <p>They buried her in Aunt Green's grave: what a meeting theirs will be at the day of
     resurrection!</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XXIX.</head>
    <head>THE OLD SCOTCH NURSE GOES HOME.</head>
    <p>Six months at least—this is clearly not a story of the unities—six months' interval must now
     elapse before the wedding-day. Charles and Emmy—for he called her Emmy still, though Jeanie
     Mackie would persist in mouthing it to "Aamy,"—wished to have it delayed a year, in respect for
     the memory of those who, with all their crime and folly, were not the less a mother and a
     brother: but the general would not hear of such a thing; he was growing very old, he said;
     although actually he seemed to have taken out a new lease of life, so young again and buoyant
     was the new-found heart within him; and thus growing old, he was full of fatherly fear that he
     should not live to see his children's happiness. It was only reasonable and proper that our
     pair of cooing doves should acquiesce in his desire.</p>
    <p>
     <pb n="96"/>Meanwhile, I am truly sorry to say it, Jeanie Mackie died; for it would have been a
     good novel-like incident to have suffered the faithful old creature to have witnessed her
     favourite's wedding, and then to have been forthwith killed out of the way, by—perishing in the
     vestry. However, things were ordered otherwise, and Jeanie Mackie did not live to see the
     wedding: if you wish to know how and where she died, let me tell you at once.</p>
    <p>Scotland—Argyleshire—Glenmuir; this was the focus of her hopes and thoughts—that poor old
     Indian exile! She had left it, as a buxom bright-haired lassie: but oaks had now grown old that
     she had planted acorns; and grandmothers had died palsied, whom she remembered born; still,
     around the mountains and the lakes, those changeless features of her girlhood's rugged home,
     the old woman's memory wandered; they were pictured in her mind's eye hard, and clear, and
     definite as if she looked upon them now. And her soul's deep hope was to see them once
     again.</p>
    <p>There was yet another object which made her yearn for Scotland. Lieutenant Stuart had been
     the younger of two brothers, the eldest born of whom became, upon his father's, the old
     laird's, death, Glenmuir and Glenmurdock. Now, though twice married, this elder brother, the
     new laird, never had a child; and the clear consequence was, that Amy Stuart was likely to
     become sole heiress of her ancestor's possessions. The lieutenant's marriage with an Italian
     and a Romanist had been, doubtless, any thing but pleasant to his friends; the strict old
     Presbyterians, and the proud unsullied family of Stuart, could not palate it at all.
     Nevertheless, he did marry the girl, according to the rites of both churches, and there was an
     end of it; so, innumerable proverbs coming to their aid about "curing and enduring" and "must
     be's," and the place where "marriages are made," etc., the several aunts and cousins were
     persuaded at length to wink at the iniquity, and to correspond both with Mrs. James and her
     backsliding lieutenant. Of the offspring of that marriage, and her orphaned state, and of Mrs.
     Mackie's care, and the indefinite detention in central Hindostan, they had heard often-times;
     for, as there is no corner of the world where a Scot may not be met with, so, with laudable
     nationality, they all hang together; and Glenmuir was written to frequently, all about the
     child, through Jeanie Mackie, "her mark," and a scholarly sergeant, Duncan Blair.</p>
    <p>Amy's rights—or Emmy let us call her still, as Charles did—were now, therefore, the next
     object of Mrs. Mackie's zeal; and all parties
     <pb n="97"/>interested willingly listened to the plan of spending one or two of those weary
     weeks in rubbing up relationships in Scotland; the general also was not a little anxious about
     heritage and acres. Accordingly, off they set in the new travelling-carriage, with due notice
     of approach, heartily welcomed, to Dunstowr Castle, the fine old feudal stronghold of Robert
     Stuart, Laird of Glenmuir and Glenmurdock.</p>
    <p>The journey, the arrival, and the hearty hospitality; and how the gray old chieftain kissed
     his pretty niece; and how welcome her betrothed Charles and her kind life-long guardian, and
     her faithful nurse were made; and how the beacons blazed upon the hill-tops, and the mustering
     clan gathered round about old Dunstowr; and how the laird presented to them all their beautiful
     future mistress, and how Jeanie Mackie and her documents travelled up to Edinburgh, where
     writers to the signet pestered her heart-sick with over-caution; and how the case was all
     cleared up, and the distant disappointed cousin, who had irrationally hoped to be the heir, was
     gladdened, if not satisfied, with a pension and a cantle of Glenmuir; and how all was
     joyfulness and feasting, when Amy Stuart was acknowledged in her rights—the bagpipes and the
     wassail, salmon, and deer, and black-cock, with a river of mountain dew: let others tell who
     know Dunstowr; for as I never was there, of course I cannot faithfully describe it. Should such
     an historian as I condescend to sheer inventions?</p>
    <p>With respect to Jeanie Mackie, I could learn no more than this: she was sprightly and lively,
     and strong as ever, though in her ninetieth year, till her foster-child was righted, and the
     lawyers had allowed her her claim. But then there seemed nothing else to live for; so her life
     gradually faded from her eye, as an expiring candle; and she would doze by the hour, sitting on
     a settle in the sun, basking her old heart in the smile of those old mountains. None knew when
     she died, to a minute; for she died sitting in the sun, in the smile of those old
     mountains.</p>
    <p>They buried her, with much of rustic pomp, in the hill-church of Glenmuir, where all her
     fathers slept around her; and Emily and Charles, hand-in-hand, walked behind her coffin
     mournfully.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <pb n="98"/>
    <head>CHAPTER XXX.</head>
    <head>FINAL.</head>
    <p>Gladly would the laird have had marriage at Dunstower, and have given away the beauteous
     bride himself: but there must still be two months more of decent mourning, and the general had
     long learned to sigh for the maligned delights of Burleigh Singleton. So, Glenmuir could only
     get a promise of reappearance some fine summer or other: and, after another day's
     deer-stalking, which made the general repudiate telescopes from that day forth (the poor man's
     eyes had actually grown lobster-like with straining after antlers)—the travelling-carriage, and
     four lean kine from Inverary, whisked away the trio towards the South.</p>
    <p>And now, in due time, were the Tamworths full of joy—congratulating, sympathizing,
     merrymaking; and the three young ladies behaved admirably in the capacity of pink and silver
     bridesmaids; while George proved equally kind in attending (as he called it) Charles's
     "execution," wherein he was "turned off;" and the admiral, G.C.B. was so hand-in-glove with the
     general, H.E.I.C.S., that I have reason to believe they must have sworn eternal friendship,
     after the manner of the modern Germans.</p>
    <p>How beautiful our Emmy looked—I hate the broad Scotch Aamy—how bright her flashing eyes, and
     how fragrantly the orange-blossoms clustered in her rich brown hair; let him speak lengthily,
     whose province it may be to spin three volumes out of one: for me, I always wish to recollect
     that readers possess, on the average, at least as much imagination as writers. And why should
     you not exercise it now? Is not Emmy in her bridal-dress a theme well worth a revery?</p>
    <p>For a similar reason, I must clearly disappoint feminine expectation, by forbearing to
     descant upon Charles's slight but manly form, and his Grecian beauty, etc., all the better for
     the tropics, and the trials and the troubles he had passed.</p>
    <p>When Captain Forbes, just sitting down to his soup in the Jamaica Coffee-house, read in the
     <hi>Morning Post</hi>, the marriage of Charles Tracy with Amy Stuart, he delivered himself
     mentally as follows:</p>
    <p>"There now! Poets talk of 'love,' and I stick to 'human nature.' When that fine young fellow
     sailed with me, hardly a year ago, in the Sir William Elphinston, he was over head and heels in
     love with old
     <pb n="99"/> Jack Tracy's pretty girl, Emily Warren: but I knew it wouldn't last long: I don't
     believe in constancy for longer than a week. It does one's heart good to see how right one is;
     here's what I call proof. My sentimental spark kisses Emily Warren, and marries Amy Stuart."
     The captain, happier than before, called complacently for Cayenne pepper, and relished his
     mock-turtle with a higher gusto.</p>
    <p>It is worth recording, that the same change of name mystified slanderous friends in the
     Presidency of Madras.</p>
    <p>And now, kind-eyed reader, this story of '<hi>The Twins</hi>' must leave off abruptly at the
     wedding. As in its companion-tale, '<hi>The Crock of Gold</hi>,' one grand thesis for our
     thoughts was that holy wise command, "Thou shall not covet," and as its other comrade
     '<hi>Heart</hi>' is founded on "Thou shalt not bear false witness," so in this, the seed-corn
     of the crop, were five pure words, "Thou shalt not commit adultery." Other morals doubtless
     grew up round us, for all virtue hangs together in a bunch: the harms of secresy, false
     witness, inordinate affections, and red murder: but in chief, as we have said.</p>
    <p>Moreover, I wish distinctly to make known, for dear "domestic" sake, that so far from our
     lovers' happiness having been consummated (that is, finished) in the honey-moon—it was only
     then begun. How long they are to live thus happily together, Heaven, who wills all things good,
     alone can tell; I wish them three score years. Little ones, I hear, arrive annually—to the
     unqualified joy, not merely of papa and mamma, but also of our communicative old general, his
     friend the G.C.B., and (all but most of any) the Laird of Glenmuir and Glenmurdock, whose heart
     has been entirely rejoiced by Charles Tracy having added to his name, and to his children's
     names, that of Stuart.</p>
    <p>Mr. and Mrs. Tracy Stuart are often at Glenmuir; but oftener at Burleigh, where the general,
     I fancy, still resides. He protests that he never will keep a secret again: long may he live to
     say so!</p>
    <trailer>THE END</trailer>
   </div>
  </body>

 </text>
</TEI>
