<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:t="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ENG18631"
 xml:lang="en">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Heart and Cross : ELTec edition</title>
    <author ref="viaf:49256072">Oliphant, Margaret (1828-1897).</author>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>ELTeC conversion</resp>
     <name>Lou Burnard</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent><measure unit="words">48020</measure><measure unit="pages">222</measure></extent>
   <publicationStmt>
    <p>Published as part of ELTeC <date>2020-04-28</date></p>
   </publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc>
    <bibl type="digitalSource"><title>The Project Gutenberg eBook of Heart and Cross, by Mrs.
      Oliphant..</title><ref target="gut:53645">Gutenberg</ref>
     <respStmt>
      <resp>Produced by </resp>
      <name>Chuck Greif and the Online Distributed Proofreading Team</name>
     </respStmt></bibl>
    <bibl type="firstEdition" n="B7679"><title>Heart and Cross</title><author>Oliphant, Margaret
      (1828-1897).</author><publisher>London: Hurst and Blackett</publisher><date>1863</date>
     <ref target="http://www.oliphantfiction.com/fiction_works/Heart_and_Cross.pdf"/></bibl>
   </sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc n="eltec-1">
   <p/>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
   </langUsage>
   <textDesc>
    <authorGender xmlns="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns" key="F"/>
    <size xmlns="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns" key="short"/>
    <reprintCount xmlns="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns" key="low"/>
    <timeSlot xmlns="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns" key="T2"/>
   </textDesc>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
   <change when="2020-04-28">LB convert to ELTeC-1</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="T2FSL">
  <front>
   <div type="titlepage">
    <gap unit="graphic"/>

    <p>HEART AND CROSS.</p>
    <p>BY </p>
    <p> MRS. OLIPHANT. </p>
    <p>AUTHOR OF “MARGARET MAITLAND,” “ADAM GRAEME,” “THE LAST OF THE MORTIMERS,” “THE LAIRD OF
     MORLAW,” ETC., ETC. </p>
    <p>IN ONE VOLUME. </p>
    <p>NEW YORK: JAMES   G.   GREGORY. 1863.</p>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>

   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER I.</head>
    <p><hi>I know</hi> no reason why I should begin my story of the fortunes of the Harleys by a
     description of my own son. Perhaps it is just because there is no reason whatever that I feel
     so much disposed to do it—also because the appearance of that son is the only difference that
     has come to my own life since last my unknown friends heard of me, and because there is quite
     an exhilaration in thinking that here is a new audience to whom I am at liberty to introduce
     the second Derwent Crofton. This story is not in the least about my boy, and, in consequence,
     it is quite an unusual delight to be able to drag him in head and shoulders. Women are not
     logical, as everybody knows.</p>
    <p>My son, then, is, at the present writing, exactly
     <pb n="006"/> seven years old. He is a little athlete—straight and strong. We have often
     explained to ourselves that it is in consequence of his having got over the baby period of
     existence sooner than most children do, that he is not quite so plump, as, for example, that
     red and white heir of the Sedgwicks, who has a succession of rosy cushions on all the points
     where there should be angles of his small frame. Derwent, I confess, has corners about him—but
     then what limbs! what color! what hard, consistent stuff the little rogue is made of! And I am
     not quite sure that I entirely approve of these fat children—not when they are past the
     baby-age. I will not delude myself, nor anybody else, into the idea that the boy is very
     clever. Truth to speak, he has not taken very kindly as yet to book-learning; but then does not
     everybody remember that it is the dunces who grow into great men? Neither is he in the
     slightest degree meditative or thoughtful, nor what you would call an interesting child. He has
     as many scars upon him as a warrior, and has been bumped and bruised in all directions. At
     first the child’s misfortunes somewhat alarmed me, but by this time I am hardened to their
     daily occurrence, and no longer grow pale when I am informed that Master Derwent has broken his
     head or got a bad fall. This
     <pb n="007"/> peculiarity is one in which his father rather rejoices. I hear Mr. Crofton
     sometimes privately communicating to his especial friends the particulars of little Derwent’s
     accidents: “He was certainly born to knock about the world, that boy of mine. Such a fellow was
     never intended to take peaceable possession of Hilfont, and settle down a calm country
     gentleman,” says Derwent, with a chuckle. And even when once or twice in the child’s life my
     husband’s fears have been really excited about some misadventure greater than usual, there has
     always been visible to me a certain gleam of complacence and pride in his fear. For already he
     sees in the boy, whom I am half disposed to keep a baby as long as possible, a man—the heir of
     his own personal qualities as well as his land.</p>
    <p>Little Derwent, however, has none of the sentimental qualities, which might be expected from
     an only child. He has indemnified himself in the oddest fashion for the want of those nursery
     friendships which sweeten the beginning of life. In the oddest fashion! I am almost ashamed to
     confess—I admit it with natural blushes and hesitation—that this little boy of ours is the most
     inveterate gossip that ever was born! Yes, there is no use disguising the fact, gossiping,
     plain, naked, and unsophisticated, is the special faculty
     <pb n="008"/> of Derwent. He has all the natural childish thirst for a story, but he prefers to
     have his stories warm from the lips of the heroes and heroines of the same; and somehow
     everybody to whom he has access confides in the child. He goes through every corner of Hilfont,
     from cellar to attic, with his bold, quick step, and his bright, curious eyes, interested about
     every individual under the roof. Too young to feel any of those sentiments which detract from
     the value of a sympathizer—without either the condescension of a superior or the
     self-comparison of an equal—I find nobody who is not pleased and comforted by the child’s warm
     interest in their concerns; pleased and half amused as well—till, by habit, housekeeper and
     nurse, kitchenmaid and groom—for any efforts I might once have made to keep Derwent a proper
     little boy, circulating only in an orthodox round between the drawing-room and the nursery,
     have proved so totally fruitless, that I have given up the endeavor—repose a flattered but
     perfectly sincere confidence in their master’s little son. Nor is the village at all stoical to
     his attractions. He drops in at all the cottages as if he were the curate or the parish
     doctor—asks questions about everything—never forgets any special circumstances which may happen
     to have been told him—knows all about
     <pb n="009"/> the old women’s marriages and the number of their children, and which one’s son
     has been wild and ’listed, and which one’s daughter is at service in Simonborough. He is ready
     for as many fairy tales as anybody will tell him; but nothing is so thoroughly interesting to
     Derwent as the people round about him and their homely lives. I began by being a little shocked
     at this propensity of his—then gradually grew amused at it—then tried my utmost to restrain
     that deep inquisitiveness which seemed inherent in him—and at last have come to accept it
     quietly as the child’s peculiarity, a part of himself. If the best object for the study of
     mankind is man, Derwent will, perhaps, some day turn out a great philosopher. At present he is
     the most sincere and simple-minded of little gossips, pursuing his favorite branch of knowledge
     boldly, without any compunctions; such is the most distinct and remarkable characteristic of my
     son.</p>
    <p>And only to imagine the difference which that pair of blue eyes has wrought in our great
     house and our calm life! My husband and I were, to be sure, “very happy,” as people say,
     before; as happy as two people can make each other, by a hearty and sincere love and cordial
     union; the climax of happiness we would have thought it, each in our separate thoughts, when we lived
     <pb n="010"/> lonely lives apart. But love, which makes labor sweet and life pleasant, does not
     answer for daily bread—never does, let the romancers say what they will; no—not even to women.
     The heart within me was dissatisfied even with Derwent—I could not content myself with that
     life we lived—that calm, happy, tranquil life, which knew no burdens, and if it overflowed in
     courtesies and charities, which cost us nothing, was thought a model existence by our
     hard-working neighbors.</p>
    <p>By dint of perpetual pin-pricks and unceasing agitation, I had managed to drive Derwent into
     Parliament, where he somewhat solaced me by his intense affliction and sufferings during the
     season of Parliamentary martyrdom, and was himself happier during the rest of the year in the
     relief of escaping that treadmill; but the content that had fluttered off from my heart, when I
     had only my husband and myself to think of, came with a flash of magic in the train of the
     little heir. All life glowed and brightened up with a different interest—there were no longer
     only ourselves who had attained all that was attainable in our own mature and settled
     existence; but this new living, loving creature, with all the possibilities of life burning
     upon his fresh horizon. The picture changed as if by enchantment; the
     <pb n="011"/> master and mistress of that tranquil great house—lone, happy people set apart,
     none of the changes of life coming near them, living for themselves, changed into a father and
     mother, linked by sweet ties of succession to the other generations of the world; belonging not
     to ourselves, but to the past and the future—to the coming age, which <hi>he</hi> should
     influence—to the former age, which had hailed <hi>our</hi> entrance as we hailed <hi>his</hi>.
     One cannot be content with the foot-breadth of human soil that supports one’s own weight—one
     must thrust out one’s hands before and behind. I felt that we fell into our due place in the
     world’s generations, and laid hold upon the lineal chain of humanity when little Derwent went
     forth before us, trusted to our guidance—the next generation—the Future to us, as to the world.
     <pb n="012"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
    <p>“<hi>I suppose</hi>, Clare,” said Mr. Crofton to me one morning at breakfast, “that Alice
     Harley has made up her mind, like somebody I once knew, to live for other people, and on no
     account to permit herself to be married—is it so?”</p>
    <p>“I really cannot undertake to say whether she is like that person you once knew,” said I,
     somewhat demurely. I had some hopes that she was—I was much inclined to imagine that it was a
     youthful prepossession, of which, perhaps, she herself was unaware, that kept Alice Harley an
     unmarried woman; but of course I was not going to say so even to Derwent, who, with all his
     good qualities, was after all only a man. An unmarried woman!—that I should call my pretty
     Alice by that harsh, mature, common-place name! But I am sorry to say the appellation was quite
     a just one. She was nearer eight and twenty than eighteen, now-a-days; she had no love, no
     engagement, no sentimental gossip at all to be made about her. I will not undertake to say
     <pb n="013"/> that she had not some ideas of another kind, with which I had but a very limited
     sympathy—but an unmarried woman Alice Harley was, and called herself—with (I thought) a little
     quiet secret interest, which she deeply resented any suspicion of, in Indian military
     affairs.</p>
    <p>“Because,” said Derwent, with the old affectionate laugh, and glance of old love-triumph over
     his old wife, which he never outgrew or exhausted, “there is that very good fellow, our new
     Rector, would give his ears for such a wife—and from all I can see, would suit her famously;
     which, by the way, Clare, now that her mother is so dependent on her, is not what every man
     would. You should say a good word for Reredos—it is your duty to look after your protégée’s
     establishment in life.”</p>
    <p>I confess when Derwent said these words a great temptation came to me. It suddenly flashed
     upon my mind that Alice in the Rectory would be my nearest neighbor, and the most pleasant of
     possible companions. At the same moment, and in the light of that momentary selfish
     illumination, it also became suddenly visible to me that my dear girl had a great many notions
     which I rather disapproved of, and was rapidly confirming herself in that <hi>rôle</hi> of
     unmarried woman, which, having once rather taken to
     <pb n="014"/> it myself, I knew the temptations of. Mr. Reredos was only about five years older
     than herself, good-looking, well-connected, with a tolerably good living, and a little fortune
     of his own. And how could I tell whether my private designs would ever come to anything?
     Derwent, simple-minded man, had not fallen on so potent an argument for many a day before.</p>
    <p>“Mamma,” said little Derwent, who heard everything without listening, “the housekeeper at the
     Rectory has a son in the Guards—like the men in the steel-coats that you showed me when we went
     to London; the other sons are all comfortable, she says; but this one, when she speaks of
      <hi>him</hi>, she puts up her apron to her eyes. Mamma, I want to know if it is wicked to go
     for a soldier—Sally Yeoman’s son ’listed last year, and <hi>she</hi> puts up her apron to her
     eyes. Now, my cousin Bertie is in India—was it wicked in him to go for a soldier?—or what’s the
     good of people being sad when people ’list?—eh, mamma?”</p>
    <p>“Did you ever see anybody sad about your cousin Bertie?” said I, with a sudden revulsion of
     feeling and the profoundest interest.</p>
    <p>“N—no,” said little Derwent. He applied himself after that devoutly to his bread and
     jam—there was something not altogether assured in
     <pb n="015"/> the sound of that “N—no.” Derwent could not help having quick eyes—but the child
     knew sometimes that it was best to hold his tongue.</p>
    <p>“I should like to know,” said Derwent the elder, laughing, “why Mr. Reredos’s housekeeper’s
     son in the Guards has been dragged headlong into this consultation. Suppose you go for a
     soldier yourself, Derwie. There’s your drum in the corner. I have something to say to
     mamma.”</p>
    <p>Little Derwent marched off, obedient, if not very willing. His inquisitive tendencies did not
     carry him beyond that rule of obedience which was the only restraint I put upon the boy.
     Derwent, elder, followed him with happy looks. He only came back to his subject after an
     interval of pleased and silent observation when there suddenly fell into the stillness of our
     cheerful breakfast-room the first thunder of Derwie’s drum.</p>
    <p>“What an inquisitive little imp it is!” said Derwent; “but in spite of the housekeeper’s son
     in the Guards, I don’t think you could do a more charitable action, Clare, than to support
     Reredos’s suit to Alice Harley. Such a famous thing for both—and such an excellent neighbor for
     yourself.”</p>
    <p>“That is very true,” said I; “but still I cannot help building something upon that son in the Guards.”
     <pb n="016"/></p>
    <p>Mr. Crofton looked up somewhat puzzled, with a smile upon his lips. I daresay he asked, “What
     on earth do you mean?” somewhat exasperated at the repetition; but Derwie’s drum filled all the
     apartment at the moment, and of course I could not hear, much less answer him. We had some
     further talk on the subject later, when Derwent called me into the library to read over that
     speech of his, which he made a few evenings before at Simonborough, and which the Editor of the
     Simonborough Chronicle had sent over in proof to ask if my husband would kindly glance over it
     and see if it was correct. Mr. Reredos was coming to dinner to meet the Harleys, among other
     people—and Mr. Crofton, always good-humored, and disposed to aid and abet all honest love
     affairs, could not sufficiently point out the advantages of such a connection to me.</p>
    <p>And I said no more to perplex him, of the son in the Guards; but for myself remembered that
     mythical personage, whatever was said to me on the subject; and appreciated with the highest
     admiration that singularly delicate line of association which suggested the reference to little
     Derwie’s mind and thoughts. Yes, to be sure! the old women will put up their aprons to their
     eyes when they talk about the son who has ’listed;
     <pb n="017"/> the young women will keep a shadowy corner in their hearts for that
     unfortunate—and yet it is not wicked to go for a soldier. I felt Mr. Reredos’s handsome figure
     quite blotted out by the suggestion conveyed in that of his housekeeper’s son. When I had
     finished my housekeeping affairs, and given orders about the visitors we expected for
     Easter—this I should have said was the Easter recess, the glimpse of spring at Hilfont, which
     was all we could catch now that Derwent, to his great affliction, was a Parliament man—I took
     my seat in the great cheerful window of that room where we had breakfasted, and which
     overlooked half the country. Far away in the distance the sun caught the spires and roofs of
     Simonborough, with its cathedral faintly shining out from among the lower level of the
     housetops, and nearer at hand struck bright upon the slow and timid river which wound through
     the fields down below us, at the bottom of this great broad slope of country, which had no
     pretensions to be a hill, though its advantage of altitude in our level district was greater
     than that of many an elevation twice or three times as high. Spring was stealing into the long
     drooping branches of those willows which marked the irregular line of the stream. Spring
     brightened with doubtful, wavering dewy
     <pb n="018"/> smiles over all the surface of the country. I remember when I should have been
     glad to turn my eyes indoors, away from the sweet suggestions of Nature conveyed by that
     sweetest and most suggestive season; but I took the fullest and freest enjoyment of it now;
     rather, I sat at the window calmly pleased and unconscious, as we are when we are happy,
     feeling no contrast to wound me between the world without and the world within—and considered
     fully the circumstances of Alice Harley, and how I ought to forward, as Derwent said, my dear
     girl’s establishment in life.</p>
    <p>Now I have to confess that many years before this I had formed my own plans for Alice—had
     quite made up my mind, indeed, to a secret scheme of match-making in which at the moment I had
     been grievously disappointed. At that time, when little Derwie was undreampt of, and I had
     prematurely made up my mind to a childless life, I had settled my inheritance of Estcourt upon
     my young cousin Bertie Nugent, with a strong hope that the boy, who had known her for so many
     years, would naturally prefer my pretty Alice to all strangers, when his good fortune and
     affectionate heart put marriage into his head. This did not turn out the case, however. Bertie
     made his choice otherwise, was
     <pb n="019"/> disappointed, and went off to India, where for eight long years he had remained.
     Sometimes, when he wrote to me, I found a message of good wishes to his old playmates at the
     very end of the page; once or twice it had occurred to him to ask, “Is not Alice Harley
     married?” but the question seemed to proceed rather from surprise and curiosity than any tender
     interest. It is impossible to imagine a greater separation than there was between these two.
     Bertie, now Captain Herbert Nugent, at a remote station in the Bengal Presidency, where,
     scattered over that vast, arid country, he had friends, brothers, and cousins by the dozen; and
     Alice, with her new-fangled notions, and staid single-woman dignity, hid away in the depths of
     a quiet English home, where she addressed herself to her duty and the education of her little
     sisters and eschewed society. Whether any secret thoughts of each other lingered in their minds
     nobody of course could tell; but they certainly had not, except in my persistent thoughts, a
     single bond of external connection. So long as they were both unmarried, I could not help
     putting them together with an imagination which longed for the power of giving efficacy to its
     dreams; but nobody else had ever done so—there were thousands of miles of land and water
     dividing them—many long
     <pb n="020"/> years, and most likely a world of dissimilar dispositions, experiences and
     thoughts.</p>
    <p>While on the other hand Mr. Reredos was actually present on the scene, in a pretty Rectory
     just half a mile from my own house, and not a dozen miles from Mrs. Harley’s cottage. The young
     clergyman lost no opportunity of doing his duty towards that lady, though her dwelling was
     certainly in another parish—and showed himself so far disposed towards Alice’s new-fangled
     notions as to preach a sermon upon the changed position and new duties of Woman, on the
     occasion of her last visit to Hilfont. I trust it edified Alice, for it had rather a contrary
     effect upon myself, and filled the parishioners generally with the wildest amazement. Most
     people are flattered by such an adoption of their own opinions—and a young woman aged
     twenty-seven, thinking herself very old, and trying hard to make every one else believe the
     same, is especially open to such a compliment. Besides, I could not say anything even to myself
     against Mr. Reredos. He was well-bred, well-looking, and well-dispositioned—the match would be
     particularly suitable in every way. Dr. Harley’s daughter, had her father and his fortune
     survived till the present day, would still have made quite a sensible marriage in accepting the
     Rector of Hilfont.
     <pb n="021"/> And then the advantage of having her so near!</p>
    <p>I sat in the great window of the breakfast-room, looking over half the county. If I had been
     a woman of elevated mind or enlightened views, I should have been thinking of all the human
     wishes and disappointments that lay beneath my eyes, each one under its own roof and its own
     retirement. But, on the contrary, I observed nothing but a small figure on a small pony
     ascending the road from the village. In the same way I ought to have been benevolently glad
     that our excellent young Rector had inclined his eyes and heart towards my own favorite and
     friend—the friend and favorite now of so many years—and that a home so suitable, at once to her
     origin and her tastes, awaited the acceptance of Alice. But I was not glad—I sent my thoughts
     ever so far away to Bertie’s bungalow, and felt aggrieved and disappointed for the boy who,
     alas! was a boy no longer, and most likely, instead of feeling aggrieved on his own account,
     would have nothing but his warmest congratulations to send when he heard of his old playmate’s
     marriage. Things are very perverse and unmanageable in this world. The right people will not
     draw together, let one wish it ever so strongly, whereas the wrong people are always
     approaching each
     <pb n="022"/> other in eccentric circles, eluding every obstacle which one can place in their
     way. I could not be very melancholy on the subject, because the pony and its little rider came
     every moment nearer, and brightened the face of the earth to my eyes—but still it was in the
     highest degree provoking. If it ever came to anything! There was still that escape from this
     perplexing matter; for whether I felt disposed to support his suit or not, it was still by no
     means certain, even when Mr. Reredos had finally declared himself, what Alice Harley might say.
     <pb n="023"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
    <p>“<hi>Who</hi> are we to have, Clare?—let us hear. You don’t suppose that my mind, weighed
     down with the responsibilities of law-making, can remember everything, eh?—even my wife’s
     guests?” said Derwent, rubbing his hands, as we sat after dinner near the fire in the warm
     crimson dining-room. When we were alone I gave Mr. Crofton’s claret my benign countenance till
     he was ready to go with me to the drawing-room. There were not enough of us to separate at that
     genial hour, especially as little Derwent sat between us peeling his orange, and quite ready to
     give his opinion on any knotty point that might occur.</p>
    <p>“Papa, please give Willie Sedgwick the little grey pony,” said Derwie, “to ride when he’s
     here; he says his papa will never let him take his horse anywhere with him—there’s such a lot
     of children,” added my boy, parenthetically, with some pity and contempt. “I like little Clary
     best—I like her because her name’s the same as mamma’s, and because she has blue eyes, and
     because she
     <pb n="024"/> likes me, and she’s good to that poor old nurse, too, who has her daughter in a
     fever, and daren’t go to see her.”</p>
    <p>“How do you know about the nurse’s daughter’s fever, Derwie?” asked I.</p>
    <p>“Mamma, they sent <hi>me</hi> to the nursery, when you were calling there,” said Derwie, with
     some emphasis, “and she told me she has the scarlet fever, and Mrs. Sedgwick won’t let her
     mamma go to see her, for fear of the children taking it—isn’t it a shame? Clary told me she
     said her prayers for her every night, to get her well; and so,” said Derwent, coloring, and
     looking up with some apparent idea that this was not perfectly right, and the most manful
     intention to stand out the consequences, “and so do I.”</p>
    <p>His father and I looked at each other, and neither of us said anything just for that moment,
     which silence emboldened Derwie to believe that no harm was coming of his confession, and to go
     on with his story.</p>
    <p>“And Mr. Sedgwick’s man—he’s such a funny fellow. I wish you’d ask him to tell you one of his
     stories, mamma,” said Derwie, “for I know he’s coming here with them. He has a brother like
     Johnny Harley—just as lame—and he got cured in Wales, at St. Winifred’s Well. Why don’t you ask
     Mrs. Harley to send Johnny to
     <pb n="025"/> St. Winifred’s Well, mamma?—she only laughed at me when I said so. I say, mamma,”
     continued Derwie, with his mouth full of his orange, “I’ll tell Russell he’s to tell you one of
     his stories—I never knew a fellow that could tell such famous stories—I wish you had a man like
     Russell, papa. He’s been all over the world, and he’s got two children at home, and the name of
     one of them is John—John Russell—like the little gentleman in <hi>Punch</hi>.”</p>
    <p>“Don’t be personal, Derwie,” said Mr. Crofton, laughing; “we are to have Mr. Sedgwick’s
     Russell, and Mrs. Sedgwick’s nurse—who else?”</p>
    <p>“The Harleys,” said I, “for we’ll postpone for a little, if you please, Derwie, your friends
     below-stairs; and Mr. Reredos and his sister, and Miss Polly Greenfield, and her little nieces.
     I fear the womankind will rather predominate in our Easter party—though Maurice Harley, to be
     sure”——</p>
    <p>“Yes—Maurice Harley, to be sure,” said Derwent, still with a smile, “is—what should you call
     him now, Clare—a host in himself?”</p>
    <p>“Fellow of Exeter College, Cambridge,” said I, demurely; “he has it on his card.”</p>
    <p>“Mamma, is Maurice Harley a clergyman?—shouldn’t a clergyman care about people?” said
     <pb n="026"/> little Derwent; “I don’t think <hi>he</hi> does. He likes books.”</p>
    <p>“And what do you mean by people?—and don’t you like books?” I asked.</p>
    <p>“Oh! yes, sometimes,” said my son; “when there’s pictures in them. But <hi>you</hi> know what
     people mean, mamma—quite well! You talk to them, <hi>you</hi> do—but Maurice Harley puts up his
     shoulders like this, and looks more tired than Bob Dawkes does after his ploughing—so
     tired—just as if he could drop down with tiredness. Oh!” cried Derwent, with a sudden burst of
     enthusiasm, “I would not give our Johnnie for a hundred of <hi>him</hi>.”</p>
    <p>“A hundred of <hi>him</hi>!” I confess the thought filled me with alarm. In my heart I
     doubted, with a little shudder of apprehension, whether the country, not to speak of Hilfont,
     could have survived the invasion of a hundred such accomplished men. “But, Derwie,” said I,
     recovering from that shock, “if you do not like books except when they have pictures in them,
     how do you think you are ever to learn all the things that Maurice Harley knows?”</p>
    <p>“Mr. Sedgwick says he’s a prig,” says little Derwent, with great seriousness, “and I know
     more things now than he does—I know how to make rabbits’ houses. If you were to get some
     <pb n="027"/> little white rabbits, mamma, I could make a beautiful house for them. Will Morris
     taught me how. Oh! papa, don’t you know Will Morris wants to marry little Susan at the shop?—he
     has her picture, and it’s not the least like her, and I heard Maurice Harley say the
     photographs <hi>must</hi> be like, because the sun took them. Does the sun see better than
     other people? That one’s like you with the paper in your hand; but Will Morris’s picture,
     instead of being Susan, is anybody in a checked dress.”</p>
    <p>“I begin to think you will turn out a great critic, Derwie,” said his admiring father, who
     desired no better than to spend his after-dinner hour listening to the wisdom of his son.</p>
    <p>“What’s a critic? is it anything like a prig?” asked Derwent, who was trying hard to set up
     the crooked stem of a bunch of raisins—now, alas, denuded of every vestige of its fruit—like a
     tree upon his plate; the endeavor was not very successful, although when propped up on each
     side by little mounds of orange-peel, the mimic tree managed to hold a very slippery and
     precarious footing, and for a few minutes kept itself upright. We two sat looking at this
     process in a hush of pleased and interested observation. Maurice Harley, with all his powers
     and pretensions, could neither have done nor said anything
     <pb n="028"/> which could thus have absorbed us, and I doubt whether we would have looked at
     the highest triumphs of art or genius with admiration as complete as that with which we
     regarded little Derwie setting up the stalk of the bunch of raisins between these little mounds
     of orange-peel.</p>
    <p>“Clare, how old is he now?” said Mr. Crofton to me.</p>
    <p>As if he did not know! but I answered with calm pride, “Seven on Monday, Derwent—and you
     remember it was Easter Monday too that year—and tall for his age, certainly—but he is not so
     stout as Willie Sedgwick.”</p>
    <p>“Ah, Monday’s your birthday, is it, old fellow?” said Derwent; “what should you like on your
     birthday, Derwie—let us hear?”</p>
    <p>“May I have anything I like, papa?” asked the child, throwing down immediately both the
     raisin-stalk and the orange-skin. His father nodded in assent. I, a little in terror of what
     “anything I like” at seven years old might happen to be, hastened to interpose.</p>
    <p>“Anything in reason, Derwie, dear—not the moon, you know, nor the crown, nor an impossible
     thing. You are a very sensible little boy when you please; think of something in papa’s
     power.”</p>
    <p>“It is only little babies that cry for the moon,”
     <pb n="029"/> said Derwie, contemptuously, “and I’ve got it in the stereoscope—and what’s the
     good of it if one had it? nobody lives there; but, papa, I’ll tell you what I should like—give
     me the key of the door of the House of Commons, where you go every day when we are in town.
     That’s what I should like for my birthday; what makes you laugh?” continued my boy, coming to a
     sudden pause and growing red, for he was deeply susceptible to ridicule, bold as he was.</p>
    <p>“Why on earth do you want to go to the House of Commons?” cried his father, when his laughter
     permitted him to speak.</p>
    <p>“It’s in the Bible that the people used to come to tell everything to the king,” said Derwie,
     a little peevishly; “and isn’t the House of Commons instead of the king in this country? and
     doesn’t everybody go to the House of Commons when they want anything? I should like to see them
     all coming and telling their stories—what fun it must be! That’s why you go there, I suppose,
     every night? but I don’t know why you never should take mamma or me.”</p>
    <p>“It would never do to let the ladies come in,” said Derwent, with mock seriousness; “you know
     they would talk so much that we could never hear what the people had to say.”</p>
    <p>“Mamma does not talk very much,” said Derwie,
     <pb n="030"/> sharply; “nor Alice either. Old Mrs. Sedgwick, to be sure—but then it’s some good
     when she talks; it isn’t all about books or things I can’t understand, it’s about people—that’s
     real talk, that is. Before I go to school—just till this session is over—oh, papa, will you
     give me that key?”</p>
    <p>“My boy,” said Derwent, with the love and the laughter rivalling each other in his eyes,
     “they don’t give me any key, or you should have it—there’s a turnkey at the door, who opens it
     to let the poor people out and in; but some day you and mamma shall go and be shut up in a cage
     we have for the ladies, and hear all that’s said. I’m afraid, Derwie, when you’ve once been
     there you won’t want to go again.”</p>
    <p>“Yes, I shall!” cried Derwie, all his face glowing with eagerness; when there suddenly
     appeared a solemn and silent apparition at the door, namely Nurse, under whose iron rule the
     young gentleman, much resisting, was still held, so far at least as his toilette was concerned.
     That excellent woman said not a word. She opened the door with noiseless solemnity, came in,
     and stood smoothing down her spotless apron by the wall. No need for words to announce the
     presence of that messenger of fate; Derwie made some unavailing struggles with destiny, and at
     <pb n="031"/> last resigned himself and marched off defiantly, followed by the mighty Nemesis.
     When the door closed upon the well-preserved skirts of that brown silk gown, in which, ever
     since little Derwie emerged from babyhood, nurse had presented herself in the dining-room to
     fetch him to bed, Mr. Crofton and I once more looked at each other with those looks of fondness
     and praise and mutual congratulation which our boy had brought to our eyes. We had already
     exhausted all the phrases of parental wonder and admiration; we only looked at each other with
     a mutual tender delight and congratulation. Nobody else, surely, since the beginning of the
     world, ever had such a boy!
     <pb n="032"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER IV.</head>
    <p><hi>The</hi> next day after, being the Saturday, our little Easter party assembled; first our
     neighbors the Sedgwicks, who were a party in themselves. Ten years before, Hugh Sedgwick had
     been the finest gentleman in our neighborhood, which he filled with amazement and consternation
     when he chose to fall in love with and marry little Clara Harley, whom, in the most literal
     sense of the word, he married out of the school-room, and who was just seventeen years old. But
     now that five children had followed this marriage, nobody could have supposed or believed in
     the existence of any such great original contrast between the husband and wife. Either Mr.
     Sedgwick had grown younger, or Clara older, than their years. He who now called Maurice Harley
     a prig, had been himself the prince of prigs—according to the estimate of the country
     gentlemen, his neighbors—in his day; but that day was long departed. Hugh Sedgwick, fastidious,
     dilettante fine gentleman, as he had been, was now the
     <pb n="033"/> solicitous father of little children, and not above giving very sound advice upon
     measles and hooping-cough—while Clara, who had gradually blossomed out into fuller and fuller
     bloom, had scarcely yet attained the height of her soft beauty, despite the little flock of
     children round her. Nobody in the county made such a toilette as little Mrs. Sedgwick. I
     suspect she must have had <hi>carte blanche</hi> as to her milliner’s bills; and when they
     entered the Hilfont drawing-room, Clara, with her pretty matronly self-possession, her graceful
     little figure, round and full as one of her own babies, and her lovely little face, with all
     its cloudless lilies and roses—nobody could have believed in the time when his good neighbors
     shrugged their shoulders and laughed at Hugh Sedgwick’s choice. She sat down, I remember, by
     Miss Polly Greenfield—dear old Miss Polly in her primeval drapery—that crimson satin gown which
     I had known all my life. Such a contrast they made in the bright youth and pale age of the two
     faces, which came together lovingly in a kiss of greeting! Since her brother, Sir Willoughby,
     had married, Miss Polly’s habits had changed greatly. She had thrown aside her old brown
     riding-dress and the stiff man’s hat she used to wear when she rode with Sir Willoughby. And
     when her old horse and
     <pb n="034"/> her old groom were old enough to be pensioned off in their respective paddock and
     cottage, Miss Polly set up a pony-carriage, more suitable to her years. Her niece, a young
     widow of twenty, a poor, little, disconsolate soul, who was all the trouble in the world to
     Miss Polly, had made a second marriage, and left her two little children to the care of their
     grandaunt. They were little girls both, and the tender old woman was very happy in their
     society—happier a hundred times than when she had been mistress of Fenosier Hall. But to hear
     how little Clara, who once had stood somewhat in awe of Miss Polly, talked to her now!—advising
     her how to manage little Di and Emmy, telling how she regulated her own Clary, who, though a
     good deal younger, was very far on for her age—with what a sweet touch of superiority and
     simplicity the dear little matron looked down from her wifely and motherly elevation upon pale
     old Miss Polly, who was neither mother nor wife! Clara was quite ready at the same moment to
     have bestowed her matronly counsels upon me.</p>
    <p>After the Sedgwicks, Alice Harley, all by herself, as became one who felt herself at home,
     and was all but a daughter of the house, came into the room. Alice was plain in her dress to
     the extreme of plainness. That she assumed an
     <pb n="035"/> evening dress at all was somewhat against her convictions, and in compassion to
     my weakness and prejudice; but the dress was of dark colored silk, made with a studied sobriety
     of cut, and lack of ornament. Instead of sharing Clara’s round soft loveliness, Alice had grown
     slender and pale. Unimaginative people called her thin. Out of her girlish beauty had come a
     face full of thoughtfulness and expression, but not so pretty as some people expected—perhaps,
     because somehow or other, the ordinary roselight of youth had failed to Alice. Half by choice,
     half by necessity, she had settled down into the humdrum useful existence which the eldest
     daughter of a large family, if she does not elude her fate by an early marriage, so often falls
     into. Various “offers” had been made to her, one of which Mrs. Harley, divided between a
     mother’s natural wish to see her daughter properly “settled,” and a little reluctance, not less
     natural, to part with her own household counsellor and helper, had given a wavering support to.
     Alice, however, said No, coldly, and not, as I thought, without the minutest possible tinge of
     bitterness answered the persuasions which were addressed to her. She was rather high and
     grandiloquent altogether on the subject of marriage, looking on with a half-comic, disapproving
     spectator observation at
     <pb n="036"/> little Clara’s loving tricks to her husband, whom that little matron had no awe
     of now-a-days, and discoursing more than seemed to me entirely necessary upon the subject.
     Alice was somewhat inclined to the views of those philosophers (chiefly feminine, it must be
     confessed) who see in the world around them, not a general crowd of human creatures, but two
     distinct rows of men and women; and she was a little condescending and superior, it must also
     be admitted, to that somewhat frivolous antagonistic creature, man. The ideal man, whom Alice
     had never—so she intimated—had the luck to light upon, was a demigod; but the real male
     representatives of the race were poor creatures—well enough, to be sure, but no more worthy of
     a woman’s devotion than of any other superlative gift. With sentiments so distinct and
      <hi>prononcés</hi>, Alice had not lived all these years without feeling some yearning for an
     independent sway and place of her own, as one may well suppose—which tempted her into further
     speculations about women’s work, and what one could do to make a place for one’s self, who had
     positively determined not to be indebted for one’s position to one’s husband. Such was the
     peculiar atmosphere out of which Alice Harley revealed herself to the common world. She was
     deeply scornful of that talk
     <pb n="037"/> about people which pleased my boy so much, and so severe upon gossip and gossips,
     that I had on more than one occasion seriously to defend myself. There she stood in her
     dark-brown silk dress beside little Clara’s flowing toilette and vivacious nursery talk,
     casting a shadow upon pale Miss Polly in her crimson satin. Alice was as much unlike that
     tender old soul, with her old maidenly restraints and preciseness, her unbounded old womanly
     indulgence and kindness, as she was unlike her matronly younger sister; and I confess that to
     myself, in all her perverseness, knowing as I did what a genuine heart lay below, there was
     quite a charm of her own about the unmarried woman. She was so conscious of her staid and sober
     age, so unconscious of her pleasant youth, and the simplicity which, all unknown to herself,
     lay in her wisdom. Such was my Alice; the same Alice who, keeping silent and keeping her
     brothers and sisters quiet in the nursery, while she knew her father lay dying many a long year
     ago, adjured me with unspeakable childish pathos—“Oh, don’t be sorry for me! I mustn’t
     cry!”</p>
    <p>I do not know how it was that, while I contemplated Alice on her first appearance with a kind
     of retrospective glance at her history, there suddenly appeared above her the head of Mr.
     <pb n="038"/> Reredos. He was a middle-sized, handsome man, with a pale complexion and dark
     hair—very gentlemanly, people said—a man who preached well, talked well, and looked well, and
     who, even to my eyes, which were no way partial, had no particular defect worth noticing, if it
     were not the soft, large, white hands without any bones in them, which held your fingers in a
     warm, velvety clasp when you shook hands with the new rector. I don’t know how he had managed
     to come in without my perceiving him. And strong must have been the attraction which beguiled
     Mr. Reredos to neglect the duty of paying his respects to his hostess, even for five minutes.
     It was not five minutes, however, before he recollected himself, and came with his soft white
     hand and his sister on his arm. His sister was so far like himself that she was very pale, with
     very black hair, and an “interesting” look. She did not interest me very much; but I could not
     help hoping that perhaps in this sentimental heroine Maurice Harley, for the time being, might
     meet his fate. I thought that would be rather a comfortable way of shelving those members of
     our party; for Maurice, though he was a very fine gentleman, not to say Fellow of his College,
     afflicted my soul with a constant inclination to commit a personal assault
     <pb n="039"/> upon him, and have him whipped and sent to bed.</p>
    <p>However, to be sure, we had all the elements of a very pleasant party about us—people who
     belonged to us, as one may say. Derwent, who liked to see a number of cheerful faces about him,
     was in the lightest spirits; he paid Clara Sedgwick compliments on her toilette, and “chaffed”
     (as he called it—I am not responsible for the word) Alice, whom he had the sincerest affection
     for, but loved to tease, and took Miss Polly in to dinner, while little Derwie did the honors
     of the nursery to a party almost as large, and quite as various. I fear we made rather a night
     of feasting than a penitential vigil of that Easter Eve.
     <pb n="040"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER V.</head>
    <p><hi>When</hi> we returned to the drawing-room after dinner, we found, hidden in a distant
     corner, with books and portfolios, and stereoscopes blocking up the table near him, Johnnie
     Harley. I have said little of this boy. He was the proxy which the handsome, healthy family had
     given for their singular exemption from disease and weakness—the one sufferer, among many
     strong, who is so often found in households unexceptionably healthful, as if all the minor
     afflictions which might have been divided among them had concentrated on one and left the rest
     free. When Johnnie was a child he had only been moved in the little wheeled chair, got for him
     in his father’s lifetime, when they were rich. Now he was better, and able to move about with
     the help of a crutch, but even now was a hopeless cripple, with only his vigorous mind and
     unconquerable spirits to maintain him through private hours of suffering. Partly from his
     infirmities—partly from his natural temperament—the lad
     <pb n="041"/> had a certain superficial shyness, which, though it was easily got over, made it
     rather difficult to form acquaintance with him. He could not be induced to dine with us that
     first night—but he was in the drawing-room, showing the stereoscope to Miss Polly’s little
     nieces, Di and Emmy, when we came back from dinner; the other little creatures were playing at
     some recondite childish game in another part of the room; but Emmy and Di were very proper
     little maidens, trained to take judicious care of their white India muslin frocks, the spare
     dimensions of which contrasted oddly enough with Clary’s voluminous little skirts and flush of
     ribbons. Clary was like a little rose, with lovely rounded cheeks and limbs like her mother,
     dimpled to the very finger-points, while Di and Emmy, though by no means deficient in good
     looks, were made up quite after Miss Polly’s own model, in a taste which was somewhat severe
     for their years. Johnnie Harley veiled himself behind these little maidens till we were safely
     settled in the room. He was twenty, poor fellow, and did not know what was to become of him. He
     was sometimes very melancholy, and sometimes very gay; he was in rather a doubtful mood
     to-night.</p>
    <p>“Look here, Mrs. Crofton,” he said, drawing me shyly aside. “I’ve put this one in a famous
     <pb n="042"/> light—do tell me if you like it. I did it myself.”</p>
    <p>I looked, of course, to please him. It was a pretty view of my own house at Estcourt, with
     the orphan children who lived there playing on the terrace—very pretty, and very minute—so
     clear that I fancied I could recognize the children. It pleased me mightily.</p>
    <p>“<hi>You</hi> did it, Johnnie,” cried I, much gratified. “I am very much pleased; but I never
     knew you were a ‘photographic artist’ before.”</p>
    <p>“No more I was,” said Johnnie, who rather affected a little roughness of speech, “till they
     got me a camera the other day. Of course I know it was Alice, and that somehow or other she’s
     spared it off herself. Do you know whether there’s anything she ought to have had that she
     hasn’t, Mrs. Crofton? One can never find Alice out. She doesn’t go when she’s made a sacrifice
     for you and keep hinting and hinting to let you know, as some people do; but look here—isn’t it
     horrible to think I’m grown up and yet have to stay at home like a girl, and can’t do anything.
     Now that I’m able to do these slides, I’d give my ears if I could sell them. I’d go and stand
     in the market at Simonborough. But of course it’s no use speaking. Don’t you think, Mrs.
     Crofton, that there’s surely something in
     <pb n="043"/> the world that could be done by a cripple like me?”</p>
    <p>“I have no doubt a dozen things,” said I, boldly; “but have a little patience, Johnnie.
     Maurice is ten years older than you are, and he does nothing that I can see. Besides, it is
     holiday time—I forbid you to think of anything but the new camera to-night. Is it a good one?
     What a pleasure it must be for all of you,” I continued, looking once more into the
     stereoscope, where, most singular of optical delusions, I certainly saw a pretty new winter
     bonnet, the back of which, in the wardrobe of Alice, I had already made a memorandum of,
     floating over the picture of my old house.</p>
    <p>“Ah,” said Johnnie, with a sigh, “if I were a fellow like Maurice!—but here, Di, you have not
     seen this,” he added, transferring another slide into that wooden box. Grave little Di looked
     at it, and summoned her sister with a little scream of delight.</p>
    <p>“It’s Miss Harley and Baby Sedgwick,” said Di, “and I do believe if any one was little enough
     they could go round behind her in the picture. Oh! let me tell Derwent and Clara, Mr.
     John!”</p>
    <p>Mr. John was very graciously pleased to exhibit his handiwork to any number of spectators,
     <pb n="044"/> and shortly we all gathered round the stereoscope. Alice stood looking on very
     demurely, while we were examining her in that pretty peep-show; she listened to all the usual
     observations with due calm, while Johnnie, quite in a flush of pleasure, produced the pictures,
     at which I understood afterwards the poor youth had been working all day long, one by one out
     of the box.</p>
    <p>“My love,” said Miss Polly, in a mild aside, “I’d like to see you just so in a house of your
     own, my dear.”</p>
    <p>Alice colored slightly; very slightly—it was against her principles to blush—and made no
     answer, except a slight shake of her head.</p>
    <p>“Such a sweet baby,” said Miss Reredos, “I think one might bear anything for such a darling!
     Oh, don’t you think so, Miss Harley? I think it’s so unnatural for a lady not to love children.
     I think if dear Clement had but a family I should be so happy.”</p>
    <p>“But, dear, shouldn’t you be happier,” said Clara, opening her bright eyes a little wider,
     with a laughing humor which now-a-days that young lady permitted herself to exercise pretty
     freely, “if you had a family of your own?”</p>
    <p>“Oh! Mrs. Sedgwick, how can you speak so? I am so glad the gentlemen are not here,” said
     <pb n="045"/> the Rector’s sister. Alice stood looking at her with a half vexed, half amused
     expression. Alice was a little afraid for the honor of (most frightful of phrases!) her
     sex.</p>
    <p>“As for Alice,” said Clara, laughing, “do you know she thinks it rather improper to be
     married? She would not allow she cared for anybody, not for the world.”</p>
    <p>“I think women ought to be very careful,” said Alice, responding instantly to the challenge
     with a little flush and start; “I think there are very few men in the world worthy of being
     loved. Yes, I do think so, whatever you choose to say. They’re well enough for their trades,
     but they’re not good enough to have a woman’s heart for a plaything. Of course there may be
     some—I do not deny that; but I never”——</p>
    <p>Here Alice paused—perhaps she was going to tell a fib—perhaps conscience stopped her—I will
     not guess; but Clara clapped her hands in triumph.</p>
    <p>“Ah, but if you did ever,” said Clara, laughing, “would you marry <hi>him</hi>, Alice?”</p>
    <p>“If he asked me it is very likely I should,” said Alice, with great composure; “but not for a
     house of my own, as Miss Polly says—nor for fun, like some other people.”</p>
    <p>“My love, it’s very natural to like a house of
     <pb n="046"/> one’s own,” said Miss Polly, with a little sigh. “I don’t mind saying it now that
     I am so old: once in my life I almost think I would have married for a home—not for a living,
     remember, Alice—but for a place and people that should belong to me, and not to another—that’s
     what one wishes for, you know; but I never talked about it either now or then; my dear, I
     wouldn’t if I were you.”</p>
    <p>At this address Alice blushed crimson—blushed up to the hair, and patted her foot upon the
     ground in a very impatient, not to say angry, way. She cast a somewhat indignant side-look at
     me, to express her conviction that I was at the bottom of this, and had suggested the mild
     condemnation of Miss Polly—which, so far as agreeing thoroughly in her sentiments went, I
     confess I might have done. Then Alice went off abruptly to the piano, and began playing to the
     children, who gathered round her; before long her voice was pleasantly audible in one of those
     immemorial songs with a fox or a robin for a hero, which always delight children; and when the
     song was finished there ensued as pretty a scene as I have ever looked at. Clara gathered the
     children in a ring, which danced round and round, with a dazzle of little rosebud faces, flying
     white frocks and ribbons, to Alice’s accompaniment. Such
     <pb n="047"/> scenes I have no doubt were of nightly occurrence in the big, grand drawing-room
     at Waterflag Hall; and little Derwie took his part so heartily, and joined in the chant with
     which they went round with lungs and will so unmistakable, that, for my part, I was quite
     captivated. Miss Polly and I sat down to watch them. Little Di, too shy and too big to join
     them, being twelve years old and a grandmother among these babes, stood wistfully behind us,
     envying Emmy, who was only ten and a half, and “not too old for such a game.” Di, a long way
     older and graver than Mrs. Clare, stood nodding and smiling to encourage her little sister
     every time she whisked past. Miss Reredos behind us was examining Johnnie’s pictures and
     talking sentiment in a soft half-whisper to that defenceless boy, while Miss Polly and I sat on
     a sofa together, looking on.</p>
    <p>“It is strange,” said Miss Polly, “but yet I’m sure I am very glad. I thought of asking you,
     Clare, whether anything had occurred to disturb that dear girl? I don’t like when I hear young
     women talk like that, my dear—it looks to me as if they had something on their mind, you know.
     Once I thought there might perhaps be something between Bertie Nugent and Alice—that would have
     been a very nice match; but
     <pb n="048"/> somehow these nice matches never come about—at least, not without a deal of
     trouble; and I suppose it was nothing but an old woman’s fancy, Clare.”</p>
    <p>“I suppose not, indeed,” said I, rather ruefully, looking at that prettiest spectacle before
     me, and recognizing, as by intuition, that Mr. Reredos had just come in, and was standing at
     the door in a glow of delight and approbation, looking at Alice, and deciding not to delay his
     proposal for an hour longer than it should be absolutely necessary to keep silent. Ah, me!
     there was some hope for us in Alice’s philosophical moods; but when she played to her little
     nieces and nephews in that shockingly happy, careless, and easy manner, I was in despair.</p>
    <p>“It’s very sad when people won’t see what’s most for their advantage,” said Miss Polly, with
     a ghost of humor in her pale old face. “I daresay, Clare, my dear, Bertie’s just as happy. I
     heard from Lady Greenfield the other day—one of <hi>her letters</hi>, you know—that the dear
     boy was getting on very well, but breaking his heart to get home that he might go to the Crimea
     to the war.”</p>
    <p>“So he tells me,” said I, “but I rather think I am very glad he has not the chance of dying
     on that dreadful hill.”
     <pb n="049"/></p>
    <p>“My dear, that’s very true,” said Miss Polly; “one faints at the thought of it, to be sure,
     for one’s own; but if I could be philosophical—which—dear, dear, it isn’t to be expected from
     an old woman! I’d say it was wrong to be sorry for the dear young creatures, God bless them!
     Think what they’re spared, my dear child. I don’t know but what it’s a great saving of the
     labor and the sorrow when they die young.”</p>
    <p>“Miss Polly, this is not like you,” I cried in surprise.</p>
    <p>“Perhaps it isn’t; but, dear, we’re always learning something,” said Miss Polly; “there’s
     Elinor now, and poor Emmy, the unfortunate little soul! but hush, here’s your new rector
     coming—I’ll tell you another time.”
     <pb n="050"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER VI.</head>
    <p>“<hi>I am</hi> surprised,” said Mr. Reredos, as he drank his coffee beside me, “to hear from
     Mr. Maurice Harley that he’s not in orders. I really felt so sure that he must be that I did
     not think of asking. He’s had his fellowship this long time, has not he? and really a
     clergyman’s son, and with the excellent connections he has—I am surprised!”</p>
    <p>“Ah, so is everybody,” said Miss Polly, significantly. Miss Polly was an old-fashioned woman,
     and had little sympathy with those delicate conscientious scruples which kept our friend
     Maurice out of the Church.</p>
    <p>“My dear,” continued Miss Polly, turning aside to me, with some energy, as Mr. Reredos,
     always polite, took her empty cup from her, “I could believe in it if he were doing anything or
     thinking of doing anything; but if you’ll believe me, Clare, it’s nothing but idleness—that’s
     what it is. When a young man’s idle, if he doesn’t fall in love with the first girl he meets,
     he falls
     <pb n="051"/> in love with himself, which is a deal worse. The Rector here will be trying to
     help Maurice out of his doubts, I shouldn’t wonder. His doubts, indeed! If he lost his
     fellowship and had to work hard for his living, I shouldn’t be afraid of his doubts, for my
     part.”</p>
    <p>“Well,” said I, “but if the loss of his fellowship dispersed poor Maurice’s dilettante
     scepticism, and forced him into orders, it might be better for himself, Miss Polly, but I doubt
     if it would be better for the Church. When his conscience keeps him outside, we have no reason
     to find fault, but if he came in against his conscience——”</p>
    <p>“Conscience! stuff!” said Miss Polly, with some heat. “Child, that’s not what I meant. I
     meant—for being his father’s and mother’s son I can’t think he’s a bad boy at the bottom—I
     meant a little trouble and fighting would soon put those idle vagaries out of his head. Now,
     Mr. Reredos, mind you don’t go and argue with Maurice Harley. I’m an old woman, and I’ve seen
     such before, many’s the time. Wait till he’s got something to do and something to bear in this
     world, as he’s sure to have, sooner or later. Ah, Life’s a wonderful teacher! When a man sits
     among his books, or a woman at her needle—and there isn’t such a great difference as you
     <pb n="052"/> might suppose—they get mazing themselves with all kinds of foolish questions, and
     think themselves very grand too for doing it; but only wait till they find out what God means
     them to do and to put up with in this world—it makes a deal of difference, Clare.”</p>
    <p>“Miss Polly, you are a philosopher, and we never knew it!” said I, while Mr. Reredos stood
     looking on, much annoyed, and in no small degree contemptuous of the pale old woman who took
     upon her to direct so perfect a person as himself—for Mr. Reredos was not unlike Maurice
     Harley, though after his different fashion; he thought he could do a great deal with his wisdom
     and his words.</p>
    <p>“I am not a philosopher; but I have been alone with the dear children since my niece Emmy
     left me,” said Miss Polly, “and not so able to stir about as I once was; and you know, my dear,
     one can’t say out everything in one’s mind to children at their age; so, somehow the thoughts
     come up as if I had been gathering them all my life, and never had time to look at them
     before.”</p>
    <p>“I suspect that is how most of the thoughts that are worth remembering do come,” said I. Mr.
     Reredos did not say anything. He stood, with a faint smile on his lip, which he did not
     <pb n="053"/> mean us to suspect, much less understand—and while he bent his handsome head
     towards the mistress of the house, gravely attentive, as it was his duty to be, his eyes turned
     towards Maurice and Alice Harley. Did not I know well enough what was in his mind? He thought
     we were a couple of old women dozing over our slow experiences. He was still in the world where
     words and looks produce unspeakable results, and where the chance of a moment determines a
     life. His eyes turned to those other young people who, like himself, were speculating upon all
     manner of questions—he would not laugh at us, but a faint gleam of criticism and superiority
     just brightened upon his lip. I liked him none the worse, for my own part.</p>
    <p>“This reads like a Newdigate,” said Maurice Harley. “I suppose Sedgwick brought the book to
     you, Clara, for a sugar-plum. Listen, how sweetly pretty! These prize poets are really too
     delicious for anything.”</p>
    <p>“You had better write a poem yourself, Maurice, and show what you can do,” cried the
     indignant Clara; “it is so grand to be a critic, and so easy! Nobody can write to please you,
     nobody can speak to please you—I should just like to see you do something yourself, Maurice,
     that we could criticise as well.”
     <pb n="054"/></p>
    <p>Maurice laughed, poising in his hand the pretty new poetry-book which Mr. Sedgwick had
     brought down from London to his wife. He looked so superior and so triumphant, that even his
     grave brother-in-law was provoked.</p>
    <p>“Maurice is not so foolish,” said Mr. Sedgwick, “as long as he doesn’t <hi>do</hi> anything
     he may be a Shakespeare for anything we know. You girls may worship him as such now, if you
     please—there he sits quite ready to receive your homage; but if he really ventured into print,
     Maurice would be only Maurice Harley—just himself, like the rest of us—might even find a critic
     in his turn, as such is the fate of mortals. No, no, you may be sure Maurice won’t commit
     himself; he’s a great deal too wise for that.”</p>
    <p>Maurice laughed a somewhat constrained laugh, and coloured slightly. Perhaps a touch of
     conscience made Mr. Sedgwick’s sarcasm tell—he threw down the book with a little petulance.</p>
    <p>“Far be it from me to object to Clara’s tastes. Thanks to my sisters, I know pretty well what
     young ladies like in the shape of poetry,” said Maurice; “they all admire the Newdigates. There
     was a time when I found Alice in tears over one of these distinguished poems—and that not so
     very many years ago.”
     <pb n="055"/></p>
    <p>“Oh! don’t be so dreadfully satirical!” said Miss Reredos, who was beginning to tire of
     Johnnie and his stereoscope. “I am sure that year that mamma and I went to Commemoration with
     Clement there was the sweetest thing imaginable—and so charmingly read too—and I have a copy of
     it now; but, oh! I know why Mr. Harley does not like the Newdigate,” cried the Rector’s sister,
     clasping her soft hands, “he’s a Cambridge man!”</p>
    <p>“Exactly,” said Maurice, recovering himself at once, for he was quite disposed to take Miss
     Reredos for his antagonist; “you know the jealousy which exists between us. Your brother and I
     preserve an outside appearance of civility, out of respect to Mrs. Crofton and the presence of
     the ladies, but nobody can doubt for a moment how we hate each other in our hearts.”</p>
    <p>“I say, do you though?” cried the small voice, down at Maurice Harley’s elbow, of my son
     Derwie, who was, unluckily, at that moment advancing with the rest of the little troop to say
     good-night. “Do you hate the Rector, Maurice?—he’s the clergyman, you know—he can’t do anything
     wrong; so <hi>he</hi> can’t hate <hi>you</hi>—why do you hate him?—is he cleverer than you are?
     Stand up a moment, please—I don’t think he’s quite as tall.”
     <pb n="056"/></p>
    <p>This interruption Derwent made with the most perfect sincerity and earnestness, unconsciously
     guessing at the only reasons which could make a person so accomplished as Maurice Harley hate
     anybody. Everybody laughed except the individual questioned, who shot a glance of wrath at my
     boy, and eyed Mr. Reredos with a sort of contemptuous inquiry. Could any one, even a child,
     imagine the new rector to be cleverer than the ineffable Maurice? He sank down again in the
     chair from which Derwie had dragged him, laughing with a very bad grace. Then all the broken
     currents of talk going on in the room, suffered a little ebb and pause. Little rosy faces
     clustered close about Clara Sedgwick, about Alice and myself, and old Miss Polly, holding up
     rose-lips full of kisses. Mr. Crofton shook hands with Derwie, and turned him off with an
     affectionate grasp upon his shoulders, declaring, with a fondness beyond caresses, that he was
     too old to be kissed. Then we all paused, looking after them as they trooped out of the room.
     Miss Reredos, full of something clever to say in the way of an attack upon Maurice—Maurice
     himself too self-conscious to be diverted by that pretty procession, and Johnnie, who was
     hanging over his stereoscope, and following the Rector’s sister with his eyes, were the only
     persons in the
     <pb n="057"/> room who did not watch with a smile and an increased warmth at heart these
     beautiful children disappearing, one by one, from the door. Mr. Reredos’s face shone, and he
     cast sidelong glances at Alice. He was young, in his first romance of love, not yet spoken. His
     heart was moved in him with an unconscious blessing to the children; visions of a house of his
     own, musical with such voices, stole into the Rector’s soul—I could see it in his face.</p>
    <p>And was it to be so? There was no side glance from the eyes of Alice, reciprocating those of
     Mr. Reredos—no consciousness, as she stood by the table watching the children, of any future
     such as that which sparkled in the young Rector’s eyes. She stood calmly watching them, nodding
     and smiling to Derwent, and her little niece Clary, who, hand in hand, were the last to leave
     the room—the maiden aunt, only a little more independent of the children than their
     mother—almost as much beloved by them—the young, unmarried woman, gravely cogitating the
     necessities of her class of age, and feeling much superior to the vanities of love-making,
     without a single palpitation in her of the future bride, the possible mother. So, at least, it seemed.
     <pb n="058"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER VII.</head>
    <p><hi>That</hi> evening—it was the first of her visit to Hilfont, and a perfectly natural
     thing, considering the long affection between us—I paid Alice a long visit in her own room. I
     might have done so, even if I had been conscious of nothing to inquire about, nothing to
     suggest. It was rather late when we all came up-stairs, and when I had seen Miss Polly safely
     established in her easy chair by her fire, and eluded as well as I could the story about
     Elinor’s (to wit, Lady Greenfield, Sir Willoughby’s wife, once Mrs. Herbert Nugent, my cousin,
     and Bertie’s aunt) letter—I turned back to the bright chamber near my own, which was always
     called Miss Harley’s room. Alice was sitting rather listlessly by the table, reading. She
     looked tired, and did not seem overmuch to enjoy her book. She was very glad to see me come in,
     and, I suspect, to be delivered from her own thoughts, which it was clear enough she could not
     quite exorcise by means of literature; for it was not a novel,
     <pb n="059"/> which there is some hope in, but a wisdom-book, much esteemed by the superior
     classes—one of those books which, if it has any power at all, excites one into contradiction,
     by conclusions about human nature in general, which we can all form our own opinions upon. I
     suspect Alice could not keep her attention to it, hard though she tried.</p>
    <p>When we had talked over indifferent matters for some time, my curiosity, which I might have
     dignified with the title of anxiety, too, roused me to closer inquiries than, perhaps, were
     quite justifiable. I knew that after Mr. Reredos had spoken—unless, indeed, he happened to be
     accepted—Alice’s lips were closed for ever on the subject, so I wickedly took advantage of my
     opportunities.</p>
    <p>“Perhaps ere long I shall have to congratulate you,” said I, “and you may be sure it would be
     a great matter for me to have you so very near. We should make famous neighbors, Alice, don’t
     you think? I may well be anxious about your decision, my dear, for my own sake.”</p>
    <p>“Mrs. Crofton, I do not understand you,” said Alice, in a little dismay, looking very
     curiously and wistfully in my face; then, after a little pause, a deep color suffused her
     cheeks, she started, and moved her hand impatiently upon the
     <pb n="060"/> table, as if in sudden passion with herself, and then added, coldly, with an
     inexpressible self-restraint and subdued bitterness, which it was hard to understand: “Pray
     tell me what you mean?”</p>
    <p>The contrast of her tone, so suddenly chilled and formal, with the burning color and subdued
     agitation of her face, struck me wonderfully. “My dear child,” said I, “I have no right to
     ask—I don’t want to interfere—but you are sure to have this question submitted to you, Alice,
     and can’t be ignorant of that now, that it has come so far. Cannot you think what I mean?”</p>
    <p>Alice paused a moment, then she cast rather a defiant glance at me, and answered, proudly:
     “If any one has been forming foolish plans about me, Mrs. Crofton, the responsibility is not
     mine—I know I am not to blame.”</p>
    <p>“That may be very true,” said I, “but I am not speaking of responsibility. Don’t you think,
     dear, that this is important enough to be taken into consideration without any impatience of
     personal feeling? Deciding one’s life by the ordeal of marriage is a human necessity it
     appears. You are a clergyman’s daughter—no way could you fill a better or more congenial place
     than as a clergyman’s wife. If I were you I should not conclude at once, because, perhaps, in
     the meantime, of your own accord, you have
     <pb n="061"/> not quite fallen in desperate love with your lover. My dear, you think I am
     dreadfully common-place, but I cannot help it. Think, Alice!—you want a life for yourself—a
     house belonging to you, and you only—you do! Don’t say no—everybody does; think! Won’t you take
     all this into consideration before you decide?”</p>
    <p>“Because I am going to have ‘an offer,’ and perhaps I never may have another—because I am not
     so young now as to be able to throw away my chances—and it is <hi>you</hi> who say so!” cried
     Alice, throwing at me an angry, bitter, scornful glance. Perhaps, if she had yielded more to my
     arguments, I might have found it harder than I did now.</p>
    <p>“You humiliate me,” she cried again: “if I want a life of my own, I want to make it myself; a
     house of my own?—no I have no ambition for that.”</p>
    <p>“But you falter a little when you say so,” said I, taking cruel advantage of her weakness.
     “Now, we are not going to discuss the disabilities of women. It is just as impossible for an
     unmarried man to have what I call a house of his own as it is for you; and as for the privilege
     of choice—good lack, good lack! much use it seems about to be to poor Mr. Reredos! My dear
     <pb n="062"/> child, don’t be foolish—there is your brother Maurice with the most complete of
     educations, and no lack of power to make use of it. What is he going to do with himself? Where
     are the great advantages he has over his sister? <hi>I</hi> can’t see them. But no, that’s not
     the question. The Rector is a good man; he is young, he is well off; he is agreeable. Your
     dearest friend could not choose a more suitable life for you than that you would have at the
     Hilfont Rectory. Now, Alice, think. Are you going to make up your mind to throw away all this,
     and a good man’s happiness besides?”</p>
    <p>“Oh, Mrs. Crofton! Mrs. Crofton! and it is you who say so!” said poor Alice, with looks which
     certainly must have consumed me had I been of combustible material—“this is from you!”</p>
    <p>“And why not, my dear?” said I, meekly. “Am not I next to your mother, Alice?—next oldest
     friend?—and next interested in your welfare?”</p>
    <p>“If you mean that you have a right to say anything you please to me,” said Alice, seizing my
     hand and kissing it in a quick revulsion of feeling, “it is true to the very farthest that you
     choose to stretch it; but that is not what you mean. Oh, dear Mrs. Crofton!” said the poor
     <pb n="063"/> girl with a rising blush and a certain solemn indignation wonderful to me—“I can
     only say it again; of all persons in the world that I should have had such words from
      <hi>you</hi>!”</p>
    <p>With which exclamation she suddenly cast a guilty, startled look upon me as if she had
     betrayed something and hid her face in her hands. How did she know what was in my heart?—how
     could she tell that I was arguing against my own dear and long-cherished plans, which I had
     made it a point of honor never to hint in the remotest manner to her? But here we approached
     the region where another word was impossible. She would not have uttered a syllable of
     explanation for her life—I dared not, if I meant to have any comfort in mine; I said nothing to
     her by which it was possible to infer that I understood what she meant. I absolutely slurred
     over the whole question—here we had reached the bound.</p>
    <p>“Well, dear,” said I, “don’t distress yourself so very much about it—you must decide
     according to your own will and not to mine; only do think it over again in the fresh morning
     before the Rector gets an opportunity of speaking to you. Good night, Alice—don’t sit reading,
     but go to sleep!”</p>
    <p>She raised her face to me, and leant her cheek a little more than was quite needful against mine
     <pb n="064"/> as I kissed her—and so we parted without another word between us. Possibly, we
     women talk a great deal on most occasions; sometimes, however, we show a singular faculty for
     keeping silent. Next morning, Alice and I met each other as if we had never spoken a word which
     all the world might not hear. We interchanged no confidences, looked no looks of private
     understanding. Indeed, surely nothing <hi>had</hi> passed between us—all the world might have
     listened and been none the wiser. What had a momentary emphasis, a sudden look to do with the
     matter? Alice spoke nothing but her usual sentiments, and I did not say a word inconsistent
     with mine.
     <pb n="065"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER VIII.</head>
    <p><hi>The</hi> next morning was Easter Sunday. I have no doubt Mr. Reredos would have been glad
     enough to add a private joy of his own to the rejoicings of the festival, and might not have
     thought it unsuitable to declare himself even on that morning could he have had a chance.
     However, there was not very much time before Church hours, and to be sure the Rector ought to
     have been thinking of something else. It was a true Easter morning, full of sunshine and that
     new life of spring born out of death and darkness which to every heart must bear a certain
     charm. Is it something of a compensation to the sorrowful that all the wonderful silent symbols
     of Nature speak to them with a special force which does not belong to the happy? We were all
     dwelling at ease, people untroubled—our hearts were glad in the sunshine, which to us looked
     like a promise of permanence and peace unclouded. Only far off with an apprehension of the
     thoughts, and not of the heart, did the meaning
     <pb n="066"/> of the feast which we were keeping occur to us. To Derwent and myself this was
     perhaps the happiest time of our lives. Perhaps to us the Resurrection was little more than an
     article of belief—I think we thus paid something for our happiness. At all events it did not
     jar upon us to perceive a certain agitation in the Rector’s tones—a certain catching of his
     breath in the little pleasant sermon, not without some small sentences in it specially meant
     for the ear of Alice, but perfectly “suited to the occasion,” which Mr. Reredos delivered.
     Everybody was very attentive, save Maurice Harley. Maurice had some liberal and lofty
     objections to the Athanasian creed; he sat down and amused himself reading the Gunpowder Plot
     Service with secret smiles of criticism, while his neighbors round him murmured forth with a
     universal rustic voice that strenuous confession of the faith—and he sketched a bracket (we
     were rather proud of our Church) while Mr. Reredos preached his sermon, and comported himself
     generally as a highly superior man, attending Church out of complacency to his friends, might
     be expected to do.</p>
    <p>Next day I fear Mr. Reredos ascertained beyond question what he had to expect from Alice
     Harley. With a look of stormy agitation, strongly restrained, he let me know on the Monday
     <pb n="067"/> that it was quite necessary for him to return to the Rectory. He had some sick
     people to attend to, who demanded his presence in his own house. I did not say that there was
     only half a mile of distance between the Rectory and the Hall—I acquiesced in his explanations,
     and accepted his apologies. Miss Reredos, however, was much more difficult to manage. I heard
     him tell her in a low tone that she must get ready to go; and the young lady’s answer of
     astonishment, and resistance, and total ignorance of any reason why her pleasure should be
     balked, was audible enough to everybody in the room.</p>
    <p>“Go away! Leave Hilfont!” she exclaimed with a gasp of amazement. “Why should we go away?
     Mrs. Crofton was good enough to ask us for a week, and I am sure you could do your duty quite
     as well here as at the Rectory. Oh, please, Mrs. Crofton, listen! The only sick people I know
     of are that old man at the turnpike, and his blind daughter—he could visit them quite as well
     going from Hilfont as from the Rectory. I believe this is the nearest of the two.”</p>
    <p>“Oh, but Mr. Williams from the little chapel goes to see old Johnnie Dunn,” interrupted
     little Derwie; “he was there yesterday, and Martha’s
     <pb n="068"/> quite well now, and goes to chapel like anything. Miss Reredos, do you know
     Martha wasn’t always blind? she used to work and make dresses when she was young. Once she
     lived in Simonborough and learned her trade, and I suppose it was there she learned to go to
     chapel. Martha says they’re not Church-folks at all. I don’t think they want Mr. Reredos to go
     there.”</p>
    <p>“You’re not very complimentary, Derwie,” said the Rector, with a slight quiver of his lip,
     which I recognized as a sign of the passion and deep excitement in which he was. With that wild
     pain and mortification tugging at his heart, it would have been a relief to him to burst out in
     an ebulition of rage or impatience against somebody, and I instinctively put out my hand to
     protect my boy. “But it is sometimes my duty to go where they don’t want me,” he added, with a
     laugh as significant, “and with many regrets and many thanks to Mrs. Crofton we must still go
     back to-day. Laura, get ready, please.”</p>
    <p>In pity for the unfortunate Rector, who, I saw, longed to escape from the room, the
     inquisitive looks of Mrs. Clara, who was present, and the distinct statement from Derwie, which
     I knew to be impending, to the effect, that of his own certain knowledge nobody was ill in the village,
     <pb n="069"/> I interposed, and we made a compromise—the Rector left us and his sister stayed.
     Miss Reredos was profoundly pleased with the arrangement. Perhaps her dear Clement did not
     confide to her his private reasons for so hasty a return, and I am not sure that she was not
     quite as well satisfied with his absence, which might have possibly spoiled her own particular
     sport—or interfered with it at least. So he went away with a certain impetus and haste upon
     him—his romance come to an effectual end, and his sensations somewhat bitter. He was not
     lackadaisical, but savage, as men are under their mortifications when they are no longer in
     their first youth. I daresay, if one could have read his thoughts, there were ferocious
     denunciations there against the women who beguile a man to commit himself so fatally, which
     would have been very unjust to poor Alice. I am afraid it is very cold-hearted of me to speak
     so lightly of a serious disappointment, which this certainly was to Mr. Reredos. I have no
     doubt he was really unhappy; but I thought it a good symptom that the unhappiness took a savage
     turn.</p>
    <p>Miss Reredos left behind, pursued, as I have said, her own sport. She was prettier than I
     thought her at first—she had a little of that teasing wit which clever young ladies exercise
     <pb n="070"/> upon attractive young men, and she had a strong sentimental reserve, much more in
     keeping with her pale complexion and black ringlets than the lighter mood. A couple of days had
     not passed over us before we all perceived that the poor lame boy, Johnnie Harley, was
     hopelessly taken in her toils. Just at first nobody had paid particular attention to the
     intercourse between these two. It was very kind of Miss Reredos to talk to the unfortunate
     young man, and interest herself about his pictures, and listen to his dreams; and so wonderful
     a prominence has one’s actual self to one’s own eyes, however unselfish, that I believe Alice
     was quite of opinion that Miss Reredos, expecting to be connected with the family by-and-by,
     was paying all these friendly attentions to Johnnie by way of conciliating herself. Nothing
     could be further from the intentions of the Rector’s sister. She was strongly of opinion that
     each man for himself was the most satisfactory rule, and being possessed of that spirit of
     conquest which some women have by nature, commenced her operations from the moment of entering
     the house. I do not think she could help it, poor girl—it was natural to her. There were in
     Hilfont only two persons accessible to her charms—Maurice, in every way an eligible victim, and
     poor cripple Johnnie, to whom, one
     <pb n="071"/> could have supposed, not even a coquettish girl at a loss for a prey, would have
     had the heart to offer her sweet poison. But the heart, I fear, has little to do with such
     concerns, and almost before the suspicions of the other women of the party, from myself
     downward, were awakened, the mischief was done. Miss Reredos, we had no difficulty in
     perceiving, had set her heart upon the subjugation of Maurice, whether for any personal reason,
     or for sport, or as a means of retaliation, it was difficult to tell; and really I was not in
     the least concerned about the peace of mind of the Fellow of Exeter. But Johnnie! we all rose
     up together to his defence, with secret vows of self-devotion. All the women of us guarded him
     about, shielding his little table and his stereoscope from the approach of the enemy—even Di,
     tall, timid, and twelve years old, stood by the lad with a natural instinct. But we were too
     late. He answered Miss Polly, I fear, rather sharply, turned his back upon myself, and gave
     Mrs. Clara a brotherly push away from him. He wanted none of us—he wanted only the Siren who
     was charming the poor boy among such rocks and quicksands as his frail boat had never yet
     ventured upon. When Miss Reredos addressed herself to Maurice, his unfortunate brother turned
     savage looks upon that all-accomplished
     <pb n="072"/> young man. In our first indignation we were all rather cold to Miss Reredos, and
     Johnnie, quick-sighted as his infirmities helped to make him, perceived it in a moment, and
     resented the neglect, which of course he attributed to our envy of her perfections. Then we
     tried artifice instead, and Clara, sister of the victim, got up a very warm sudden regard for
     the enchantress, whose opinion she sought upon everything; but this Miss Reredos speedily
     discovered, exposed, and exulted in; there was no help for it—the damage which was done, was
     done, and could not be repaired.</p>
    <p>Meanwhile the flirtation with Maurice did not advance so satisfactorily—he was so much
     accustomed to admire himself, that the habit of admiring another came slowly to him; and then,
     as Miss Reredos took the initiative, and did not spare to be cleverly rude to the young man,
     he, taking advantage of his privileges, was cleverly rude to her in reply, from which
     fashionable mode of beginning, they advanced by degrees to closer friendship, or, at least,
     familiarity of address. Alice looked on at all this with the most solemn disapproval—it was
     amusing to see the dead gravity of her glances towards them, the tacit displeasure, and shame,
     and resentment on account of “her sex!” Poor Alice took the responsibility
     <pb n="073"/> on her own shoulders; she watched the levity of the other girl, who did not
     resemble herself in a single particular, with a solemn sense of being involved in it, which
     struck me as the oddest comicality I had seen. Could anybody suppose Maurice Harley concerned
     about another man’s shortcomings, only because the culprit was a man, and one of his own
      <hi>sex</hi>? If it had not been so entirely true and sincere, it would have been absurd—this
     championship of Alice; only women ever dream of such an <hi>esprit de corps</hi>—but she
     maintained it with such absolute good faith and solemn gravity, that while one laughed one
     loved her the better. There she sat, severe in her youthful virtue, gravely believing herself
     old, and past the period of youth, but in her heart as high-flying, as obstinate, as heroical
     as if she were seventeen. Mrs. Clara knew nothing of that romance; perhaps there are delicate
     touches of feminine character, which only show themselves to perfection in the “unmarried
     woman”—the woman who has come to maturity without having the closer claims of husband and
     children to charm her out of her thoughts and theories—though it is only in a very gracious
     subject that such an example as Alice Harley could be produced.
     <pb n="074"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER IX.</head>
    <p>“<hi>Well</hi>, really!” said little Mrs. Sedgwick, bridling with offended virtue, “I don’t
     think I am very hard upon a little innocent flirting—sometimes, you know, there’s no harm in
     it—and young people will amuse themselves; but <hi>really</hi>, Mrs. Crofton, <hi>that</hi>
     Miss Reredos is quite ridiculous. I do wonder for my part how men can be so taken in!—and our
     Maurice who is so clever!—and she is not even pretty—if she had been pretty one could have
     understood.”</p>
    <p>“My dear Clara,” said I, “perhaps it is not very complimentary to your brother, but I do
     think the most sensible thing Maurice could do would be to fall in love. I don’t say of course
     with Miss Reredos; but then, you see, we can’t choose the person. If he fell desperately in
     love and made a fool of himself, I am sure I should not think any worse of him, and it would do
     him no harm.”</p>
    <p>Both the sisters drew up their shoulders a little, and communicated between each other a telegraphic
     <pb n="075"/> glance of displeasure. Between themselves they could be hard enough upon Maurice,
     but, after the use of kinsfolk, could not bear the touch of a stranger.</p>
    <p>“Really, I cannot say I should be very grateful to Maurice for such a sister-in-law,” said
     Clara, with a toss of her head.</p>
    <p>“I don’t think there is very much to fear,” said Miss Polly. “Do you know what little Derwie
     told me yesterday? He said a poor woman in the village had three or four children ill with the
     hooping-cough—at least so I understood the child from the sound he made to show me what it was.
     Now, I really think if I were you, Clare, I would not let that child wander so much about the
     village. Neither Di nor Emmy has ever had hooping-cough, and I shall be almost frightened to
     let them go out of doors.”</p>
    <p>“Oh, I assure you it’s nothing, Miss Polly!” cried Clara—“mine had it two years ago—even the
     baby—and took their walks just the same in all weathers; and they must have it one time or
     other, you know—and such great girls as your two nieces! Our children all got over it perfectly
     well. Though Hugh says I am ridiculously timid, I never was the least afraid. Their chests were
     rubbed every night, and they had something which Hugh said it was polite to call
     <pb n="076"/> medicine. Oh, I assure you there’s nothing to be at all afraid of! especially at
     this time of the year.”</p>
    <p>“I daresay that’s very true, my dear,” said Miss Polly, who took little Clara’s nursery
     instructions and assurances in very good part, “but it isn’t always so. There’s my poor little
     nephew, little Willoughby—dear, dear! to think what a strong man his father is, and how
     delicate that poor child looks! I can’t help thinking sometimes it must be his mother’s fault;
     though to be sure they have the best of nurses, and Lady Greenfield can’t be expected to make a
     slave of herself; that poor dear little soul was very ill with the hooping-cough. Clara—all
     children are not so fortunate as your pretty darlings; and that reminds me, Clare, that you
     have never seen Elinor’s letter yet; she mentions her nephew in it, as I think I told you; so,
     though it’s almost all about Emmy, my dear children’s mother, if you’ll wait a minute I’ll just
     bring it down.”</p>
    <p>Saying which Miss Polly left the room. Alice sat rather stiffly at her work and looked very
     busy—so very busy that I was suspicious of some small gleam of interest on her part touching
     the contents of Lady Greenfield’s letter.</p>
    <p>“Miss Polly does not love Lady Greenfield too
     <pb n="077"/> much,” said Clara, laughing; “but,” she added, with a little flush of angry
     anticipation, “it’s nothing to laugh at after all. Suppose Maurice were to marry Miss Reredos!
     Oh, Mrs. Crofton, isn’t it shocking of you to put such dreadful thoughts in one’s head! Fancy,
     Alice! and to settle down hereabout—to be near us!—I am sure I could never be civil to her: and
     what do you suppose mamma would say?”</p>
    <p>“Maurice has nothing but his fellowship,” said Alice.</p>
    <p>“Well, to be sure, that is some comfort,” said Clara; “but then I daresay he might get a
     living if he tried, and Hugh could even”——</p>
    <p>Here Miss Polly came in with her letter, so we did not hear at that moment what could be done
     by Hugh, who, in the eyes of his little wife, was happily a person all-powerful.</p>
    <p>“My dear,” said Miss Polly, laying down the letter in her lap, and making a little
     preliminary lecture in explanation, “you remember that Emmy, my niece, two years ago, married
     again. Well, you know, one couldn’t well blame her. She was only one and twenty, poor little
     soul, when she was left with these two children; and I was but too glad to keep the little
     girls with me, so she was quite what people call without encumbrance, you see. So she married
     that curate
     <pb n="078"/> whom she had met at Fenosier. Well, it’s no use disguising it—Lady Greenfield and
     I are perhaps not such great friends as we ought to be, and Emmy has a temper of her own, and
     is just the weak-minded sort of little soul that will worry herself to death over those slights
     and annoyances that good near neighbors can do to each other—she ought to know better, after
     all she’s gone through. So here’s a letter from Elinor, telling me, of course, she’s as
     innocent as the day, and knows nothing about it—and so sorry for poor dear little Emmy—and so
     good and sweet-tempered herself, that really, if I were as near to her as Emmy is, I do believe
     I should do her a mischief. There’s the letter, Clare; you can read that part about Bertie out
     aloud if you please—perhaps the girls might like to hear it.”</p>
    <p>With which, shaking off a little heat of exasperation which had gathered about her, Miss
     Polly resumed her usual work and placidity. I confess it was not without a smile I read Lady
     Greenfield’s letter. I fortunately was under no temptations of the kind myself. If I had been,
     I daresay, I should have turned out exactly like my neighbors; but the spectators of a domestic
     squabble or successful piece of neighborly oppression and tyranny always see the ludicrous
     <pb n="079"/> side of it, and I could understand my lady’s mild malice and certainty of not
     being to blame, so well. It appeared that the poor little Emmy, completely overpowered by Lady
     Greenfield’s neighborly attentions, had in her turn worried her curate, and that the result of
     their united efforts was the withdrawal of the young clergyman, who did not feel himself able
     to cope with my lady at the Hall and his own exasperated little wife in the cottage, which
     unlooked-for result Lady Greenfield took the earliest opportunity of communicating to her dear
     Polly, with condolences over Emmy’s want of spirit and weak propensity, poor child!—to see
     neglect and slight where nothing of the kind was meant. I was so long getting over this, that,
     having heard from him recently myself, I did not make the haste I might have done to read what
     Lady Greenfield had to say about Bertie. I was reminded of this by seeing suddenly over the top
     of the letter a slight, quick movement made by Alice. It was only the most common change of
     position—nothing could be more natural; but there was a certain indescribable something of
     impatience and suspense in it which I comprehended by a sudden instinct. I stumbled immediately
     down to the paragraph about Bertie:</p>
    <p>“Pray tell Clare Crofton,” wrote Lady Greenfield,
     <pb n="080"/> “in case she should not have heard from Bertie lately—which is very likely, for
     young men I know don’t always keep up their correspondences as they ought, especially with
     elderly female relations, like dear Clare and myself—that I had a letter from my nephew by the
     last mail. He has not done yet lamenting that he could not get home and go to the Crimea, but
     says his old brigadier is suspicious of the Native army, and prophesies that there will be some
     commotion among them, which Bertie thinks will be great fun, and that a thorough cutting down
     would do these pampered fellows all the good in the world: so he says, you know, as boys will
     talk—but the Company’s officers laugh at the idea. If all keeps quiet, Bertie says he is rather
     sick of India—he thinks he will come back and see his friends: he thinks perhaps his dear
     cousin Clare has somebody in her pocket whom she means him to marry. To be sure, after giving
     him Estcourt, it would be only right that she should have a vote in the choice of his wife.
     Such a great matter, you know, for a boy like Bertie, his father’s fourth son, to come into a
     pretty little property like Estcourt—and so good of dear Clare!—pray tell her, with my
     love.”</p>
    <p>Not having taken the precaution to glance
     <pb n="081"/> over this, as I ought to have done from my previous acquaintance with “dear”
     Elinor, I had stumbled into the middle of that statement about the somebody whom cousin Clare
     had in her pocket before I was aware; and after an awkward pause, felt constrained to proceed.
     I thought the malice of the epistle altogether would defeat itself, and went on accordingly to
     the end of the sentence. Then I folded up the letter and gave it to Miss Polly.</p>
    <p>“I wonder does Lady Greenfield mean to make me so thoroughly uncomfortable when Bertie comes
     home that I shall not let him come here at all,” said I; “or to terrify me out of the
     possibility of introducing him to anybody, lest I should be said to be influencing his choice?
     But indeed she need not take the trouble. I know Bertie, and Bertie knows me much too well for
     the success of any such attempt. I will not have my liberty infringed upon, I assure you, Miss
     Polly, not by half a dozen Lady Greenfields.”</p>
    <p>“My dear, you don’t suppose me an accessory?” said Miss Polly, with a little spirit. “Did any
     one ever see such a wanton mischief-maker? I think she takes quite a delight in setting people
     by the ears. If Bertie ever did say such a thing, Clare,” said Miss Polly, with a little
     vehemence, “about somebody in your pocket, you
     <pb n="082"/> know, I could swear it was Elinor, and nobody else, who put it into his
     head.”</p>
    <p>By the merest inadvertence I am sure, certainly not by any evil intention, Miss Polly, as she
     delivered these words, allowed her mild old glances to stray towards Alice. I at the same
     moment chanced to give a furtive look in the same direction. Of course, just at the instant of
     danger, Alice, who had been immovable hitherto, suddenly looked up and detected us both. I do
     not know what meanings of which they were innocent her sensitive pride discovered in our eyes,
     but she sprang up with an impatience and mortification quite irrestrainable, her very neck
     growing crimson as she turned her head out of my sight. I understood well enough that burning
     blush of shame, and indignation, and wounded pride; it was not the blush of a love-sick girl,
     and my heart quaked when it occurred to me that Lady Greenfield might possibly have done a more
     subtle act of mischief by her letter than even she intended. Whom was I so likely to have in my
     pocket as Alice Harley? Indeed, was not she aware by intuition of some such secret desire in my
     mind? And suppose Bertie were coming home with tender thoughts towards the friend of his
     boyhood, and perhaps a little tender pleasant wonder, full of suggestions, why
     <pb n="083"/> Alice Harley, and she alone, out of her immediate companions, should remain
     unmarried—what good would that laudable, and much-to-be-desired frame of mind do to the poor
     boy now? If he came to Hilfont this very night, the most passionate lover, did not I know that
     Alice would reject him much more vehemently than she had rejected the Rector—scornfully,
     because conscious of the secret inclination towards him, which, alas! lay treacherous at the
     bottom of her heart? Oh, Lady Greenfield! Oh, dearest of “dear” Elinors! if you had anywhere
     two most sincere well-wishers, they were surely Miss Polly and myself!
     <pb n="084"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER X.</head>
    <p>“<hi>Why</hi> will not you come with us to London, Alice?” said I. “Mr. Crofton wishes it
     almost as much as I do. Such a change would do you good, and I do not need to tell you how
     pleasant it would be to me. Mrs. Harley and the young people at home can spare you. Kate, you
     know, is quite old enough to help your mother. Why are you so obstinate? You have not been in
     town in the season since the year after Clara’s marriage.”</p>
    <p>“I went up to see the pictures last year,” said Alice demurely.</p>
    <p>“Oh pray, Alice, don’t be so dreadfully proper!” cried Clara; “that’s what she’s coming to,
     Mrs. Crofton. The second week in May—to see all the exhibitions and hear an Oratorio in Exeter
     Hall—and make ‘mems.’ in her diary when she has got through them, like those frightful people
     who have their lives written! Oh dear, dear! to think our Alice should have stiffened into such
     a shocking old maid!”
     <pb n="085"/></p>
    <p>“Well, Clara, dear, I am very glad you find your own lot so pleasant that you would like to
     see everybody the same as yourself,” said Alice, sententiously, and with no small amount of
     mild superiority; “for my part I think the <hi>rôle</hi> of old maid is quite satisfactory,
     especially when one has so many nephews and nieces—and why should I go to London, Mrs. Crofton?
     It is all very well for Clara—Clara is in circumstances, of course, that make it convenient and
     natural—but as for me, who have nothing at all to do with your grand life, why should I go and
     vex myself with my own? Perhaps I might not have strength of mind to return comfortably to the
     cottage, and look after the butcher’s bills, and see that there were no cobwebs in the
     corners—and though I am of very little importance elsewhere,” said Alice, coloring a little,
     and with some unnecessary fervor, “I am of consequence at home.”</p>
    <p>“But then, you see,” said I, “Mrs. Harley has four daughters—and I have not one.”</p>
    <p>“Ah! by-and-by,” said Alice, with a smile and a sigh, “Mrs. Harley will only have one
     daughter. Kate and little Mary will marry just as Clara has done. I shall be left alone with
     mamma and Johnnie; that is why I don’t want to do anything which shall disgust me with my quiet
     life—at least that is one reason,” added Alice, with a
     <pb n="086"/> slight blush. “No, no—what would become of the world if we were all exactly
     alike—what a hum-drum, dull prospect it would be if everybody were just as happy, and as gay,
     and as much in the sun as everybody else. You don’t think, Clara, how much the gray tints of
     our household that is to be—mamma old, Johnnie, poor fellow, so often in trouble, and myself a
     stout housekeeper, will add to the picturesqueness of the landscape—much more than if our house
     were as gay as your own.”</p>
    <p>“Why, Alice, you are quite a painter!” cried I, in a little surprise.</p>
    <p>“No, indeed—I wish I were,” said Alice. “I wonder why it is that some people can <hi>do</hi>
     things, and some people, with all the will in the world, can only admire them when they’re
     done, and think—surely it’s my own fault—surely if I had tried I could have done as well! I
     suppose it’s one of the common troubles of women. I am sure I have looked at a picture, or read
     a book many a time, with the feeling that all that was in my heart if I could only have got it
     out. You smile, Mrs. Crofton—perhaps it’s very absurd—I daresay a woman ought to be very
     thankful when she can understand books, and has enough to live on without needing to work,”
     added this feminine misanthrope
     <pb n="087"/> with a certain pang of natural spite and malice in her voice.</p>
    <p>Spite and malice! I venture to use such ugly words, because it was my dear Alice, the purest,
     tenderest, and most lovable of women, who spoke.</p>
    <p>“There are a great many people in this world who think it a great happiness to have enough to
     live on,” said I, besides women. “I don’t know if Maurice has your ambition, Alice—but, at
     least he’s a man, and has no special disadvantages; yet, begging your pardons, young ladies, I
     think Alice is good for something more than <hi>he</hi> is, as the world stands.”</p>
    <p>“Ah, but then Maurice, you know, Mrs. Crofton—Maurice has doubts,” said Clara, with a slight
     pique at my boldness. “Poor Maurice! he says he must follow out his inquiries wherever they
     lead him, and however sad the issue may be. It is very dreadful—he may not be able to believe
     in anything before he is done—but then, he must not trifle with his conscience. And with such
     very serious things to trouble him, it is too bad he should be misunderstood.”</p>
    <p>“Don’t, Clara! hush!” whispered Alice, looking a little ashamed of this argument.</p>
    <p>“But why should I hush? Hugh says just the same as Mrs. Crofton—it’s very provoking—but these
     active people do not take into consideration
     <pb n="088"/> the troubles of a thoughtful mind, Maurice says.”</p>
    <p>“That is very likely,” said I, with a little complacency—“but remember this is all a
     digression—Alice, will you come to London or will you not?”</p>
    <p>Alice got up and made me a very pretty curtsey. “No, please, Mrs. Crofton, I will not,” said
     that very unmanageable young lady. She looked so provokingly pretty, piquant, and attractive at
     the moment that I longed to punish her. And Bertie was coming home! and her mind was
     irretrievably prejudiced against him; it was almost too much for human patience—but to be sure,
     when a woman is seven-and-twenty, she has some sort of right to know her own mind.</p>
    <p>At that moment little Clary Sedgwick, all in a flutter of pink ribbons, came rustling into
     the room, her very brief little skirt inflated with crinoline, and rustling half as much as her
     mamma’s—a miniature fine lady, with perfect little gloves, a miraculous little hat, and
     ineffable embroideries all over her; but with a child’s face so sweet, and a little princess’s
     air so enchanting, that one could no more find fault with her splendor than one could find
     fault with the still more exquisite decorations of a bird or a flower. Clary came to tell her
     mamma that the carriage was
     <pb n="089"/> at the door, and little Mrs. Sedgwick swept off immediately, followed by Alice,
     to get ready for her drive. They were going to call upon somebody near. Clary remained with me
     till they came back, and Derwie was not long of finding out his playfellow. Derwie (my boy was
     a vulgar-minded boy, with a strong preference for things over thoughts, as I have before said)
     stood speechless, lost in admiration of Clary’s grandeur. Then he cast a certain glance of
     half-comical comparison upon his own coat, worn into unspeakable shabbiness by three weeks of
     holidays, and upon his brown little hands, garnished with cuts and scratches, and I am grieved
     to say not even so clean as they might have been. When he had a little recovered his first
     amazement, Derwie turned her round and round with the tips of his fingers. Clary was by no
     means unwilling; she exhibited her Easter splendor with all the grace of a little belle.</p>
    <p>“Mamma, isn’t she grand?” said Derwie—“isn’t she pretty? I never saw her look so pretty
     before.”</p>
    <p>“Oh, Derwie, for shame!” said Clary, holding down her head with a pretty little affectation
     of confusion wonderful to behold.</p>
    <p>“For shame?—Why?—For you know you are pretty,” said my straightforward son, “whether
     <pb n="090"/> you are dressed grand or not. Mamma, did you ever see her like this before?—I
     never did. I should just like to have a great big glass case and put you in, Clary, so that you
     might always look just as you look now.”</p>
    <p>“Oh, Derwie!” cried Clary, again, but this time with unaffected horror, “I’d starve if you
     put me in there!”</p>
    <p>“No, because I’d bring you something every day,” said Derwie—“all my own pudding, and every
     cake I got, and the poor women in the village would be so pleased to come and look at you,
     Clary. Tell me what’s the name of this thing; I’ll tell Susan Stubbs, the dressmaker, all about
     you. They like to see ladies in grand dresses, all the cottage people; so do I; but I like to
     see you best of all. Here, Clary, Clary! don’t go away! Look at her pink little gloves,
     mamma!—and I say, Clary, haven’t you got a parasol?”</p>
    <p>“You silly boy! what do you suppose I want with a parasol when I’m going to drive with
     mamma?” cried Clary, with that indescribable little toss of her head.</p>
    <p>At that interesting moment the mamma, of whom this delightful little beauty was a
     reproduction, made her appearance, buttoning pink gloves like Clary’s, and rustling in her rosy,
     <pb n="091"/> shining, silken draperies, like a perfect rose, all dewy and fragrant, not even
     quite full-blown yet, in spite of the bud by her side. Alice came after her, a little demure,
     in her brown silk gown, very affectionate, and just a little patronizing to the pretty mother
     and daughter—on the whole rather superior to these lovely fooleries of theirs, on her eminence
     of unmarried woman. My pretty Alice! Her gravity, notwithstanding she was quite as much a child
     as either of them, was wonderfully amusing, though she did not know it. They went down-stairs
     with their pleasant feminine rustle, charming the echoes with their pleasant voices. My boy
     Derwie, entirely captivated by Mrs. Sedgwick’s sudden appearance on the scene—an enlarged
     edition of Clary—followed them to the door, vainly attempting to lay up some memoranda in his
     boyish mind for the benefit of Susan Stubbs. Pleased with them all, I turned to the window to
     see them drive away, when, lo! there suddenly emerged out of the curtains the dark and agitated
     face of Johnnie Harley. Had we said anything in our late conversation to wound the sensitive
     mind of the cripple? He had been there all the time.
     <pb n="092"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XI.</head>
    <p>“<hi>Johnnie</hi>, is there anything the matter. Why have you been sitting there?” cried
     I.</p>
    <p>“Oh, no, there’s nothing the matter,” said Johnnie, in such a tone as a wild beast making a
     snap at one might have used if it had possessed the faculty of words. “I was there because I
     happened to be there before you came into the room, Mrs. Crofton; I beg your pardon! I don’t
     mean to be rude.”</p>
    <p>“I think it is quite necessary you should say as much,” said I. “Your sisters and I have been
     talking here for some time, quite unaware of your presence. That is not becoming. No one ought
     to do such things, especially a young man of right feeling like yourself.”</p>
    <p>“Oh, you think I have right feelings,” cried Johnnie, bitterly, “you think I am man enough to
     know what honor means? That is something, at least. I have been well brought up, haven’t I?
     Mrs. Crofton,” continued the unfortunate youth, “you were rather hard upon Maurice
     <pb n="093"/> just now—I heard you, and he deserves it. If I were like Maurice, I should be
     ashamed to be as useless as he is. I’m not so useless now, in spite of everything; but you’ll
     be frank with me—why does Alice speak of keeping house with my mother and <hi>Johnnie</hi>?
     Why, when Kate, and even little Mary, are supposed to have homes of their own, and Maurice, of
     course, to be provided for—why is there to be a special establishment, all neutral colored and
     in the shade, for my mother, and Alice, and <hi>me</hi>?”</p>
    <p>I sat gazing at the poor youth in the most profound confusion and amazement. What could I say
     to him? How, if he did not perceive it himself, could I explain the naturalness of poor Alice’s
     anticipations? I had not a word to say; his question took me entirely by surprise, and struck
     me dumb—it was unanswerable.</p>
    <p>“You do not say anything,” said Johnnie, vehemently. “Why does Alice suppose <hi>she</hi>
     will have to take care of me all my life through? Why should I go to contribute that
     alternative of shade which makes the landscape picturesque?—picturesque!” exclaimed poor
     Johnnie, breathing out the words upon a long breath of wrath and indignation; “is that all I am
     good for? Do you suppose God has made me in a man’s form, with a man’s heart, only to add a subtle
     <pb n="094"/> charm to another man’s happiness by the contrast of my misery? I believe in no
     such thing, Mrs. Crofton. Is that what Alice means?”</p>
    <p>“I believe in no such thing either,” said I, relieved to be able to say something; “and you
     forget, Johnnie, that the same life which Alice assigned to you she chose for herself. She
     thought, I suppose, because your health is not strong, that you would choose to live at
     home—she thought”——</p>
    <p>“Mrs. Crofton,” said Johnnie, “why don’t you say it out? she thought—but why say thought—she
      <hi>knew</hi> I was a cripple, and debarred from the joyous life of man; she thought that to
     such as me no heavenly help could come; it did not occur to her that perhaps there might be an
     angel in the spheres who would love me, succor me, give me a place among the happy—yes, even
     me! You think I speak like a fool,” continued the young man, the flush of his excitement
     brightening all his face, and the natural superlatives of youth, all the warmer and stronger
     for the physical infirmities which seemed to shut him out from their legitimate use, pouring to
     his lips, “and so I should have been, but for the divine chance that brought me here. Ah, Mrs.
     Crofton, you did not know what an Easter of the soul you were asking me to! I came only
     <pb n="095"/> a boy, scarcely aware of the dreary colors in which life lay before me. Now I can
     look at these dreary colors only by way of Alice’s contrast—to make the reality more
     glorious—for I too shall have the home and the life of a man!”</p>
    <p>He stopped, not because his words were exhausted, but because breath failed him—he stood
     before me, raising himself erect out of his habitual stoop of weakness, strengthened by the
     inspiring force of the great delusion, which gave color to his face and nerve to his hand.
     Looking at him so, his words did not seem such sad, bitter, heart-breaking folly as they were.
     Poor boy! poor Johnnie! how would he fall prostrate upon the cold, unconsolatory earth, when
     this spell was broken! I could have cried over him, as he stood there defying me; he had drunk
     that cup of Circe—but he did not know in his momentary intoxication that it was poison to
     him.</p>
    <p>“My dear Johnnie,” said I, “I am very glad of anything that makes you happy—but there is
     surely no occasion to speak so strongly. Alice, I must remind you again, chose exactly the same
     life for herself that she supposed for you”——</p>
    <p>“Alice has had her youth and her choice,” said Johnnie, with a calmer tone, and sinking,
     <pb n="096"/> his first excitement over, into a chair; “but she does not think Maurice is
     likely to share that gray life of hers—Maurice, who, as you say yourself, is of no use in the
     world—nor Harry, whom they have all forgotten now he is in Australia, nor the children at home;
     only mamma when she is old, and <hi>Johnnie</hi>—well, it is of no use speaking. A man’s
     business is not to speak, but to work.”</p>
    <p>“That is very true, certainly,” said I: “but tell me, will you—if it is not wrong to ask—what
     has made this great change in your ideas, all at once?”</p>
    <p>“Ah, Mrs. Crofton, don’t you know?” cried Johnnie, blushing, a soft overpowering youthful
     blush, which would have done no discredit to Clara herself; and the poor, foolish boy looked at
     me with an appealing triumphant look, as if he at once entreated me to say, and defied me to
     deny that <hi>she</hi> was altogether an angel, and he the very happiest of boys or men.</p>
    <p>“My dear boy,” said I, “don’t be angry with me. I’ve known you all your life, Johnnie. I
     don’t mean to say a word against Miss Reredos—but tell me, has there been any explanation
     between her and you?”</p>
    <p>He hesitated a moment, blushing still.</p>
    <p>“No,” he said, after a pause; “no—I have
     <pb n="097"/> not been able to arrange my thoughts at all yet. I have thought of nothing
     but—but herself—and this unimaginable hope of happiness—and I am a man of honor, Mrs. Crofton.
     I will not speak to her till I know whether I have anything but love to offer—not because I am
     so base as to suppose that money could recommend a man to <hi>her</hi>, or so foolish as to
     think that I will ever have anything beyond <hi>income</hi>; but when I do speak, you
     understand, Mrs. Crofton, it is not for vague love-making, but to ask her to be my wife.”</p>
    <p>He looked at me with his sudden air of manhood and independence, again somewhat defiant.
     Heaven help the poor boy! I heard myself groaning aloud in the extremity of my bewilderment and
     confusion; poor Johnnie, with his superb self-assumption!—he, a fortnight ago, the cheerfulest
     of boy invalids, the kindest of widow’s sons!—and she, five years older than he, at the lowest
     reckoning, an experienced young lady, with dreams of settlements and trousseaux occupying her
     mature mind! Alack, alack! what was to come of it? I sat silent, almost gaping with wonderment
     at the boy. At last I caught at the idea of asking him what his prospects or intentions
     were—though without an idea that he had any prospects, or knew in the least what he was talking about.
     <pb n="098"/></p>
    <p>“You spoke of income, Johnnie—may I ask what you were thinking of?”</p>
    <p>Johnnie blushed once more, though after a different fashion; he grew confidential and
     eager—like himself.</p>
    <p>“I have told no one else,” he said, “but I will tell you, Mrs. Crofton, not only because you
     are our oldest friend, but because I have just told you something so much more important. I—I
     have written something—nobody knows!”</p>
    <p>“Oh, you poor boy!” cried I, quite thankful to be able on less delicate ground to make an
     outcry over him; “don’t you think half the people in the country have written something?—and
     are you to make an income by that?”</p>
    <p>“I beg your pardon,” said Johnnie, with dignity, “but it’s <hi>accepted</hi>, Mrs.
     Crofton—that makes all the difference. Half the country don’t have letters from the booksellers
     saying that it’s very good and they’ll publish it on the usual terms. I could show you the
     letter,” added my young author, blushing once more, and putting his hand to his
     breast-pocket—“I have it here.”</p>
    <p>And there it was, accordingly, to my intense wonderment—and Johnnie’s hopes had, however
     small, an actual foundation. On the book about
     <pb n="099"/> to be published on “the usual terms” the poor boy had built up his castle. Here
     he was to bring Miss Reredos to a fairy bower of love and literature—which, alas! I doubted
     would be very little to that young lady’s taste; but I dared not tell Johnnie so—poor,
     dreaming, foolish cripple-boy! Nothing afterwards, perhaps, would taste so sweet as that
     delusion, and though the natural idea that “it would be kindness to undeceive him” of course
     moved me strongly, I had not the boldness to try, knowing very well that it would do no good.
     He must undeceive himself, that was evident. Thank Heaven he was so young! When his eyes were
     opened he would be the bitterest and most miserable of misanthropes for a few months, and then,
     it was to be hoped, things would mend. I saw no other ending to Johnnie’s romance. But he went
     hobbling away from me with his stick and his stoop, as full of his momentary fallacious
     happiness, as if he had been the handsome young prince of the fairy tale, whom the love of Miss
     Reredos would charm back to his proper comeliness. Alas, poor Johnnie! If his Laura could have
     wrought that miracle I fear the spell was still impossible, for lack of the love—miraculous
     magic! the only talisman which even in a fairy tale can charm the lost beauty back.
     <pb n="100"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XII.</head>
    <p>“<hi>Now</hi>, if I had the luck to hold a confidential talk with Maurice, I should have gone
     round the entire Harley family,” said I to myself the next morning, “and be in the secret of
     sundry imaginations which have not seen the light of day—but Maurice, fortunately, is not
     likely to make me nor any one else his <hi>confidante</hi>. I wonder if there is anything at
     all concerning him which it would be worth one’s while to be curious about?”</p>
    <p>The question was solved sooner than I thought. When everybody had left our pleasant
     breakfast-room but myself, and I, with my little basket of keys in my hand, was preparing to
     follow, Maurice, who had been lingering by the great window, startled me by asking for a few
     minutes’ conversation, “if I was quite at leisure.” I put down my basket with the utmost
     promptitude. Curiosity, if not courtesy, made me perfectly at leisure to hear anything he might
     have to say.
     <pb n="101"/></p>
    <p>“I have undertaken a very foolish office,” said Maurice—“I have had the supreme conceit and
     presumption of supposing that I could perhaps plead with you, Mrs. Crofton, the cause of a
     friend.”</p>
    <p>“I trust I shall feel sufficiently flattered,” said I, assuming the same tone. “And pray who
     is the friend who has the advantage of your support, Maurice? and what does he want of me?”</p>
    <p>The young man colored and looked affronted—he was highly sensitive to ridicule, like all
     self-regarding men.</p>
    <p>“Nay, pray don’t convince me so distinctly of my folly before I start,” he said; “the friend
     is a college friend of mine, who was so absurd as to marry before he had anything to live on; a
     very good fellow with—oh! don’t be afraid—perfectly sound views, I assure you, Mrs. Crofton,
     though he is acquainted with me.”</p>
    <p>“I should think being acquainted with you very likely to help a sensible man to sound views,”
     said I, with some natural spite, thankful for the opportunity of sending a private arrow into
     him in passing; “and what does your friend want that I can help him in?”</p>
    <p>“The Rector of Estcourt is an old man, and very ill,” said Maurice, after a pause of offence;
     <pb n="102"/> “Owen, my friend, has a curacy in Simonborough. I told him I should
     venture—though of course aware I had not the slightest title to influence you—to name him to
     Mrs. Crofton, in case of anything happening.”</p>
    <p>“Aware that you have not the slightest title to influence me—that means, does it not,
     Maurice?” said I, “that you rather think you have some claim upon that Rectory at Estcourt, and
     that you magnanimously resign it in favor of your friend? It was your father’s—it is your
     mother’s desire to see you in his place—you have thought of it vaguely all your life as a kind
     of inheritance, which you were at liberty to accept or withdraw from; now, to be sure, we are
     very, very old friends—is not that plainly, and without any superfluity of words, what you
     mean?”</p>
    <p>Maurice made a still longer pause—he was seized with the restlessness common to men when they
     are rather hard tested in conversation. He got up unawares, picked up a book off the nearest
     table, as if he meant to answer me by means of that, and then returned to his chair. Then,
     after a little further struggle, he laughed, growing very red at the same time.</p>
    <p>“You put the case strongly, but I will not say you are wrong,” he answered; “after all, I
     believe, if it must be put into words, that is about
     <pb n="103"/> how the thing stands; but, of course, you know I am perfectly aware”——</p>
    <p>“Exactly,” said I; “we both understand it, and it is not necessary to enter further into that
     part of the subject; but now, tell me, Maurice, supposing your rights of natural succession to
     be perfectly acknowledged, why is it that you substitute another person, and postpone your own
     settlement to his?”</p>
    <p>“My dear Mrs. Crofton,” cried Maurice, restored to himself by the question, “what would not I
     give to be able to accept as mine that calm, religious life?—what would not I relinquish for a
     faith as entire and simple as my friend Owen’s? But that is my misfortune. I suppose my mind is
     not so wholesomely constituted as other people’s. I cannot believe so and so, just because I am
     told to believe it—I cannot shape my creed according to the received pattern. If I could, I
     should be but too happy; but <hi>que voulez-vous</hi>? a man cannot act against his
     convictions—against his nature.”</p>
    <p>“Nay, I assure you I am a very calm spectator,” said I; “I would not have either one thing or
     another. I have not the least doubt that you will know better some day, and why should I
     concern myself about the matter?”</p>
    <p>“Why, indeed?” echoed Maurice, faintly; but
     <pb n="104"/> he was mortified; he expected a little honor, at the very least, as his natural
     due, if not a womanish attempt at proselytizing. The discomfiture of my adversary was balm to
     my eyes—I was, as may be perceived, in a perfectly unchristian state of mind.</p>
    <p>“And how then about yourself?—what do you mean to do?” asked I; “you are getting towards the
     age when men begin to think of setting up houses and families for themselves. Do you mean to be
     a College Don all your life, Maurice? I fear that must be rather an unsatisfactory kind of
     existence; and one must take care, if that is the case, not to ask any young ladies again to
     meet you—some one might happen to be too captivating for your peace of mind—a Miss Reredos
     might outweigh a fellowship;—such things have been even with men of minds as original as your
     own.”</p>
    <p>“Miss Reredos! ah, she amuses herself!” said Maurice, with a conscious smile.</p>
    <p>“Yes, I think you are very well matched,” said I, calmly; “you will not do her much harm, nor
     she inflict a very deep wound on your heart, but it might have happened differently. People as
     wise as yourself, when their turn comes, are often the most foolish in these concerns.”</p>
    <p>“Ah, you forget that I am past youth,” said
     <pb n="105"/> Maurice; “you, Mrs. Crofton, have made a private agreement, I suppose, with the
     old enemy, but I have no such privilege—I have done with that sort of thing long ago. However,
     about Owen, if I may remind you, is there anything to say?”</p>
    <p>“Somebody asked me for the living of Estcourt when your father lay dying; I was younger then,
     as you say—I was deeply horrified,” said I. “We must wait.”</p>
    <p>“Ah, yes; but my father was a man in the prime of life, and this is an old man, whom even his
     own family cannot expect to live long,” said Maurice; “but, of course, if you do not like it, I
     have not another word to say.”</p>
    <p>“Ah, Maurice,” said I, forgetting for a moment the personage who sat before me, and thinking
     of Dr. Harley’s death-bed, and the fatherless children there so helpless and dependent on other
     people’s judgment, “your father was a good man, but he had not the heart to live after he lost
     his fortune, and your mother is a good woman, but she had not the heart to bring you up poorly
     and bravely in your own home. They are my dear friends, and I dare speak of them even to you.
     Why did she send you to that idle uncle of yours, to be brought up in idleness?—you big,
     strong, indolent man! What is
     <pb n="106"/> the good of you, though you are Fellow of Exeter? You might have been of some use
     in the world by this time if you had lived among your brothers and sisters, a widow’s son.”</p>
    <p>Maurice started—rose up—made a surprised exclamation of my name—and then dropped into his
     chair again without saying anything. He did not answer me a word. The offence melted out of his
     face, but he kept his eyes down and did not look at me. I could not tell whether he was angry—I
     had been moved by my own feelings beyond, for the moment, thinking of his.</p>
    <p>“Ask your friend to come and see you here,” I said, after an awkward little pause; “say, Mr.
     Crofton and I will be glad if he will dine with us before you go—perhaps, to-morrow, Maurice,
     and that will leave him time to get home on Saturday—and we will think about it, should the
     living of Estcourt fall vacant. Forgive me,” I continued, as I rose to go away, “I said more
     than I ought to have said.”</p>
    <p>He took my hand and wrung it with an emphatic pressure; what he said I made out only with
     difficulty, I think it was, “No more than is true.”</p>
    <p>And I left him with somewhat uncomfortable feelings. I had not the very least right to
     lecture this young man; quite the other way—for
     <pb n="107"/> was not I a woman and an illiterate person, and he Fellow of his College? I
     confess I did not feel very self-complacent as I left the room. This third confidential
     interview, in which I had over-passed the prudent limits of friendliness, did not <hi>feel</hi>
     at all satisfactory. Nevertheless, I was glad to see that Maurice was magnanimous—that he was
     likely to forgive me—and that possibly there were elements of better things even in his
     regarding indolence. All which symptoms, though in a moral point of view highly gratifying,
     made me but feel the more strongly that I had gone beyond due limits, and exceeded the margin
     of truth-telling and disagreeableness which one is <hi>not</hi> allowed towards one’s guests,
     and in one’s own house.
     <pb n="108"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XIII.</head>
    <p><hi>It</hi> may be allowed to me to confess that I watched during the remainder of that day
     with a little natural, but extremely absurd curiosity to see “what effect” our conversation had
     upon Maurice Harley. After I had got over my own unpleasant sensations, I began to flatter
     myself, with natural vanity, that perhaps I might have “done him good.” I had an inkling that
     it was absurd, but that made very little difference, and I acknowledge that I felt quite a new
     spur and stimulus of interest in the young man. I listened to his chance observations during
     the day with an attention which I had never before bestowed upon them. For the moment, instead
     of simple impatience of his indolence, and virtuous, gentlemanly good-for-nothingness, I began
     to sympathize somewhat in the lamenting admiration of his friends that so much talent should be
     lost to the world. Altogether, in my capacity of hostess to Maurice, I was for that day a
     reformed and penitent person, full of compunction for my
     <pb n="109"/> offence. I am obliged to confess, however, that there was no corresponding change
     upon my guest. Maurice demeaned himself that day exactly as he had done the day before—was as
     superior, and critical, and indifferent, as much above the common uses of life and motives of
     humanity as he had ever been. Still, my penitential feelings lasted out the day, and it was not
     till I perceived how entirely he was laying himself out to charm and captivate Miss Reredos and
     make up to her for the attentions she had paid him, that I detected myself in the simple-minded
     vanity of expecting to have “done him good.” The flirtation that evening was so evident, and
     Maurice threw himself so much more warmly into it than on any former occasion, that we, the
     spectators, were all roused to double observation. Johnnie sat behind the little table in the
     corner, with the stereoscope before him, blazing the wildest rage out of his half-hidden eyes
     upon his brother, and sometimes quite trembling with passion. Alice moved about with a little
     indignant dilation of her person and elevation of her head—half out of regard to the honor of
     her “sex,” which Miss Reredos, she supposed, was compromising, and half out of shame and
     annoyance at the “infatuation” of her brother. And not quite knowing what
     <pb n="110"/> this new fervor might portend, I took an opportunity as I passed by Maurice’s
     chair to speak to him quietly—</p>
    <p>“Is Miss Reredos, then, to be more attractive than the fellowship?” I said, lingering a
     moment as I passed.</p>
    <p>Maurice looked up at me with a certain gleam of boyish malice and temper in his eye.</p>
    <p>“You know we are very well matched, and I cannot do <hi>her</hi> much harm,” he said, quoting
     my own words.</p>
    <p>This was the good I had done him—this, out of a conversation which ended so seriously, was
     the only seed that had remained in that fertile and productive soil, the mind of Maurice
     Harley, and behold already its fructifications. I went back to my seat, and sat down
     speechless. I was inexpressibly angry and mortified for the moment. To be sure it was a little
     private and personal vanity which made the special sting. Yet he had been unquestionably moved
     by my candid opinion of him, in which very little admiration was mingled with the regret—but
     had I not piqued <hi>his</hi> vanity as well?</p>
    <p>As for Johnnie, having been taken into his confidence, I was doubly alive to the feelings
     with which he watched his brother. Miss Reredos managed admirably well between the
     <pb n="111"/> lover real and the lover make-believe, <hi>her</hi> vanity being of course in
     play even more decidedly than anybody else’s. I believe she was quite deceived by the sudden
     warmth of Maurice. I believe the innocent young woman fell captive in an instant, not to his
     fascinations, but to the delusion of believing that she had fascinated him, and that the name
     of the Fellow of Exeter was that evening inscribed upon her long list of victims; but,
     notwithstanding, she would not give up Johnnie; I suppose his youthful adoration was something
     new and sweet to the experienced young lady—the absoluteness of his trust in her and admiration
     of her was delicious to the pretty coquette, with whom warier men were on their guard. Over
     Johnnie she was absolute, undisputed sovereign—he was ready to defy the whole world in her
     behalf, and disown every friend he had at her bidding. Such homage, even from a cripple, was
     too sweet to be parted with. Somehow, by means of those clever eyes of hers, even while at the
     height of her flirtation with Maurice, she kept Johnnie in hand, propitiated, and calmed him. I
     don’t know how it is done—I don’t think Alice knew either; but I am not sure that a certain
     instinctive perception of the manner of that skilful double movement did not come natural to
     Clara Sedgwick, and
     <pb n="112"/> stimulate her disgust at the proceeding. If she had not been married so early and
     been so happy a little wife, Clara might have been a little flirt herself—who knows? I saw that
     she had an intuition how it was done.</p>
    <p>As for Miss Polly, she could do nothing but talk about the advantages of useful training for
     girls. “If these poor children should turn out flirts, Clare!” she cried, in dismay. To be
     sure, Emmy, the pretty one, was only ten and a half—but still if education could hinder such a
     catastrophe, there was certainly no time to be lost.</p>
    <p>Mr. Owen came to dinner next day, according to my invitation. He was a young man, younger
     than Maurice, and a hundred times more agreeable. He was curate of St. Peter’s, in
     Simonborough, where a curate among the multitude of divines congregated about the cathedral,
     was as hard to find or make any note of as the famous needle in the bundle of hay. And it is
     very probable that he was not a brilliant preacher, or noted for any gift in particular; but I
     liked the honest, manful young fellow, who was not ashamed either to do his work or to talk of
     it when occasion called—nor afraid to marry upon his minute income, nor to tell me with a
     passing blush and a happy laugh, which became him, what a famous little housekeeper his wife
     <pb n="113"/> was, and what fun they had over her economics. Maurice heard and smiled—calm,
     ineffable, superior—and wished he could only submit his unhappily more enlightened mind to a
     simple faith like Owen’s. And Owen, on his part, was respectful of the dainty disbeliever, and
     took off his hat to that scepticism, born of idleness and an unoccupied mind, for which I, in
     my secret heart, for sheer impatience and disgust, could have whipped the Fellow of Exeter. Mr.
     Owen was as respectful of it as if that pensive negation had been something actual and of
     solemn importance. He shook his head and talked to me mysteriously of poor Harley. Maurice had
     rather distinguished himself at college before he sank into his fellowship. His old companions
     who were of the same standing were a little proud of his scholarly attainments. “He could be
     anything if he chose,” they said to themselves; and because Maurice did not choose, his
     capabilities looked all the grander. Owen was quite a partisan of Harley. “What a pity it was!”
     the honest fellow said, “with such a mind, if he could but get right views”——</p>
    <p>At which juncture I struck the excellent young man dumb and breathless by uttering aloud a
     fervent desire and prayer that by some happy chance Maurice should fall in love.
     <pb n="114"/></p>
    <p>Mr. Owen looked at me for a moment thunderstruck, the words of his own former sensible
     sentence hanging half-formed about his lips; then, when he had recovered himself a little, he
     smiled and said, “You have so much confidence in a female preacher? No doubt they are
     irresistible—but not in matters of doctrine, perhaps.”</p>
    <p>“No such thing,” said I, “I have no confidence in female preachers or religious courtship;
     but apart from the intense satisfaction which I own I should have in seeing Maurice make, as
     people say, a fool of himself, that is the only means I see of bringing him back to life.”</p>
    <p>“To life!” said my new acquaintance, with a lively look of interrogation.</p>
    <p>“Oh, I do not mean anything grand; I mean common life, with the housekeeping to be provided
     for,” said I smiling, “and the daily bread, and the other mouths that have to eat it. I
     daresay, even you yourself, who seem to stand in no such need as Maurice, have found out
     something in the pleasant jingle you were talking of—of Mrs. Owen’s basket of keys.”</p>
    <p>The young man blushed once more that slight passing color of happiness, and answered gravely,
     yet with a smile, “It is true, I see what you mean—and it is very possible indeed—but,” he
     <pb n="115"/> added, stopping abruptly, and looking at his friend, who was in the full tide of
     flirtation with Miss Reredos, “Mrs. Crofton, look there!”</p>
    <p>I shook my head. “Nothing will come of it,” said I; “they are amusing themselves.”</p>
    <p>Condign punishment came upon my head almost as I spoke; I had turned my head incautiously,
     and Johnnie and Alice had both heard me.</p>
    <p>“Amusing themselves!” cried Johnnie, hissing the words into my ears in a whisper. “Amusing!
     do you suppose that it is anything but her angel-sweetness, Mrs. Crofton, that makes her so
     forbearing with Maurice—<hi>my</hi> brother? I adore her for it,” cried (but in a whisper) the
     deluded boy.</p>
    <p>“Amusing themselves!” cried Alice, raising her head, “and <hi>you</hi> can say so, Mrs.
     Crofton? Oh, I am ashamed, to think a woman should forget herself so strangely; I could forgive
     anything—almost anything,” said Alice, correcting herself with a blush, “which really sprang
     from true strong feeling; but flirting—amusing themselves! Oh, Mrs. Crofton!”</p>
    <p>“My dear child, it is not my fault,” said I, “I have no hand in the matter, either one way or
     the other.”</p>
    <p>“Yes, that is true,” said Alice, with that lively
     <pb n="116"/> impatience and disinclination to suffer a dear friend to rest in an opinion
     different from her own, which I have felt myself and understood perfectly,—“but you will not
     see how unworthy it is—how dishonoring to women! That is what wounds me.”</p>
    <p>“Is it not dishonoring to men as well?—two are playing at it, and the other creature is
     accountable likewise. Are you not concerned for the credit of your sex?” said I, turning to
     Owen.</p>
    <p>The young curate laughed, Alice blushed and looked deeply affronted, and Johnnie, turning all
     the fury of his jealousy upon me, looked as if it would have pleased him to do me some bodily
     harm. Well, well, one can bear all that—and I am happy to say that I think I accelerated
     distantly and humbly by this said conversation, the coming on of Maurice Harley’s fate.
     <pb n="117"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XIV.</head>
    <p><hi>Very</hi> shortly after our little party separated, it was time to go back to London to
     Derwent’s treadmill; our holiday was over—and as Alice had positively declined my invitation to
     go with us to London, we were again for several months quite separated from our country
     friends. I heard from them in the meantime various scraps of information, from which I could
     gather vaguely how their individual concerns went on. Mr. Reredos was again a visitor at the
     cottage, and Mrs. Harley, who was not in the secret of his previous rejection, wrote to me two
     or three long, anxious, confidential letters about his evident devotion to her dear girl—and
     what did I think of it? It was, the good mother said, the position of all others which she
     would choose for her daughter, if it lay in her decision—a country clergyman’s wife, the same
     position which she herself had held long ago, when Dr. Harley lived, and she was happy!—but she
     could not make out what
     <pb n="118"/> Alice’s mind was. Alice was sometimes cordial and sometimes distant to this
     candidate for her favor—“And I often fear that it will just be with Mr. Reredos as with the
     rest,” said Mrs. Harley, despondingly—“and I like him so much—he reminds me of what her dear
     father was once—and the connection would altogether be so eligible that I should be very sorry
     if it came to nothing. Do you think, dear Mrs. Crofton, that you could use your influence with
     her on this subject? My dear girl is so shocked and disgusted with the idea of people marrying
     for an establishment, that I really do not venture to say a word to her about her own
     establishment in life; but <hi>you</hi> know as well as I do, dear Mrs. Crofton, that such
     things must be thought of, and really this is so thoroughly eligible”——</p>
    <p>Alice followed on the same key.</p>
    <p>“Mamma teases me again on that everlasting subject, dear Mrs. Crofton; there is some one so
     completely eligible, she says—and I quite feel it—so entirely eligible that if there was not
     another in the world! Mamma is provoked, and says if somebody came who was quite the reverse of
     eligible that I should answer differently—and indeed I am not sure but there is justice in what
     she says. But do interfere on my behalf, please; I prefer to be always Alice Harley—do, please,
     <pb n="119"/> dear Mrs. Crofton, persuade my mother not to worry me, but to believe that I know
     my own mind.”</p>
    <p>From which double correspondence I inferred that Mr. Reredos had somehow managed to resume
     his suit and to make a partisan of Mrs. Harley without giving a desperate and hopeless affront
     to the pride of Alice, which raised my opinion of his generalship so greatly that I began to
     imagine there might possibly be some likelihood of success for the Rector—a conclusion which I
     fear did not gratify me so much as Mrs. Harley had imagined it should.</p>
    <p>Along with this information I heard of a sister of Mr. Owen’s, who was paying them a visit—of
     repeated excursions into Simonborough—of Maurice’s growing relish for home, and some anxieties
     on the young man’s part about his future life. And Johnnie’s book was published—a book which in
     my wildest imagination I could not have supposed to be produced by the cripple boy, who, out of
     the cottage, knew nothing whatever of life. Johnnie’s hero was a hero who did feats of strength
     and skill unimaginable—tamed horses, knocked down bullies, fought, rode, rowed, and cricketed,
     after the most approved fashion of the modern youth, heroical and muscular—and in his leisure
     hours made love!—such love!—full
     <pb n="120"/> of ecstasies and despairs, quite inconceivable to any imagination above
     twenty—but all enforced and explained with such perfect ingenuousness and good faith that one
     could have hugged the boy all the time for the exquisite and delightful folly, in which there
     did not mix an evil thought. Nothing could well be more remarkable than this fiery outburst of
     confined and restrained life from the bosom of the cripple, to whom all these active delights
     were impossible—it was profoundly pathetic too, to me. Poor Johnnie! with that fervid
     imagination in him, how was he to bear the gray life which Alice had predicted—the life which
     must be his, notwithstanding all his dreams and hopes? How, when it came to that, was he to
     undergo the downfall of his first miraculous castle in the air, his vain and violent
     love-passion? Poor heart, foredoomed! would he ever learn to bring the music of Patience, so
     lovely to those who hear, so hard to those who make it, out of those life-chords which were
     drawn all awry, beyond the reach of happiness? I was happy myself in those days. I had little
     desire to think of the marvellous life to come in which all these problems shall be made clear.
     I could not cast forward my mind beyond this existence—and the strange inequality between this
     boy’s mind and his fate vexed me at the heart.
     <pb n="121"/></p>
    <p>And so, quite quietly and gradually, the time stole on. I heard nothing more from poor Bertie
     Nugent, in India; he meant to come home, but he had not yet obtained his leave of absence, and
     it remained quite uncertain when we should see him. Everything was very quiet at home. Our
     fighting was over—our national pride and confidence in our own arms and soldiers, revived by
     actual experience; everything looking prosperous within the country, and nothing dangerous
     without.</p>
    <p>It was at this time that the dreadful news of the Indian mutiny came upon the country like
     the shock of an earthquake. News more frightful never startled a peaceful people. Faces paled,
     and hearts sickened, even among people who had no friends in that deadly peril; and as for us,
     who had relatives and connections to be anxious for, it is impossible to describe the fear that
     took possession of us. I knew nobody there but Bertie, and he, thank Heaven, was but a man, and
     could only be killed at the worst; but I had people belonging to me there, though I did not
     know them; people whom I had heard of for years and years, though I had never seen them;
     cousins, and such like—Nugents—with women among them—God help us! creatures who might have to
     bear tortures more cruel than death. The
     <pb n="122"/> thought woke me up into a restless fever of horror and anxiety, which I cannot
     describe. Perhaps I felt the hideous contrast more because of my own perfect safety and
     happiness, but I could neither sleep by night nor smile by day, for the vision of that horrible
     anguish which had fallen upon some, and might be—might be—for anything I knew—at any moment—ah!
     the thought was too much for flesh and blood. It was growing towards autumn, yet I, who hated
     London, was reluctant that year to leave it. We were nearer to those news which it was so
     sickening to hear, yet so dreadful to be out of reach of, and it seemed to me as if it would be
     impossible to go into those tranquil country places, where all was happy, and still, and
     prosperous, with such a cloud of horror, and fear, and rage about one’s heart. At that time I
     almost think I could have heard without any great additional pang that Bertie himself had been
     killed. He was a man, thank Heaven, and they could only kill him! Mere family affection was
     lost for the moment in the overpowering horror of the time.</p>
    <p>But the first miseries were over by the time we went to Hilfont—it had begun to be a fight of
     man to man—that is to say, of one man to some certain number of heathen creatures, from a dozen
     to a hundred—and the news, breathless
     <pb n="123"/> news, mad with gasps of grief, anxiety, and thanksgiving, did not now strike such
     horror and chill to our blood. We went home and quieted ourselves, and grew anxious about
     Bertie—very anxious. Of course he was in the thick of the fight. If he had not been, could we
     ever have forgiven him?—but he was, and we had only to wait, and long, and tremble for news, to
     catch here and there a glimpse of him through obscure telegraphic reports, and slow dispatches,
     coming long, long, and slow, after that bewildering, tantalizing snatch of half-comprehensible
     tidings. Then I saw, for the first time, how thoroughly the young man, though he had been away
     eight years, kept his hold upon our hearts. Derwent would ride a dozen miles to the railway for
     a chance of hearing a little earlier than was possible at Hilfont, when the <hi>new</hi> news
     came in; everybody about the house looked breathless till they heard if the Captain, as they
     called him, was still safe. As for Alice Harley, I do not remember that she ever asked a
     question—she went and came about the house, read all the papers, listened to all the
     conversations, stood by and heard everything, while her sister Clara poured forth inquiry upon
     inquiry, while the gentlemen discussed the whole matter, and decided what everybody must do;
     while even Lady Greenfield, drawn towards me,
     <pb n="124"/> though we were but indifferent friends, by a common touch of nature (for I cannot
     deny that she liked her nephews), consulted and argued where Bertie could be now, and wished
     him safe home. My little Derwent, with a flush on his childish cheeks, and tears in his eyes,
     cried out against her; “Do you think Bertie will come safe home when they are murdering the
     women and the babies?” cried Derwie, with a half-scream of childish excitement. “Bertie?—if he
     did, I would like to kill him; but he never, never, will till they’re all on board the ships—he
     had better be killed than come safe home!”</p>
    <p>The tears were in my own eyes, so that I did not see the child very clearly as he spoke; but
     I saw Alice bend quickly down to kiss him, and heard in the room the sound of one sob—a sound
     surprised out of somebody’s heart. Not Lady Greenfield’s, who put her handkerchief to her eyes,
     and said that really she was only human, and might be forgiven for wishing her own relations
     safe. Miss Polly had come with her sister-in-law that day—she was paler than ever, the tender
     old lady. She cried a little as we talked, but it was not out of her calm old heart that such a
     sob of anguish and passion came.</p>
    <p>“My dear,” said Miss Polly, speaking as if she addressed me, but not looking in my direction,
     <pb n="125"/> “I’m afraid Derwie’s right; if he die he must do his duty—there’s no talk of
     being safe in such times.”</p>
    <p>“It is very easy for you to speak,” said Lady Greenfield, and I believe she thought so; “but
     Clare and I feel differently—he is not a relation of yours.”</p>
    <p>“I pray for the dear boy, night and morning, all the same. God bless him, at this moment,
     wherever he may be!” said Miss Polly. I was conscious of a quick, sudden movement as the words
     fell, soft and grave, from her dear old lips. It was Alice who had left the room.</p>
    <p>She could not bear it any longer. <hi>She</hi> did not belong to him—she was not old enough
     to speak like Miss Polly—she durst not flutter forth her anxiety for her old playfellow as
     Clara did. Her heart was throbbing and burning in her young warm breast. She did not say a word
     or ask a question; but when the tender old woman bade God bless him, Alice could stand quiet no
     longer. I knew it, though she had not a word to say.
     <pb n="126"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XV.</head>
    <p><hi>This</hi> time of anxiety was one which, in that great common interest and grief, drew
     many people together who had little sympathy with each other in ordinary times. Many a close,
     private, confidential talk, deluged with tears, or tremulous with hope, I had within these days
     with many a troubled woman, who up to that time had been only an acquaintance, or very slightly
     known to me, but who was now ready, at the touch of this magical sympathy, to take me into her
     heart. Derwent’s custom of riding to the railway for the earliest perusable news, and an
     occasional message by telegraph, which came to him when any important intelligence arrived,
     made our house besieged by anxious people, to whom the greatest joy of their lives was to find
     no mention in these breathless dispatches of the individual or the place in which they were
     interested. Nugents, whom I had never heard of, started up everywhere, asking from me
     information about Bertie and his family. The girls who
     <pb n="127"/> had been brought up at Estcourt deluged me with letters asking after him. I am
     not sure that our entire household did not feel, amid all its anxiety, a little pride in the
     consciousness of thus having a share in the universal national sympathy which was bestowed so
     warmly and freely upon all who had friends in India. As for little Derwie, he devoted himself
     entirely now to the business of carrying news. He knew already by heart the list of all the
     families—I had almost said in all the county, certainly between Hilfont and Simonborough—who
     had soldier-sons; and Derwie and his pony flew along all the country roads for days together
     when news came, the child carrying in his faithful childish memory every detail of the dispatch
     to the cottage women, who had no other means of hearing it. The people about—that is to say,
     Miss Reredos and the important people of the village—called my boy the telegraph-boy, and I am
     not quite sure that I was not rather proud of the name. Whether his news-carrying always did
     good I will not say—perhaps it was little comfort to the mother of a nameless rank-and-file man
     to hear that another battle had been won, or a successful march made, in which, perhaps, God
     knows, that undistinguished boy of hers might have fainted and fallen aside to die. But the
     common people—God bless
     <pb n="128"/> them!—are more hopeful in their laborious hearts than we who have leisure to
     think all our anxieties out, and grow sick over them.</p>
    <p>Derwie flew here and there on his pony, telling the news—possessed with it to the exclusion
     of every other thought—and I could but be thankful that he was a child, and the telegraph-boy,
     not a man, able to set out with a heart of flame to that desperate and furious strife.</p>
    <p>I surprised a nursery party at this memorable period in the expression of their sentiments.
     It was somebody’s birthday at Waterflag, and all the little people were collected there.
     Derwent had been telling them of a feat performed in India by a Flintshire man, which all the
     newspapers had celebrated, and which we were all rather proud of. Derwie, in his capacity of
     newsboy, read the papers to the best of his ability, with very original readings of the Indian
     names, but he was much more thoroughly informed than any of the others—by reason of his
     trade—and they listened to him as to an oracle. Then came an account of the mutiny and all its
     frightful consequences, as well as Derwie knew. The children listened absorbed, the girls
     being, as I rather think is very common, much the most greatly excited. Willie Sedgwick, the
     chubby pink and white heir, who looked so much younger
     <pb n="129"/> than Derwie, sat silent, fingering his buttons, and with no remarkable expression
     in his face; but Miss Polly’s two nieces bent down from their height of superior stature to
     listen, and Clara Sedgwick—lovely little coquette—stood in the middle of the room, arrested in
     something she had been doing, breathless, her little face burning with the strongest childish
     excitement. She was not now arrayed in that glorious apparel which had captivated Derwie and
     myself in the spring. It was only a simple gray morning frock, which was expanded upon her
     infantine crinoline at this moment; but her beautiful little figure, all palpitating with
     wonder, wrath, and excitement, was a sight to see.</p>
    <p>“Oh!” cried out the child, stamping her little foot, as Derwie, breathless himself, paused in
     his tale—“oh! if I had only a gun, I would take hold of papa’s hand and shoot them all!”</p>
    <p>“Ah!” cried Emmy, whose thoughts had been doubtless following the same track, and to whom
     this sudden sense of a want which, perhaps, she scarcely realized in ordinary times, came sharp
     in sudden contrast with that exclamation of Clary’s—“Ah, Clary!” cried the poor child, with a
     shrill accent in the momentary pang it gave her, “but we have no papa.” It struck me like a
     sudden passionate, artless postscript of personal
     <pb n="130"/> grief, striking its key-note upon the big impersonal calamity which raised, even
     in these children’s bosoms, such generous horror and indignation.</p>
    <p>“He was killed in India,” said Di, in a low tone, her womanly little face growing dark with a
     sudden twilight of feeling more serious than her years.</p>
    <p>“They don’t want <hi>us</hi> to fight,” said Derwie, whom this personal digression did not
     withdraw from his main interest; “you may be sure, Clary, they don’t want a little thing like
     you, or me, or Willie; to be sure, if we had been older!—but never mind, there’s sure to be
     somebody to fight with when we’re big enough; and then there’s such famous fellows
     there—there’s Sam Rivers, I was telling you of, that Huntingdonshire man; I know his mother,
     I’ll take you to see her, if you like; and there’s Bertie—there’s our Bertie, don’t you
     know?—he’ll never come home till they’re all safe, or till he’s killed.”</p>
    <p>“If he’s killed he’ll never come back,” said Willie Sedgwick.</p>
    <p>“Oh, I wish you would go away, you horrid great boy!” cried Clary, indignantly—“Killed! when
     you know mamma is so fond of Mrs. Crofton’s Bertie, and loves him as much as Uncle Maurice!—but
     Willie doesn’t care for anything,”
     <pb n="131"/> she said, in an aggrieved tone, turning away from her brother with a disgust
     which I slightly shared.</p>
    <p>“I could bear him to be killed,” said Derwie, who, poor child, had never seen the hero he
     discussed, “if he did something worth while first—like that one, you know, who blew himself up,
     or that one”——</p>
    <p>“But, Derwie, what was the good of blowing himself up,” said Clary, with wondering round
     eyes.</p>
    <p>“Don’t you see?” cried Derwie, impatiently; “why, to destroy the powder and things, to be
     sure, that they might not have it to fire at us.”</p>
    <p>“I’d have poured water all on the powder, if it had been me, and spoiled it without hurting
     any one,” said the prudent Willie.</p>
    <p>“As if he had time to think about hurting any one!” said Derwie—“as if he didn’t just
      <hi>do</hi> it—the first thought that came into his head.”</p>
    <p>“Oh, Derwent!” cried Clary again, “if they were all—every one—ten thousand thousand, standing
     up before one big gun, and papa would only take hold of my hand, I would fire it off!”</p>
    <p>“Aunty says we should forgive,” said Miss Polly’s gentle Di, in a low voice; “’tis dreadful
     to be killed, but it would be worse to kill somebody else.”
     <pb n="132"/></p>
    <p>“I don’t think so at all,” cried Clary, “I would kill them every one if I could—every one
     that did such horrid, cruel, wicked things. I hope Bertie will kill ever so many—hundreds!
     Don’t you hope so, Derwie? I would if I were him.”</p>
    <p>This sanguinary speech was interrupted by an arrival of nurses and attendants, and Clary,
     quite beautiful in her childish fury, went off to make a captivating toilette for the early
     childs’ dinner, where everybody was to appear in gala costume, to do honor to the birthday
     hero. The elder Clara, the child’s mother, had been standing with me in one end of the great
     nursery, listening to this discussion. She turned round with a laugh when the party had
     dispersed.</p>
    <p>“What a little wretch!” said Clara; “but oh! Mrs. Crofton, isn’t it absurd what people say
     about children’s gentleness and sweetness, and all that? I know there is never a story told in
     my nursery of a wicked giant, or a bad uncle, or anything of that sort, but the very baby, if
     he could speak, would give his vote for cutting the villain up in little pieces. There never
     were such cruel imps. They quite shout with satisfaction when that poor innocent giant, who
     never did any harm that I can see, tumbles down the beanstalk and gets killed—though I am sure
     that impudent little thief Jack deserves it a great deal
     <pb n="133"/> more. But what a memory Derwie has!—and how he understands! I am sure, I hope
     most sincerely that Bertie, after all, will get safe home. Is there any more news?”</p>
    <p>“No more,” said I, “I have not heard from himself a long time now—and the public news only
     keeps us anxious. I am not quite so philosophical as Derwie—few things would make me so
     thankful as to hear that Bertie was on his way home.”</p>
    <p>“Oh, I should be so glad!” said Clara, eagerly; then, after a pause and with a smile, “young
     men who want their friends to get dreadfully interested about them should all go out—don’t you
     think, Mrs. Crofton? There is Alice, for example. I thought everything was coming round quite
     nicely, and that Alice was going to be quite rational, and <hi>settle</hi> like other people,
     at last—but just when everything seemed in such excellent train, lo! here came this Indian
     business, and upset the whole again.”</p>
    <p>“Upset what? I don’t understand what you mean,” said I, with a little wonder, partly affected
     and partly real.</p>
    <p>“Oh, Mrs. Crofton! you <hi>do</hi>,” cried Clara; “you know mamma and I had just been making
     up our minds that Mr. Reredos was <hi>the</hi> person, and that all was to be quite pleasant
     and comfortable. He was <hi>so</hi> attentive, and Alice really
     <pb n="134"/> so much better behaved than she had ever been before. Then this Indian business,
     you know, happened, and she was all in a craze again. She doesn’t say much, but I am quite sure
     it is nothing else that has upset her. Of course, looking at it in a rational way, Bertie and
     Alice can’t <hi>really</hi> be anything to each other. But he’s far away, and he’s in danger,
     and there’s quite an air of romance about him. And Alice is so ridiculous! I am quite sure in
     my own mind that this is the only reason why she’s so very cool to the Rector again.”</p>
    <p>“It is very injudicious to say so, Clara,” said I; “of course she must be interested—her old
     playfellow—like a brother to you both; but as for interposing between her and an
     eligible”——</p>
    <p>“Now, please don’t be rational,” pleaded Clara, “I know exactly what you are going to say—but
     after all she must marry somebody, you know, and where is the harm of an eligible
     establishment? Perhaps it would be as well if mamma did not use the word—but still!—oh! to be
     sure, dear, good, kind Bertie—the children are quite right,” said Clara, with a sweet suffusion
     of kindness and good feeling over all her face—“I am sure I love him every bit as much as I
     love Maurice—he was always like a brother, the dear fellow! I don’t say Alice should not be
     interested in him; but only it’s all her romance,
     <pb n="135"/> you know. She’s not in love with him—if she were in love with him, I couldn’t say
     a word—it’s only sympathy, and friendship, and sisterhood, and all that; and because he’s in
     trouble she’ll forget all about herself, and send this good man, who is very fond of her,
     away.”</p>
    <p>“These young ladies, you see, Clara,” said I, “they are not at all to be depended on; they
     never will attend to what we experienced people say.”</p>
    <p>“Ah, yes, that is true,” said Alice’s younger sister, with a sigh of serious acquiescence,
     and the simplest good faith.</p>
    <p>Clara, with her five babies, had forgotten that she was not her sister’s senior—while Alice,
     for her part, looking down from her quiet observatory in her brown silk dress upon Clara’s
     wonderful toilettes and blooming beauty, felt herself a whole century older than that pretty
     matron-sister, who was always so sweetly occupied with life, and had so little time for
     thought. I smiled upon them both, being near twenty years their senior, and thought them a
     couple of children still. So we all go on, thinking ourself the wisest always. In these days I
     began to moralize a little. I have no doubt Miss Polly had similar thoughts of me.
     <pb n="136"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XVI.</head>
    <p><hi>That</hi> evening I had the satisfaction (or dissatisfaction) of beholding a very similar
     condition of things to that which had occupied my attention in my own house at Easter. All the
     Harleys were at Waterflag, in honor of Willie’s birthday, including the pretty little Kate,
     whose first party this was, and—a more perplexing addition—their mother. Mrs. Harley was
     exactly what she had always been, but age had made her uncertain mind more uncertain, while it
     increased her anxiety to have her children “provided for,” as she called it. The colder Alice
     was to Mr. Reredos, the more warmly and tenderly her mother conciliated and courted him. Here
     was a good match, which might be lost for a caprice, one might have supposed the good woman to
     be thinking; and it was her duty to prevent that consummation, if possible. Mrs. Harley quite
     gave herself up to the task of soothing down the temper which Alice had ruffled, and whispering
     perseverance to the discouraged
     <pb n="137"/> suitor. She referred to him on all occasions, thrust his opinions into anything
     that was going forward, contrived means of bringing him into immediate contact with Alice,
     which last brought many a little sting and slight to the unfortunate and too well-befriended
     lover—on the whole, conducted herself as a nervous, anxious, well-meaning woman, to whom
     Providence has not given the gift of comprehending other people’s individualities, might be
     supposed likely to do. As Mrs. Harley sat in her great chair by the fire in the Waterflag
     drawing-room, and looked round her upon her children and descendants, I did not wonder that she
     was both proud and anxious. There was Maurice with a new world of troublous thoughts in his
     face. I could no more understand what was their cause than I could interfere with them. Was it
     that dread following out of his investigations into Truth, wherever she might lead him, which
     he had contemplated with tragical but complacent placidity six months since—or had other
     troubles, more material, overtaken the Fellow of Exeter? I was somewhat curious, but how could
     I hope to know? Then there was Johnnie, poor, happy, deluded boy! Miss Reredos was of the
     company—and while she still saw nobody else who was more likely game, she amused herself with
     <pb n="138"/> Johnnie, and overwhelmed his simple soul with joy. His book and his love together
     had changed him much, poor fellow; he was sadly impatient of being spoken to as a youth, or
     almost as a child, in the old sympathetic, tender custom which all his family had fallen into.
     He was jealous of being distinguished in any way from other people, and took the indulgences
     long accorded to his ill-health and helplessness fiercely, as if they had been so many insults.
     Poor Johnnie! he thought himself quite lifted above the old warm family affection, which clung
     so close to the weakest of the flock, by this new imaginary love of his. I wonder what that
     syren of his imagination felt when she saw what she had done! I imagine nothing but amusement,
     and a little pleasurable thrill of vanity. Many men made love to Miss Reredos, or had done so
     during the past career of that experienced young lady; few perhaps had thrown themselves at her
     feet <hi>tout entier</hi>, like our poor cripple Johnnie. She felt the flattery, though she
     cared little about the victim. I believe, while she foresaw quite coolly the misery she was
     bringing on the boy, she yet had and would retain a certain grateful memory of him all her
     life.</p>
    <p>But it appeared that she had either tired of Maurice, or recognized as impracticable her flirtation
     <pb n="139"/> with that accomplished young gentleman. They were on somewhat spiteful terms,
     having a little passing encounter of pique on the one side and anger on the other, whenever
     they chanced to come in contact. The pique was on the lady’s side; but as for Maurice, he
     looked as if it would have been a decided relief to his feelings to do her some small personal
     injury. There was a kind of snarl in his voice when he addressed her, such as I have heard men
     use to a woman who had somehow injured them, and whom they supposed to have taken a mean
     advantage of her woman’s exemption from accountability. “If you were a man I could punish you;
     but you are not a man, and I have to be polite to you, you cowardly female creature,” said the
     tone, but not the words of Maurice’s voice; and I could discover by that tone that something
     new must have happened which I did not know of. All the more fervently for the coolness of his
     mother and sisters to her, and for the constraint and gloomy looks of Maurice, did Johnnie,
     poor boy, hang upon the words and watch the looks of the enchantress—he saw nobody else in the
     room, cared for nobody else—was entirely carried beyond all other affections, beyond gratitude,
     beyond every sentiment but that of the exalted boyish passion which had, to
     <pb n="140"/> his own consciousness, changed all his life and thoughts.</p>
    <p>And there, on the other hand, was Alice, thwarting all the wishes and inclinations of her
     friends. Mrs. Harley forgave Johnnie, and turned all her wrath for his foolishness upon Miss
     Reredos; but she did not forgive Alice for those cold and brief answers, that unapproachable
     aspect which daunted the Rector, comfortable and satisfactory as was his opinion of himself. I
     could not help looking at these young people with a passing wonder in my mind over the strange
     caprices and cross-purposes of their period of life. Maurice, for instance—what was it that had
     set Maurice all astray from his comfortable self-complacency and <hi>dilettante</hi> leisure?
     Somehow the pleasure-boat of his life had got among the rocks, and nothing but
     dissatisfaction—extreme, utter, unmitigated dissatisfaction—was left to the young man, as I
     could perceive, of all his accomplishments and perfections. Alice was thrusting ordinary life
     away from her—thrusting aside love, and independence, and “an eligible establishment,” trying
     to persuade herself that there were other pursuits more dignified than the common life of
     woman—for—a caprice, Clara said. Johnnie, poor Johnnie, was happy in the merest folly of
     self-deception that ever innocent
     <pb n="141"/> boy practised. Alas! and that was but the threshold of hard, sober existence, and
     who could tell what bitter things were yet in store for them? How hard is life! Perhaps Bertie
     Nugent at that moment lay stark upon some Eastern field of battle; perhaps he was pledging his
     heart and life to some of those languid-lively Indian Englishwomen, ever so many thousand miles
     off—who can tell? And why, because Bertie was in danger, should Alice Harley snub that
     excellent young Rector, and turn from his attentions with such an air of impatience, almost of
     disgust? Nobody could answer me these simple questions. Indeed, to tell the truth, I did not
     ask anybody, but quietly pursued the elucidation of them for myself.</p>
    <p>And of course our conversation during the course of the evening ran upon matters connected
     with India and the last news. Derwent and Mr. Sedgwick held grave consultations on the
     political aspect of the matter and the future government of India. Miss Reredos shuddered, and
     put on pretty looks of earnest attention; Clara told the story of the conversation in the
     nursery; while, in the mean time, Alice expressed her interest neither by look nor word—only
     betrayed it by sitting stock-still, taking no part in the conversation, and restraining more
     than was natural
     <pb n="142"/> every appearance of feeling. That silence would have been enough, if there had
     been nothing else, to betray her to me.</p>
    <p>But I confess I was surprised to hear the eager part which Maurice took in the conversation,
     and the heat and earnestness with which he spoke.</p>
    <p>“If there is one man on earth whom I envy it is Bertie Nugent,” said Maurice, when Clara had
     ended her nursery story. “I remember him well enough, and I know the interest Mrs. Crofton
     takes in him. You need not make faces at me, Clara—I don’t think he’s very brilliant, and
     neither, I daresay, does Mrs. Crofton; but he’s in his proper place.”</p>
    <p>“Maurice, my dear, the place Providence appoints to us is always our proper place,” said Mrs.
     Harley, with the true professional spirit of a clergyman’s wife.</p>
    <p>“Oh! just so, mother,” said the Fellow of Exeter, with a momentary return of his old, superb,
     superior smile, “only, you know, one differs in opinion with Providence now and then. Bertie
     Nugent, however, has no doubt about it, I am certain. I envy him,” added the young man, with a
     certain glance at me, as if he expected me to appreciate the change in his sentiments, and to
     feel rather complimented that my poor Bertie
     <pb n="143"/> was promoted to the envy of so exalted a personage.</p>
    <p>“I thought Mr. Maurice Harley despised soldiers,” said Miss Reredos, dropping her words
     slowly out of her mouth, as if with a pleasant consciousness that they contained a sting.</p>
    <p>“On the contrary, I think soldiering the only natural profession to which we are born,” said
     Maurice, starting with an angry flush, and all but rudeness of tone.</p>
    <p>“Don’t say so, please, before the children,” cried Clara. “War’s disgusting. For one thing,
     nobody can talk of anything else when it’s going on. And then only think what shoals of poor
     men it carries away, never to bring them back again. Ah, poor Bertie!” cried Clara, with a
     little feeling, “I wish the war were over, and he was safe home.”</p>
    <p>“I am not sure that war is not the most wholesome of standing institutions,” said Maurice,
     philosophically. “Your shoals of poor men who go away, and never return, don’t matter much to
     general humanity. There were more went off in the Irish exodus than we shall lose in India. We
     can afford to lose a little blood.”</p>
    <p>“Oh, yes, and sometimes it takes troublesome people out of the way,” said the Rector’s
     sister—“one should not forget that.”
     <pb n="144"/></p>
    <p>“Extremely true, and very philosophical, for a woman,” said Maurice, with a savage look. “It
     drains the surplus population off, and makes room for those who remain.”</p>
    <p>Clara and her mother, both of them, rushed into the conversation with the same breath as
     women rush to separate combatants. I should have been very much surprised had I been more
     deeply interested. But at present I was occupied with that imperturbable, uninterfering
     quietness with which Alice sat at the table, saying nothing;—how elaborately unconscious and
     unconcerned she looked!—that was much more important to me than any squabble between Maurice
     and the Rector’s sister—or than the Rector himself, or any one of the many and various
     individual concerns which, like the different threads of a web, were woven into the quiet
     household circle—giving a deep dramatic interest to the well-bred, unpicturesque pose of the
     little company in that quiet English room.
     <pb n="145"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XVII.</head>
    <p><hi>We</hi> stayed all that night at Waterflag, as we always did when we dined with the
     Sedgwicks, and of course I was subjected to a long private and confidential conversation with
     Mrs. Harley in my dressing-room, when we both ought to have been at rest. She poured out her
     anxieties upon me as she had done many a long year ago, when all these young people were
     unconscious little children, and Dr. Harley, poor good man, was newly dead. Only Time had
     changed both of us since then—she had become an old woman with silver-white hair under her
     snowy cap. I was old too, though my boy was but a child, and kept me nearer to youth than
     belonged to my years; but Mrs. Harley was as glad of this outlet to her anxieties, and felt as
     much relief in pouring these anxieties forth upon somebody else’s shoulders as ever.</p>
    <p>“Ah, Clare!” she said, “you have only one, to be sure, and he’s nobly provided for; but we’re
     never so happy, though we don’t think it,
     <pb n="146"/> as when they’re all children. There’s nothing but measles and such things to
     frighten one <hi>then</hi>—but <hi>now</hi>!—dear, dear! the charge of all these grown up young
     people, Clare, is far too much for a poor woman like me. I believe I shall break down all at
     once, one of these days.”</p>
    <p>“Let us take it quietly,” said I, “they are very good, sensible, well-educated young
     people—they know what they are doing—don’t you think you might trust them to act for
     themselves?”</p>
    <p>“They will, whether I trust them or not,” sighed poor Mrs. Harley. “Ah dear! to think how one
     toils and denies one’s self for one’s family, and how little account they make of one’s wishes
     when all is done! I think mine have quite set themselves—all but Clara, dear girl, who is so
     perfectly satisfactory in every way—to thwart and cross me, Alice—you know how unreasonable she
     is—I can do nothing with her. Just the thing of all others that I could have chosen for her,
     and such a nice, excellent, judicious young man. You saw how she behaved to him to-night.”</p>
    <p>“But really, Mrs. Harley, if Alice doesn’t like him”—I interposed with humility.</p>
    <p>“Oh, nonsense—she does like him—at least, she doesn’t like anybody else that I know of—
     <pb n="147"/>and why shouldn’t she like him?” asked the exasperated mother. “You know, Mrs.
     Crofton, that my poor income dies with me—and there is Johnnie, poor child, to make some
     provision for, and when I die what will she do?—though to be sure,” concluded Mrs. Harley,
     drawing herself up a little, “I am not the sort of person to marry my daughters merely for an
     establishment—that never was my way. This case, you must perceive, Clare, is quite different.
     He is such a very nice—such an entirely satisfactory person; and the position—I was a
     clergyman’s wife myself, and I would choose that sphere rather than any other for Alice; and as
     for liking, I really cannot see a single reason why she should not like him, do you?”</p>
    <p>“Why, no—except just, perhaps, that—I fear—she doesn’t,” said I, with hesitation; for I
     confess this superlative mother’s argument quite nonplused me. After all, why shouldn’t she
     like that good, young, handsome Rector? I reserved the question for private consideration, but
     was a little staggered by the strength of Mrs. Harley’s case.</p>
    <p>“My opinion is that Alice thinks it rather a merit to refuse an eligible person,” said Mrs.
     Harley—“like all these young people. There is Maurice, too—you will not believe it, Clare—
     <pb n="148"/>but Maurice has actually had the folly to fall in love with Francis Owen’s sister
     in Simonborough. I could not believe my ears when I heard of it first. Maurice, who has always
     been such a very prudent boy! She is a very nice, pretty girl, but, of course has not a
     penny—and Maurice has nothing but his fellowship. It is a pretty mess altogether. In the very
     best view of the case, if Maurice even had been content to think like other people, and had a
     nice living waiting for him, they might both have done better—<hi>he</hi> might have done a
      <hi>great</hi> deal better at least. But, no!—when they find somebody quite unsuitable, that
     is the very thing to please young people in these days; and there is my son, Clare—my eldest
     son—who was never intended for any profession but the Church—actually broaching all kinds of
     wild schemes about work, and talking of going to Australia, or taking a laborer’s hod, or any
     other wild thing he can think of; it is enough to break my heart!”</p>
    <p>“Then do you mean that Maurice intends to throw up his fellowship, and marry?” said I,
     thinking this too good news to be true.</p>
    <p>Mrs. Harley shook her head.</p>
    <p>“It is all a muddle,” she said, “there is no satisfaction at all in it; she thought he
     flirted with Miss Reredos, and he thought she flirted with
     <pb n="149"/> some of the officers; and Miss Reredos has such a grudge at him for falling in
     love with anybody but herself, that she did all she could to help them to a quarrel; and a very
     good thing, too, for of course they never would have been so mad as to marry, and I dislike
     long engagements exceedingly; only since then it is really almost impossible to endure Maurice
     in the house. He is <hi>so</hi> ill-tempered, it is really quite dreadful. I am sure, when I
     was young, I never gave my parents any uneasiness about me, yet my two eldest children seem to
     think it quite an amusement to worry me out of my life.”</p>
    <p>“Let us believe they don’t do it on purpose,” said I; “troubles never come single, you
     know—and I daresay this is the most critical time of their life.”</p>
    <p>“Ah, Alice should have had all these affairs over long ago!” said Mrs. Harley,
     disapprovingly; “Alice is seven and twenty, Mrs. Crofton—she ought to have been settled in life
     years ago. I am sure, considering all the opportunities she has had, it is quite disgraceful. I
     can’t help feeling that people—her father’s friends, for instance—will blame me.”</p>
    <p>I found it difficult not to smile at this refinement of maternal anxiety, but after a while
     succeeded in soothing the good mother, whose mind
     <pb n="150"/> was evidently eased by the utterance, and persuading her that everything would
     come right. She went away shaking her head, but smiling through her anxious looks. She laid
     down her burden at my door, and left it there. When she had gone I took up my portion of it
     with sundry compunctions. Bertie Nugent had been seven years away—when he went away Alice was
     scarcely twenty. They had of course been very much in each other’s society before this, but
     seven years is a long break, even for lovers. These two were not lovers; and was not Clara
     right when she stigmatized as the merest foolish romance any interest which Alice might have in
     her long-departed and indifferent playfellow? I began to blame myself for cherishing in my own
     mind the lingering hope that my wishes might still be accomplished concerning them. Perhaps
     that hope had, by some subtle means, betrayed itself to Alice, and had helped to strengthen her
     in her natural perversity and the romance of that vague visionary link which existed only in
     her mind and mine. I have known very similar cases more than once in my life—cases in which a
     childish liking, kept up only by chance inquiries or friendly messages at long intervals on one
     side or the other, has forestalled the imagination of the two subjects of it so completely,
     <pb n="151"/> that both have kept from all engagements for years, until at long and last,
     encountering each other once again, they have discovered themselves to have loved each other
     all this time, and married out of hand. This vague sort of tie, which is no tie, has a more
     captivating hold upon the mind than a real engagement; but then it might come to nothing. And
     after an interval of seven years, was it not everybody’s duty to turn the dreamer away from
     that romantic distance to the real ground close at hand? I had considered the question many
     times with too strong a regard for Bertie (who, to be sure, had no particular solicitude about
     the matter, or he might have been home long ago) in my thoughts. Now I rather changed my point
     of view. If Alice liked Bertie, it was purely a love of the imagination. Why, for that
     Will-o’-the-wisp, was she to keep dreaming in the twilight while the broad daylight of life and
     all its active duties were gliding out of her reach? I resolved to bestir myself and startle
     Alice into common sense and ordinary prudence. Here was she, letting youth pass her, not
     perceiving how it went, looking so far away out of her horizon to that fantastic, unreal
     attraction at the other end of the world. Thinking over it I grew more and more dissatisfied.
     She was wrong to entertain,
     <pb n="152"/> I was wrong to encourage, so uncomfortable a piece of self-delusion. It is true,
     Bertie was in danger, and surrounded with a flush of interest and anxiety which doubled his
     claims on everybody who knew him. Still it must not be permitted to continue—she must be roused
     out of this vain imaginary attachment which blinded her to the love that sought her close at
     hand. Why did she not like the Rector? I resolved to be at the bottom of that question, which I
     could not answer, before twenty-four hours were out.
     <pb n="153"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XVIII.</head>
    <p><hi>But</hi> who can tell what is to happen within twenty-four hours? When I left my
     dressing-room next morning, I found Derwent lingering in the corridor outside, waiting for me.
     He carried in his hand one of those ominous covers which thrill the hearts of private people
     with fears of evil tidings. He had been half afraid to bring it into me, but he did not hide
     either the startling hieroglyphics which proclaimed the nature of the dispatch, nor his own
     distressed and sorrowful face.</p>
    <p>“What is the matter?” I cried, in breathless alarm, when I saw him; “something has
     happened!”</p>
    <p>“I fear so,” said Derwent; “but softly—softly, Clare; in the first place it is not absolutely
     his name and there are such perpetual mistakes by this confounded telegraph. Softly, softly,
     Clare.”</p>
    <p>I had seized the dispatch while he was speaking—I read it without saying a word—did I not
     know how it would be?—ah, that concise, dreadful,
     <pb n="154"/> murderous word—killed! I knew it the moment I saw Derwent’s face.</p>
    <p>“But, my love, it is not his name—look! it absolutely may be somebody else and not Bertie,”
     cried my husband.</p>
    <p>Ah, Bertie! the sound of his dear, pleasant, homely name overcame me. There was no longer any
     Bertie in the world! I had borne the dreadful excitement of reading the dispatch, but I lost my
     self-command entirely when all the world of love and hope that had lived in him came before me
     in his name—it went to my heart.</p>
    <p>Long after, Derwent returned to point out the possibilities, which I had no heart to find
     out. I heard him languidly—I had made up my mind at once to the worst. One hopes least when
     one’s heart is most deeply concerned; but still my mind roused to catch at the straw, such as
     it was. The telegraph reported that it was Captain N. Hugent who was killed. It was a very
     slight travesty to rest any confidence upon; but then Bertie was Lieutenant-Colonel, lately
     breveted. I refused to listen for a long time; but at last the hope caught hold of me. Derwent
     recalled to my recollection so many other errors—even in this very dispatch the name of one
     place was quite unrecognizable. When I did receive
     <pb n="155"/> the idea into my head, I started up, crying for an Army List. Why did they not
     have one in Waterflag? It was afternoon then, and the day had gone past like a ghost, without a
     thought of our return home, or of anything but this dismal piece of news. Now I put my bonnet
     on hurriedly, and begged Derwent to get the carriage. We had a list at home. We could see if
     there was anybody else whose name might be mistaken for our dear boy’s.</p>
    <p>A pale afternoon—a ghostly half twilight of clouds and autumn obscurity. I went into Clara’s
     favorite sitting-room, where she was by herself, to bid her good-bye, unable to bear the sight
     of the whole family, especially of Mrs. Harley, and the sympathy, sincere though it was, which
     she would give me. That miserable morsel of hope, which I did not believe in, yet trusted to,
     in spite of myself, raised to a fever my grief and distress. The deepest calamity, which is
     certain, and not to be doubted, is so far better than suspense, that it has not the burning
     agitation of anxiety to augment its pangs. I went into Clara’s room with the noiseless step of
     a ghost, impelled by I cannot tell what impulse of swiftness and silence. Clara was crying
     abundantly for her old playfellow. Alice, as I did not observe at the time, but remembered
     afterwards, was not
     <pb n="156"/> to be seen that day, and never came to whisper a word of consolation to me, nor
     even to bid me good-bye. I put my veil aside for a moment to kiss Clara. “Oh, Mrs. Crofton! it
     will turn out to be somebody else!” cried Clara, with her unreasoning impulse of consolation. I
     wrung the little hand she put into mine and hurried away. Ah! God help us! if it was not Bertie
     it must be somebody else—if we were exempted, other hearts must break. Oh, heavy life! oh,
     death inexorable! some one must bear this blow, whether another household or our own.</p>
    <p>We hurried back to Hilfont, all very silent, little Derwie leaning back in his corner of the
     carriage, his eyes ablaze, and not a tear in them; the child was in the highest excitement, but
     not for Bertie’s life—panting to know, not that the cousin whom he had never seen was saved,
     but that something noble and great had been done by this hero of his childish imagination. As
     for my husband, I knew it was only in consideration of my weakness that he had remained all day
     inactive. I saw him look at his watch, and lean out to speak to the coachman. I knew that he
     would continue his journey to town as fast as steam could carry him. I felt certain Derwent
     could not rest without certain news.</p>
    <p>When we reached home, I hastened at once, in
     <pb n="157"/> advance of them all, to the library, where I knew that Army List was. I remember
     still how I threw the books out of my way till I found it, and how, with a haste which defeated
     its own object, I ruffled over the leaves with my trembling hands. I found nothing like
     Bertie’s name—nothing that could be changed into that Captain N. Hugent in all his regiment. I
     threw the book away from me and sunk upon a chair, faint and giddy. My hopes had grown as I
     approached to the point of resolving them; now they forsook me in a moment. Why should I
     quarrel with that inevitable fate? Why should we be exempted, and no other? Long and peaceful
     had been this interregnum. Years had passed since grief touched us—now it was over, and the age
     of sorrow had begun again.</p>
    <p>“I have only a minute to spare,” said Derwent, looking over the list himself, with a grave
     and unsatisfied face; “of course I must go to town immediately, Clare, and see if any more
     information is to be had. But look here! it is not so much the mistake of name as of rank which
     weighs with me; military people, you know, are rigid in that respect. Had it been Colonel, I
     should not have questioned the transposing of the initials; but see! he is registered as Major
     even here.”
     <pb n="158"/></p>
    <p>“Don’t say anything, Derwent,” said I; “let me make up my mind to it. Why should not we have
     our share of suffering as well as so many others? Do not try to soothe me with a hope which you
     don’t feel.”</p>
    <p>“My dear, if I were not so anxious, I should be sure of it,” said Derwent. “I am very hopeful
     even now. And, Clare,” said my husband, stopping sorrowfully to look at me, “grieved as we are,
     think, at the most, it might have been worse still—it might have been your own son.”</p>
    <p>I turned my head away for the moment, with something of an added pang. My boy Bertie!—he was
     not my son—he did not even look so very, very much younger than I, now-a-days, as he had been
     used to do; yet he was my boy, kindred in blood and close in heart. Little Derwent stood by,
     listening up to this moment in silence. Now he spoke.</p>
    <p>“Mamma, are you sorry?” cried the child; “our Bertie would not die for nothing, if he did
     die. Is it for Bertie, because he’s been a brave soldier that you cry? Then how will you do,
     mamma, when <hi>I’m</hi> a man?”</p>
    <p>How should I do? I clasped my son close in my arms and wept aloud. His father went away from
     us with a trembling lip, and tears in
     <pb n="159"/> his eyes. My heart groaned and exulted over the child, who felt himself a knight
     and champion born. Ah! what should I do when he was a man? What would every one do who loved
     Derwie, if death and danger came in the way of <hi>his</hi> duty? But some such men bear
     charmed lives.</p>
    <p>Derwent went away that day to do all that was possible towards ascertaining the truth. We
     were left alone in the house, Derwie and I. My boy kept by me all day, unfolding to me the
     stores of his wonderful childish information—what in my pride and admiration I had been used to
     call Derwie’s gossip. He did not console, nor suggest consolation; but the heart swelled in his
     child’s bosom to think of some great thing which he had yet to hear of, that Bertie had done.
     He was entirely possessed with that idea; and by-and-by his enthusiasm breathed itself into his
     mother also. I began to bear myself proudly in the depths of my grief. “Another for England!” I
     said in my heart: Ah! more than for England, for humanity, nature, our very race and blood. If
     Bertie had died to deliver the helpless from yonder torturing demons, could we grudge his life
     for that cause? So I tried to stifle down my fond hopes for my chosen heir—to put Alice Harley
     and Estcourt aside out of my mind, that nothing might come between me and our dearest young
     hero. He
     <pb n="160"/> was killed. That murderous chariot of war had gone over him, and extinguished
     those fair and tender prospects out of this world; but not the praise nor the love, which
     should last for ever.</p>
    <p>So I thought, waiting for further tidings, persuading myself that I had no other expectation
     than to hear that fatal dispatch confirmed—yet cherishing I cannot tell what unspoken,
     unpermitted secret hopes at the bottom of my heart.</p>
    <p>Some days of extreme suspense ensued. Derwent found no satisfaction in London; but remained
     there in order to get the first news that came. Heavily those blank hours of uncertainty went
     over us. Lady Greenfield came to Hilfont, and she and I grew friends, as we mingled our
     tears—friends for the first time. All my other neighbors distressed me with inquiries or
     condolences. Some wondered I went to church on the next Sunday, and was not in mourning. Nobody
     would let me alone in my anxiety and grief. I had a visit almost every day from Clara Sedgwick,
     who came in crying, as if that would console me, and hung upon my neck. I was far too deeply
     excited to take any comfort out of Clara’s caresses; perhaps, if truth must be told, I was a
     little bored with demonstrations of affection, to which, uneasy and miserable as I was, I could
     make so little response.</p>
    <p>Then came the day for news—the dread day,
     <pb n="161"/> when all secret hopes which might be lurking in our hearts were to receive
     confirmation or destruction, the last being so very much the most probable. I felt assured that
     if the news was favorable, Derwent would return that day, and waited with a beating heart for
     the dispatch, which I knew he would not delay a moment in sending me. The news came—alas! such
     unhappy no-news! The same perplexing, murderous information, simply repeated without a single
     clue to the mistake, whatever it was. I sank down in my chair, with an overpowering sickness at
     my heart while I read—sickness of depressed hope, of disappointment of a conviction and
     certainty which crushed me. The repetition somehow weighed heavily with my imagination. I could
     no longer either deny or doubt the truth of it. It was all over. There was no more Bertie
     Nugent of Estcourt now to maintain the name of my fathers; so many hopes and dreams were ended,
     and such a noble, fresh young life, full of all good and generous impulses, was finished for
     ever.</p>
    <p>“I fear—I fear, Derwie, my darling—I fear it must be true,” said I.</p>
    <p>“But what did he do? Bertie did not die for nothing, mamma—is it not in the paper what he
      <hi>did</hi>?” cried Derwie.
     <pb n="162"/></p>
    <p>If it had been, perhaps one could have borne it better. If he had died relieving a distressed
     garrison, or freeing a band of agonized fugitives, and we had known that he did so,
     perhaps—perhaps—it might have been easier to bear. I sat down listlessly in the great window of
     the breakfast-room. Something of the maze of grief came over me. If I had seen him coming
     through the avenue yonder, crossing the lawn, approaching to me with his pleasant smile, I
     should not have wondered. Death had separated Bertie from the limits of place and country—he
     was mysteriously near, though what remained of him might be thousands of miles away.</p>
    <p>Thus I sat languidly looking out, and saying over in my heart those verses which everybody
     must remember who has ever been in great trouble—those verses of <hi>In Memoriam</hi>, in which
     the poet sees the ship come home with its solemn, silent passenger, and yet feels that if along
     with the other travellers he saw the dead man step forth—</p>
    <quote>
     <l>“And strike a sudden hand in mine,</l>
     <l>  And ask a thousand things of home;—</l>
     <l>“And I should tell him all my pain,</l>
     <l>And how my life had drooped of late,</l>
     <l>And he should sorrow o’er my state,</l>
     <l>And marvel what possessed my brain;
      <pb n="163"/></l>
     <l>“And I perceived no touch of change,</l>
     <l>No hint of death in all his frame,</l>
     <l>But found him all in all the same,</l>
     <l>I should not feel it to be strange.”</l>
    </quote>
    <p>Wonderful subtle intuition of the poetic soul! Who does not know that strange contrast of
     death and life? A week ago, and had I seen Bertie from that window, I should have hailed his
     appearance with the wildest amazement. But I should neither have wondered nor faltered had I
     seen him this day; on the contrary, would have felt in my heart that it was natural and fit he
     should be there.</p>
    <p>But I did not see Bertie. I saw far off a homely country gig driving up rapidly towards the
     house, and strained my eyes, wondering if it could be Derwent, though he had sent me no
     intimation of his return. As it came closer, however, I saw that one of the figures it
     contained was a woman’s, and at last perceived that my visitors were no other than Alice Harley
     and her brother Maurice. I started nervously up, and hid away my dispatch, for I trembled to
     see my dear girl. What had she to do coming here?—she who could not ask after his fate with
     calmness, and yet to the bottom of her maiden heart felt that she had <hi>no right</hi> to be
     concerned.</p>
    <p>Alice was very pale—I could see the nervous
     <pb n="164"/> trembling over her whole frame, which she subdued painfully, and with a nervous
     force, as she came in. Though her voice would scarcely serve her to say the words, she made an
     explanation before she asked if I had any news. “My mother sent me,” said Alice, with bare
     childish simplicity, but with that breathless gasp in her voice which I knew so well—gasp of
     utter despair at the thought of enduring that suspense, and concealing it for five minutes
     longer—“to know if you had any further news—if you had heard,” she added, with a convulsive
     calmness, casting at me a fiery glance, defiant of the compassion she saw in my face. I saw she
     meant to say his name, to show me how firm she was, but nature was too much for Alice—she
     concluded hurriedly in the baldest, briefest words—“anything more?”</p>
    <p>I shook my head, and she sank into the nearest seat—not fainting—people do not faint at such
     moments—kept alive and conscious by a burning force of pain.</p>
    <p>“Only the same miserable news over again,” said I, “with the same mistake in the name;
     letters must come, I fear, before we can know—but I am afraid to hope.”</p>
    <p>A little convulsive sound came from Alice’s breast—she heard it herself, and drew herself up
     <pb n="165"/> after it to hide the wound still if she could. Maurice, too, was greatly
     affected, though he could scarcely be said to have known Bertie; he walked about the room in
     his careless man’s way, doing everything in the world without intending it, to make that
     composure we two women had wound ourselves up to, impossible—making his lamentations as he
     paced about from table to table, picking up all the books to look at them as he went and
     came.</p>
    <p>“Poor Nugent!” said Maurice—“poor honest fellow!—he was not very brilliant, but people liked
     him all the better for that. What a bright frank face he had—what a laugh! I shall never hear
     anybody laugh so heartily again. And to think of a fellow like that, and hundreds more,
     sacrificed to these black demons! Good heavens! and we sitting here at home idling away our
     lives!”</p>
    <p>“Ah, my Bertie!” cried I, out of my heart, “and no one left behind him to bear his
     name—nobody to mourn for him except ourselves—nobody belonging to <hi>him</hi>! If there is one
     thing a man has a right to in life and death, it is surely a woman’s tears.”</p>
    <p>I did not think what I was saying. The words were scarcely out of my lips when an
     overpowering burst of tears broke through all the painful reserve and forced calmness of Alice.
     She covered
     <pb n="166"/> her face with her hands, hid her head, drew her veil frantically over her
     passionate weeping. But the flood would have its way, and she could not stop it. I dried my own
     tears to look on almost with awe at that outburst of controlled and restrained nature. My poor
     Bertie! the last sad right of a man had fallen to him unawares; he had that mournful
     possession, all to himself, poured forth upon the grave of his youth with a fulness that knew
     no reserve—a woman’s tears!</p>
    <p>Maurice stood by overwhelmed with surprise; he looked at his sister—he grew crimson up to his
     hair—he drew back a step as if he felt himself an intruder spying upon this unsuspected grief.
     Then he retired to the bookcase at the other side of the room, with an appealing glance at me.
     I followed him softly, Alice being far too entirely absorbed to observe us for the moment.</p>
    <p>“What does it mean—was there anything between them?” asked Maurice, in my ear.</p>
    <p>“They were playfellows and dear friends,” said I; “you know how Clara feels it too.”</p>
    <p>“Not like <hi>that</hi>,” said Maurice, once more growing red, as he turned to the books in
     the shelves—he stood there absorbed in these books, taking out some to examine them, showing
     himself entirely occupied with this investigation till Alice had recovered her composure. She
     <pb n="167"/> looked up at me with a guilty, pale face when she had wept out her tears; and I
     was comforted that she saw her brother coldly standing in the background with his back to us
     and a book in his hand. I had never been so pleased with Maurice before.</p>
    <p>“You are not well, my dear child,” said I, “I will bring you some wine, and you must rest a
     little. Thank you for remembering him, Alice. Now we can give him nothing but tears.”</p>
    <p>Alice, all pale, miserable, and abashed, gasped forth something of which I could only
     distinguish the words “playfellow” and “old friend.”</p>
    <p>“I was saying so—you were like his sisters, Clara and you,” said I, out loud to reach
     Maurice’s ear.</p>
    <p>Alice looked up in my face, now that she had betrayed herself. I thought she was almost
     jealous that I did not understand her—that I really believed these were, like Clara’s, friendly
     and sisterly tears.</p>
    <p>What could I do? I hushed her, drawing her head to my breast. I could say nothing,—he was
     gone—he could neither learn what love was bestowed upon him nor return it. Words could no
     longer touch that secret matter which was made holy by Bertie’s grave.</p>
    <p>“Look here, Mrs. Crofton,” said Maurice,
     <pb n="168"/> turning round upon me, when he saw I had left Alice’s side, with the Army List in
     his hand; “it is not in Nugent’s regiment, certainly, but the 53d is in India, too—look
     here.”</p>
    <p>I looked with little interest, believing it only a kind expedient to break up the trying
     situation in which we all stood. It was a name which Maurice pointed out, the name entirely
     unknown to me, of Captain Nicolas Hughes.</p>
    <p>“What of it?” said I, almost disposed to think he was making light of our trouble.</p>
    <p>“Captain N. Hughes—Captain N. Hugent—the mistake might be quite explainable; at least,” said
     Maurice, putting up the book, “at least with such a similarity we ought not yet to despair.
     Alice we’ll go home now. I daresay Mrs. Crofton has too many visitors just at present, and my
     mother will be anxious to hear. Dear Mrs. Crofton,” said the young man, in whom I could not
     recognize that Fellow of Exeter, grasping my hand warmly, “don’t despair.”</p>
    <p>And Alice, with a painful blush on her cheeks, and her veil over her face, followed him out
     without a word. I took but faint hope from the suggestion of that name; but if it were
     possible—if still we might hope that Bertie was spared—never would Alice Harley forgive him for
     that outburst of tears.
     <pb n="169"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XIX.</head>
    <p><hi>Derwent</hi> had not yet returned, and I could understand perfectly why he waited, uneasy
     for further news, or at least for some explanation of that which we had already heard. I waited
     also, spending the days sadly, but giving up hope, and consequently in a state of anxiety less
     painful. Sometimes, indeed, Derwie thrust me back into my fever of suspense by his oft-repeated
     wonder that there should be no news yet of that feat of arms which had cost Bertie his life.
     The child could not and would not understand how the bravest may perish by some anonymous
     undistinguished shot, as well as the coward; nor believe that “Bertie had died for nothing,” as
     he said. And sometimes that name which Maurice Harley pointed out to me wavered through my
     memory for hours together, and upset my calm. Captain Nicolas Hughes—who was he? I wondered,
     musing at the window, with still that vague thrilling thought at my heart that it would not
     surprise me to see Bertie
     <pb n="170"/> coming across the lawn. Was he young, perhaps, and had mother and sisters at home
     breaking their hearts with an anxiety kindred to our own—or, harder still, perhaps a wife
     trembling to believe that her children had no father? Alas! alas! who could choose to be
     delivered one’s-self at the cost of another’s heartbreak? God’s will be done, whatever it was!
      <hi>He</hi> knew, though we did not. There was nothing else to say.</p>
    <p>A few days after I had an unexpected, and, I am grieved to say, not very welcome visit from
     Mrs. Harley. I had shunned seeing her hitherto, afraid alike of her condolences over a sorrow
     which I had not consented to, or her weak encouragements of a hope in which I durst not
     believe. Had it been possible to so old a friend, I would have denied myself, when I saw the
     same gig in which Maurice had driven Alice—a convenient rural vehicle belonging to a farmer
     close by her house—driving up once more to Hilfont with Mrs. Harley; but as, in spite of thirty
     years’ close friendship, the good woman would still have set this down as a slight to her
     poverty, I did not venture to refuse her admittance. She came in with her best conventional
     look of sympathy, shook my hand with emphasis, and gave me a slow lingering kiss; did
     <pb n="171"/> all those things by which our friends mark their profound consciousness of our
     sorrow, and readiness to receive our confidence. I, for my part, was disposed to say very
     little on the subject. There was no more news—nothing to say. I was afraid to speculate, or to
     have any speculations upon this, which none of us could elucidate. It was best to leave it in
     silence while we waited—time enough to speak when all was secure.</p>
    <p>Yet when I saw that Mrs. Harley’s sympathy was the merest superficial crust overlaid upon her
     own perennial anxieties, I am not sure that I was pleased. One feels it impossible that one’s
     friends can feel for one fully; yet one is disappointed, notwithstanding, when one perceives
     how entirely occupied they are with the closer current of their own affairs. Mrs. Harley had no
     sooner expressed her feeble affliction over “the sad calamity,” than she forsook that subject
     for a more interesting one; and it was a little grievous to be called upon to adjudicate in
     favor of Alice’s lover, just after I had looked with respect and sympathy on Alice’s tears.</p>
    <p>“My dear Mrs. Crofton, I am sure I would not for the world trouble you with my affairs, when
     you are in such deep affliction,” said Mrs. Harley, doing of course the very thing she
     <pb n="172"/> deprecated; “but I am in such anxiety about Alice; and really Mr. Reredos is so
     very urgent that I no longer know what to say to him. I ventured to give him an intimation, a
     few weeks ago, that Alice was rather inclining towards him, as I thought—and of course the poor
     young man redoubled his attentions; and now, whether it is mere perversity or dislike, or what
     it is, I cannot tell, but from that time Alice has treated him with such indifference, not to
     say disdain, that I am at my wit’s end.”</p>
    <p>“It would have been better to have said nothing to the Rector without Alice’s consent,” said
     I, languidly, yet not without a certain satisfaction in piercing my visitor with this little
     javelin. Mrs. Harley shook her head and wiped her eyes.</p>
    <p>“It is so easy to say so,” said the troubled mother, “so easy to think what is best when
     one’s own heart is not concerned; But if I <hi>was</hi> wrong I cannot help it now—Alice is so
     very unreasonable. She cannot endure the very sight of Mr. Reredos now—it is extremely
     distressing to me.”</p>
    <p>“I am very sorry to hear it, Mrs. Harley, but you know I cannot help you,” said I.</p>
    <p>“Oh! my dear Clare, I beg your pardon a thousand times for troubling you when you have
     <pb n="173"/> such distressing news, but you know quite well you are all-powerful with Alice.
     Then another thing, Clara tells me that dear Bertie—dear fellow!—I am sure I loved him like a
     child of my own—had something to do with her sister’s behavior to the Rector—not that they were
     in love, you know, only some old childish friendship that the dear girl remembered when he was
     in danger. Do you think there is anything in it, Clara? Can that be the reason? but you know of
     course it is quite nonsense. Why, they have not met for eight years!”</p>
    <p>“That proves it must be nonsense, to be sure,” said I; “but excuse me, Mrs. Harley, this dear
     boy who is gone was very dear to me—I cannot mingle his name in any talk about other people. I
     beg your pardon—I can’t indeed.”</p>
    <p>“Dear, dear, it is I who should beg your pardon,” cried Mrs. Harley, in great distress; “I am
     sure I did not mean to be so selfish; but you used to be very fond of Alice, Clare—fonder of
     her than of any one else, though I say it. Long ago you would not have turned off anything that
     was for the poor girl’s good.”</p>
    <p>“You know I am as fond of Alice as ever I was—what do you want me to do?” cried I.</p>
    <p>“Oh, nothing, Clare, dear—nothing but a little good advice,” said Mrs. Harley. “If it
     <pb n="174"/> should happen to be dear Bertie whom she has set her thoughts upon, just because
     he was in danger, as girls will do, and refusing other eligible offers, and throwing away quite
     a satisfactory match and suitable establishment, wouldn’t you speak to her, dear Clare? Her
     dear papa had such confidence in you that you would always be a friend to his girls—he said so
     many a time, long before we knew what was going to happen. You have such influence with all my
     children, Mrs. Crofton—almost more than their mother has. Do represent to Alice how much she’s
     throwing away—and especially, alas! <hi>now</hi>.”</p>
    <p>This emphasis was rather too much for my patience.</p>
    <p>“You forget,” I said, “that Alice is able to judge for herself—she is not a girl now”——</p>
    <p>“She is seven and twenty, Mrs. Crofton—do you mean to reproach her with her age?” said Mrs.
     Harley, with an angry color rising on her face.</p>
    <p>“Reproach her! for what?” said I, constrained to laugh in the midst of my grief. “Why will
     you tease Alice, and yourself, and me? She is very well—she is,” I added, with a little gulp,
     swallowing my better knowledge, “quite contented and happy—why will you torture her into
     marrying? She is quite satisfied to be as she is.”
     <pb n="175"/></p>
    <p>“Ah, Clare—but I have so many children to provide for!” cried poor Mrs. Harley, with a gush
     of tears.</p>
    <p>This silenced me, and I said no more. But Mrs. Harley had not exhausted her budget of
     complaints.</p>
    <p>“And Maurice,” said this unfortunate mother; “after the education he has had, and all the
     money and pains that have been expended on him—Maurice, I do believe, Mrs. Crofton, will do
     something violent one of these days; he will go into business, or,” with another outburst of
     tears, “set himself to learn a trade.”</p>
    <p>“Surely nothing quite so bad as that,” said I, with as much sympathy as I could summon
     up.</p>
    <p>“Ah, you don’t know how he speaks—if you could only hear him; and the troubles in India and
     this last dreadful news have had such an effect upon Maurice,” said Mrs. Harley; “you would
     suppose, to hear him speak, that the poor soldiers had suffered all the more because he was
     doing nothing. Such nonsense! And instead of going into the Church in a proper and dignified
     manner, like his dear father, I see nothing better for it but that he’ll make a tradesman of
     himself.”</p>
    <p>“But it would be satisfactory to see him doing something for himself—improving his own position;
     <pb n="176"/> he can never settle and make a home for himself while he has only his Fellowship.
     Don’t you think Maurice is right?” said I, keeping up the conversation from mere politeness,
     and already sufficiently tired of the interruption it made.</p>
    <p>“He has his mother’s house,” said Mrs. Harley, a little sharply, “and he has the position of
     a gentleman,” she added a moment after, in a faltering, apologetic tone. Good, troubled woman!
     She had come to that age of conflicting interests when the instincts of the heart do not always
     guide true. She wanted—very naturally—to see her daughter provided for; and so, if she could,
     would have persuaded Alice into an unwilling marriage. She could not bear to see her son
     derogating from the “position” which his father’s son ought to fill; and as he would not go
     into the Church, she would fain have condemned the young man to shrivel up into the dreary
     dignity of a College Don. Poor Mrs. Harley!—that was all that the philosophy of the affections
     instructed her to do.</p>
    <p>She had scarcely left me half an hour when I was startled by the appearance of the Rector. He
     was grave and pale, held my hand in his tight grasp, and made his professions of sympathy all
     very properly and in good taste. But his looks and his tone aggravated a sick impatience
     <pb n="177"/> of sympathy which began to grow about my heart. I began to comprehend how people
     in deep and real grief, might grow disgusted with the conventional looks expected from them,
     and learn an almost levity of manner, to forestall those vulgar, dreary sympathies; and this
     sympathy, too, covered something very different—something a great deal nearer to the Rector’s
     heart.</p>
    <p>“It may seem to you a very indelicate question—I beg your pardon, Mrs. Crofton—I ask it with
     great diffidence—but I do not hesitate to confess to you that my own happiness is deeply
     concerned,” said Mr. Reredos, blushing painfully—and I knew at once, and recognized with a
     certain thrill of impatience and disgust, what he was going to ask; “Miss Harley and the late
     Captain Nugent were almost brought up together, I have heard; will you forgive me asking if
     there was any attachment—any engagement between them?”</p>
    <p>“<hi>Colonel</hi> Nugent, please!” said I, I fear rather haughtily; “and it is surely
     premature to say the late, as I trust in Heaven we shall yet have better news.”</p>
    <p>“I beg your pardon,” repeated the Rector, quickly, “I—I was not aware—but might I ask an
     answer to my question?”
     <pb n="178"/></p>
    <p>“If there was any engagement between Alice and my dear Bertie?—none whatever!” cried I, with
     all my might—“nothing of the kind! Pardon me, you have <hi>not</hi> been delicate—you have
      <hi>not</hi> considered my feelings—if Alice has been unfavorable to you, it is for your own
     merits, and not on his account.”</p>
    <p>I was half sorry when I saw the grave, grieved, ashamed expression with which this other
     young man turned away. He bowed and was gone almost before I knew what I had said—I fear not
     without an arrow of mortification and injured pride tingling through the love in his heart.
     <pb n="179"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XX.</head>
    <p><hi>And</hi> after all, the Rector was premature—we were all premature, lamenting for him
     over whom we were so speedily to rejoice. When Derwent put the dispatch into my hand (he did
     not send, but brought it, to make more sure), I could not read the words for tears. My eyes
     were clear enough when I saw that terrible <hi>killed</hi>, in which we believed to read
     Bertie’s fate. But the dear boy’s own message, in rapid reply to one which Derwent, out of my
     knowledge, had managed to have sent to him, floated upon me in a mist of weeping. The truth
     came inarticulate to my mind—I could neither see, nor scarcely hear the words in which it was
     conveyed.</p>
    <p>But, alas! alas! it <hi>was</hi> Captain Nicholas Hughes who had fallen, instead of Bertie. I
     inquired all that I could learn about this unknown soldier, with a remorseful grief in the
     midst of my joy, which I cannot describe. I could not join in the tumult of exultation which
     rose round
     <pb n="180"/> me. I could not forget that this news, which came so welcome to us, brought
     desolation upon another house. I could not think of him but as Bertie’s substitute, nor help a
     painful, fantastical idea that it was to our prayers and our dear boy’s safety that he owed his
     death. I was almost glad to find that the widow whom he had left behind him had need of what
     kind offices we could do her for the bringing up of her children, and vowed to myself, with a
     compunction as deep as it was, no doubt, imaginary, that she should never want while Estcourt
     remained mine. Was it not their dismal loss and bereavement which had saved the heir of my
     father’s house?</p>
    <p>“It is the fortune of war,” said Derwent, when he learned, to his profound amazement, this
     idea which had taken possession of me. “It is the will of God,” said Captain Hughes’s pale
     widow, lifting her tearful face to me, from under the heavy veil of her mourning. So it was—but
     sharp and poignant is the contest between grief and joy.</p>
    <p>“See what your despised telegraph can do, after all!” cried Derwent, rejoicing with all his
     honest heart over the news he had brought.</p>
    <p>“But, ah! if Bertie’s friend had been poor!” said I. “How many souls do we wring with
     additional pangs, to have our anxiety dispelled the
     <pb n="181"/> more easily? Think of the news of a battle, with so many killed and wounded—and
     some dreadful fortnight, or maybe month, to live through before one knows whether one’s own is
     dead or alive. No, ’tis a cruel earthly Geni, and not a celestial Spirit—it does good now and
     then, only because it cannot help it—relieves us, Derwent, but slaughters poor Mrs.
     Hughes.”</p>
    <p>“I believe Clare is not half-content—nobody must be killed to satisfy you women—but,
     unfortunately that will not do in this world,” said Derwent. “We have to be thankful for our
     own exemption, without entering too deeply into other people’s grief. And most of us find that
     philosophy easy enough.”</p>
    <p>“Most of us are very poor creatures,” said Maurice Harley, sententiously. He came alone to
     make his inquiries this time. Alice was invisible, and not to be heard of. I could not see her
     even when I called at the cottage. She had taken overpowering shame to herself, and shrank from
     my eyes. It was her brother who carried our news to his mother’s house—carried it, as I
     discovered incidentally, with the rarest and most delicate care for her—rigidly keeping up the
     fiction of supposing her not to care for it, nor to be specially interested, any more than for
     her old playfellow. He was ill at ease himself, and distracted
     <pb n="182"/> with questions no longer of a <hi>dilettante</hi> kind. In my eyes this increased
     his kindness all the more.</p>
    <p>“Yes, we are poor creatures the most of us,” repeated Maurice, when my husband—who did not
     notice any particular improvement in the Fellow of Exeter, and was disposed to be contemptuous,
     as elder men are, of his superiority to ordinary mortals—had sauntered, half-laughing,
     half-disgusted, out of the room. “Something you said the other day has stuck to my memory, Mrs.
     Crofton—help me out with it, pray. Are we worth a woman’s tears, the greater part of us? What
     is the good of us? I don’t mean Bertie, who is doing something in this world, but, for example,
     such a fellow as me!”</p>
    <p>“Take care, Maurice! I see hoofs and a tail upon that humility of yours,” said I. “You, who
     are so wise, do you not know that women and their tears are no more superlative than men and
     their doings? Did you think I meant the tender, heroical, sentimental tears of romance, for the
     sake of which the sublime knight might be content to die? No such thing. I meant only that
     there seems a kind of pathetic, homely justice in it, when the man who dies—especially the man
     who dies untimely—has a woman belonging to him, to be his true and faithful mourner;
     <pb n="183"/> that is all—it is nothing superlative; the sublime men are no better loved than
     the homeliest ones. Alice, if you asked her, would give you the poetical youthful
     interpretation of it, but I mean no such thing, Maurice. We want no great deeds, we womenkind;
     we were born to like you, and to cry over you, troublesome creatures that you are!”</p>
    <p>“Ah! that is very well,” said Maurice, who in his heart was young enough to like the
     superlative idea best. “I wish I had a supreme right to somebody’s tears—but why should anybody
     cry over me? Am not I foredoomed to shrivel up into a College Don?”</p>
    <p>“If you please,” said I.</p>
    <p>“And if I don’t please?” cried Maurice, starting up, and seizing, after his usual fashion, a
     book off the table. He made a hurried march about the room, as usual, too; throwing that down;
     and picking up another to look at its title, then returned, and repeated, with some
     emphasis—“And what if I don’t please?”</p>
    <p>“Why then, please God, you will do something better,” said I; “I hope so sincerely—it will
     give me the greatest pleasure—but you don’t make any progress by talking of it; that is our
     woman’s province. <hi>Do</hi>, Maurice, <hi>do</hi>! don’t <hi>say</hi>!”</p>
    <p>The young man flashed with an angry and
     <pb n="184"/> abashed color. “Thank you, I will, if it were to carry a hod. I have not
     forgotten,” he said, with a little bitter meaning, “that I am a widow’s son.”</p>
    <p>“A widow’s son should be the prince of sons,” said I. “You make me preach, you young people,
     though it is not my vocation. Carry a hod then, if you will, like a gentleman and a Christian,
     and I, for one, will bid you God speed.”</p>
    <p>Maurice put down his book, and came forward to me, holding out his hand. I suspect he liked
     me, though he had no great reason, and I confess, now-a-days, that I liked him. He held out his
     hand to say good-bye, and in saying good-bye opened his heart.</p>
    <p>“Mrs. Crofton, you preach very well, considering that it is not your vocation; but I begin to
     think I am coming to that big preacher, Life, whom you once told me of. <hi>He</hi> is not a
     college don. Do you know,” said Maurice, with a frank, confused laugh, and rising color, “I’m
     in love?”</p>
    <p>“I suspected as much,” said I. “Is all well?”</p>
    <p>“All was ill, what with my own folly, and what with that spiteful little witch at the
     Rectory,” said Maurice; “but it’s coming right again. If I were to die to-morrow—little as I
     deserve them—I believe I should have these woman’s tears.”
     <pb n="185"/></p>
    <p>“My dear boy, be thankful, and go home and live!” said I, with the water in my eyes. I was
     half inclined to kiss, and bless, and cry over him in the foolishness of my heart.</p>
    <p>“I will,” said Maurice, in the fulness and effusion of his; and he kissed my hand with a
     congenial impulse, and went away abruptly, moved beyond speaking. He left me more profoundly
     and pleasantly touched than I had been for a long time. Perhaps I thought, with natural vanity,
     that I had a little—just a little—share in it. Dire must be the disappointment, and heavy the
     calamity, which should shrivel up Maurice Harley now into a college don.
     <pb n="186"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XXI.</head>
    <p><hi>Another</hi> long period of home quietness, but great anxiety followed this. Bertie, of
     course, would not return while the crisis of affairs in India had not yet been determined; and
     we were so much the more anxious about him, since he had been restored to us, as it seemed, out
     of the very grave. Later he was seriously wounded, threatened with fever, and really in great
     danger, but got through that as he had through all the other perils of that murderous Indian
     war. He distinguished himself, too, to our great pride and delight, especially to the boundless
     exultation of Derwie, and gained both credit and promotion almost beyond the hopes of so young
     a man. But, in the meantime, we were both anxious and concerned, for we could not induce him to
     think that he had encountered his full share of the fighting, and might now, surely, with
     perfect honor and satisfaction bring his laurels home.</p>
    <p>“If the women and the babies are all safe on board the ships,” said Derwie, who was almost
     <pb n="187"/> as reluctant to consent to Bertie’s return before the fighting was over as Bertie
     himself.</p>
    <p>During all this time I scarcely saw Alice; she avoided coming in my way; when we met, avoided
     speaking to me—avoided looking in my face when that was practicable—could neither forgive
     herself for having betrayed her feelings, nor me for having witnessed that betrayal. Altogether
     her feelings towards me and in my presence were evidently so uncomfortable, that out of mere
     charity and consideration I no longer visited Mrs. Harley’s as I had done, nor invited them to
     Hilfont. They still came sometimes, but not as they had done before. I began to fear that I had
     lost Alice, which, to be sure, was unkind of her, considering what very old friends we were;
     but she could not forget nor forgive either herself or me for those tears out of which she had
     been cheated over that supposititious grave where Bertie Nugent was not.</p>
    <p>So that there occurred an interregnum of information, at least, if not of interest, in
     respect to the Harleys. Maurice was in London, struggling forward to find what place he could
     in that perennial battle—struggling not very successfully—for, to the amazement of all, and,
     above all, to his own, he was not so greatly in advance of other people, when he had done
     something definite
     <pb n="188"/> to be judged by, as the Fellow of Exeter had supposed himself. Providence, in
     quaint, poetic justice, had deprived Maurice, for example, of that faculty of writing which he
     had, maybe, esteemed too highly. His admirers had prophesied great triumphs for him in the
     field of literature before he had tried his pen there; but it turned out that Maurice could not
     write, and the discovery was rather humiliating to the young man. I have no doubt he made an
     infinitude of other discoveries equally unpleasant. His Fellowship kept him from starving, but
     it aggravated his failures and the pain of them, and held up more conspicuously than might have
     been desired, the unexpected imperfections of “Harley of Exeter,” in whom his contemporaries
     had been disposed to put a great deal of faith. Nevertheless, Maurice held on bravely. I liked
     him better and better as he found himself out. And he bore the discovery like a man.</p>
    <p>As for Johnnie, poor boy, who had, all uneducated and without training as he was, just that
     gift of putting his mind into words which his brother lacked—he had not yet come to the bitter
     ending of his boyish dream. He was busy with his second book, in high hope and spirits,
     thinking himself equally secure of fame and of love. The poor lad had forgotten entirely the
     <pb n="189"/> difference between the present time and that past age in which literature, fresh
     and novel, took its most sovereign place. He thought how Fanny Burney was fêted and applauded
     for her early novel; he thought of Scott’s unrivalled influence and honor; and he forgot that a
     hundred people write books, and especially write stories, now-a-days, for one who wrote
     then—and that he himself was only the unconsidered member of a multitudinous tribe, over whose
     heads Fame soared far away. It was not wonderful—he was scarcely one and twenty yet, though he
     was an author, and Miss Reredos’s slave. He meant to make the lady of his love “glorious with
     his pen,” as Montrose did, and expected to find an equal monarchy in her heart. Poor cripple
     Johnnie! a sadder or more grievous folly never was.</p>
    <p>But it surprised me to find that he, poor fellow, was never the object of his mother’s
     anxiety. She was sorry, with a sort of contempt for his “infatuation,” and could not for her
     life imagine what men could see in that Miss Reredos. Mrs. Harley was a very kind and tender
     mother, ready at any time to deny herself for any real gratification to her boy; but she did
     not make much account of his heartbreak, of which “nothing could come.” For all practical purposes
     <pb n="190"/> Johnnie’s love-tale was but a fable—nothing could ever come of it. Anything so
     unlikely as that Miss Reredos would marry the cripple never entered anybody’s mind but his own.
     And Mrs. Harley accordingly took it calmly, save for a momentary outburst of words now and then
     against the cause of Johnnie’s delusion—that was all. Nothing save the bitter disappointment,
     the violent mortification, the youthful despair, all augmented and made doubly poignant by the
     ill health and infirmities of this unfortunate boy, could result from his unlucky love-fever.
     So his mother was calm, and made no account of that among her may troubled and anxious
     concerns.</p>
    <p>As for Alice, she was still Mrs. Harley’s greatest grievance, though I was not trusted with
     the same confidences, nor implored to use my influence, as before. Alice was more capricious,
     more tantalizing, less to be reckoned on than ever. She had, I suppose, dismissed Mr. Reredos
     with less courtesy than the Rector believed due to him, for he went about his duties with a
     certain grim sullenness, like an injured man, and never permitted himself to mention her name.
     I was in the Rector’s ill graces, as well as in those of Alice. He could not forgive me any
     more than she could, for the confidence themselves had
     <pb n="191"/> bestowed. It was rather hard upon me to be thus excommunicated for no ill-doings
     of my own; but I bore it as best I could, sorry for Mr. Reredos, and not doubting that, some
     time or other, Alice would come to herself.</p>
    <p>It was thus, in our immediate surroundings, that we spent the time until Bertie’s return.
     <pb n="192"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XXII.</head>
    <p><hi>It</hi> was once more spring when Bertie returned. Spring—Easter—that resurrection time
     which came to our hearts with a more touching force when we received home into our peaceful
     house—so pale, so worn out, and yet so sunburnt and scarred with violent labors past—that
     Bertie, who had gone from us so strong and so bold. He had been repeatedly wounded—had suffered
     more than once from fever—had felt, at last, that his health was broken, and that there was
     little more use in him while he remained in India, and so was persuaded to come home. Derwent,
     kindest of friends, went to meet him at Southampton, and brought him home as tenderly as any
     nurse, or rather far more tenderly, with a tenderness more considerate and requiring less
     response than that of a woman. To see our young hero an invalid, overpowered me entirely. I
     quite broke down under it, comparing him with what he was, and fearing everything from the
     mortal paleness, thrown by his sunbrowned complexion
     <pb n="193"/> into a ghastly yellow, which sometimes overspread his face. Derwent judged more
     justly—he held up his finger to me when he saw the exclamation of dismay and grief that
     trembled on my lips.</p>
    <p>“He’s tired, Clare,” said my husband. “A bright fire, and an English bed and rest—that’s all
     Bertie wants to-night. He’ll answer all your questions to-morrow. Come, old fellow, you know
     your way to your old room.”</p>
    <p>“I should think so, indeed—and thank God I am at home,” cried Bertie, with his familiar
     voice. With a thrill of anguish I restrained my salutations and followed quietly to see that
     all was comfortable for him. He protested that it was nonsense, that he could come downstairs
     perfectly well, that Mr. Crofton only wanted to humble his vanity; but at the same moment drew
     up his foot wearily upon the sofa, with a gesture that showed better than words his need of
     rest.</p>
    <p>“Alas, Derwent, has it come to this?” said I, as we went downstairs.</p>
    <p>Derwent turned round upon me, put his big hands upon my shoulders, and thrust me in before
     him to the handiest room. “Now, Clare,” he said, with comical solemnity, “if we are going to
     have any nonsense or lamentations, I’ll
     <pb n="194"/> shut you up here till my patient’s better. The boy is as sound as I am, and would
     be able to ride to cover in a fortnight, if any such chances were going. Now don’t say a word—I
     am speaking simple truth.”</p>
    <p>“I must trust my own eyes,” said I; “but you need not fear my indiscretion. See how I have
     refrained from agitating him now.”</p>
    <p>“Agitating him! Oh!” cried Derwent, with a good-humored roar. “What stuff you speak, to be
     sure! He is quite able to be agitated as much as you please—there is nothing in the world but
     wounds and fatigue the matter with Bertie. I am afraid you are only a woman after all, Clare;
     but you’re not to interfere with my patient. I’ve taken him in hand, and mind you, I’m to have
     the credit, and bring him through.”</p>
    <p>“But, oh, Derwent,” said I, “how pale he is!”</p>
    <p>“If I had seen as many dreadful sights as he has, I should be pale too,” said Derwent.
     “Seriously, he is tired and worn out, but not ill. Don’t be sorry for him, Clare—don’t put
     anything in his head. Talk pleasantly. I don’t forbid the subject, for example,” said my
     husband, looking at me with a certain affectionate cloudy mirth, as if he had known my secret
     all along, “of Alice Harley, if you choose.”</p>
    <p>I put him aside a little impatiently, and he
     <pb n="195"/> followed me into the very late dinner, which had been deferred for the arrival of
     the travellers, and where Bertie’s empty chair struck me again with a little terror. But I was
     wise for once, and yielded to Derwent’s more cheerful opinion. On the next morning Bertie was
     better—he went on getting better day by day. Derwent took care of him, and attended him in a
     way which took me by surprise; never teasing him with questions—never gazing at him with his
     heart in his eyes, as we womanish creatures do, to mar the work we would give our lives to
     accomplish; but with his eyes always open, and his attention really missing nothing that
     happened, and taking account of all.</p>
    <p>A week after his arrival, Bertie, who hitherto had been telling me, as he could, his
     adventures in India—dread adventures, interwoven with all the thread of that murderous
     history—at last broke all at once into the full tide of home talk.</p>
    <p>“And dear old Estcourt, Cousin Clare,” said Bertie, “stands exactly as it was, I suppose; and
     Miss Austin as steadfast as the lime trees—and the children to keep the old park cheerful—all
     as it was?”</p>
    <p>“All as it was, Bertie; but the other house ready and waiting for you.”</p>
    <p>I looked up with a little anxiety to see the
     <pb n="196"/> effect of what I said. Distracted with a disappointed love, Bertie had left
     us—ill and languid he had returned. I thought my words might recall to his mind at once his old
     dreams and his present weakness; and with some terror I glanced at his face. He was lying on
     the sofa in that bright morning room with the great bow window, from which, shining afar like a
     great picture, he could see all the peaceful slope of our low-country, with the river
     glistening in links and bends, and the cathedral towers far off, lending a graceful centre and
     conclusion to the scene.</p>
    <p>Bertie did not return my glance; he lay still, with a languid ease and satisfaction in his
     attitude which struck me for the first time—as if he was profoundly content to be there, and
     felt his fatigues and pains melt away in that warmth of home. As I looked at him a warmer color
     rose over his brown-pale face, a pleasant glimmer woke in his eye—his whole aspect warmed and
     brightened—a half conscious smile came playing about his parted lips. Whatever Bertie thought
     upon, it was neither disappointment nor broken health.</p>
    <p>There was a long pause—the silence was pleasant—broken only by the soft domestic sounds of a
     great house; brightly lay that pleasant landscape
     <pb n="197"/> outside the window, all soft and sweet with spring; tender and pleasant was the
     contrast of all the scene, the care and love surrounding the soldier now, with the burning
     plains and cruel contests from which he had come; and thoughts, dear, warm, and tender, arose
     in Bertie’s heart. He paused long, perhaps, with a simple art, to conceal from me a little the
     link of pleasant association which had directed his thoughts that way—then, with that wavering,
     conscious smile, spoke—</p>
    <p>“So Alice Harley is not married,” he said, turning on his elbow, with a pretence of
     carelessness, as if to get a fuller view. “How is that, Cousin Clare?”</p>
    <p>To think that Alice Harley connected herself instinctively with the idea of Bertie’s house
     which was ready for him, was a pleasant thought to me; but I only answered, “There is no
     telling, Bertie. She might have been married two or three times had she pleased.”</p>
    <p>“I am very glad of it,” said Bertie; “to see every pretty girl whom one used to know
     converted into the mother of ever so many children, makes a fellow feel old before his time. I
     am not so frightfully old, after all; but I fear nobody will have anything to say to a worn-out
     poor soldier like me.”</p>
    <p>“Don’t be too humble, Bertie,” said I. “I
     <pb n="198"/> don’t think, between ourselves, that Colonel Nugent is so very diffident of his
     own merits. On the contrary, he knows he has made a little noise in this world, is aware that
     people will drink his health, and fête him when he is well enough, and that all the young
     ladies will smile upon the hero. Don’t you think now, honestly, that this is the real state of
     the case?”</p>
    <p>Bertie blushed and fell back to his old position. “Don’t be hard upon a fellow, Cousin
     Clare,” he said, with a slightly pleading tone—half afraid of ridicule—half conscious that
     little ridicule was to be expected from me.</p>
    <p>“No indeed, quite the reverse—nobody will be hard upon you, my boy,” said I. “Huntingshire is
     quite ready to bestow anything you wish upon you, Bertie—anything from a seat in Parliament, up
     to the prettiest daughter it has, if you mean to set up your household gods in the Estcourt
     jointure-house.”</p>
    <p>Bertie blushed once more, and coughed, and cleared his throat a little, as if he had some
     intentions of taking me into his confidence, when my boy Derwie suddenly made a violent
     diversion by rushing in all red and excited, and flinging himself against our soldier with all
     his might.</p>
    <p>“Bertie!” shouted little Derwent, “is it true you’re going to have the Victoria Cross?”</p>
    <p>Bertie colored violently as he recovered from
     <pb n="199"/> that shock. I don’t believe, if he had been suddenly charged with running away,
     that he would have looked half as much abashed.</p>
    <p>“Why, you know, Derwie, we’d all like it if we could get it,” he said, faltering slightly;
     but I knew in a moment, by the sudden movement of his head and glance of his eye, that he
     really did believe it possible, and that this was the darling ambition of Bertie’s heart.</p>
    <p>“But Bevan told me!” cried Derwie—“he told me about those gates, you know, that you and the
     rest blew up. Mamma, listen! There were six of them, forlorn-hope men, Bevan says”——</p>
    <p>“Ah, Derwie, hush!—four of them sleep yonder, the brave fellows!—four privates, who could not
     hope for distinction like me,” cried Bertie, with that same profound awe and compunction,
     contrasting his own deliverance with the calamity of others, which had once stricken me.</p>
    <p>“A private can have the Victoria Cross as well as a general,” cried Derwie, clapping his
     hands; “and more likely, Bevan says—for a general commands and doesn’t fight.”</p>
    <p>“That is true—God save the Queen!” cried Bertie. “If Corporal Inglis gets it, Derwie—and he
     ought—we’ll illuminate.”</p>
    <p>“If you get it,” said Derwie, “you deserve it all the same. Mamma, they blew up the gates
     <pb n="200"/> with gunpowder; they went close—so close that”——</p>
    <p>“Boh!” cried Bertie; “mamma read all about it in the papers. It was nothing particular—it
     only had to be done, that’s all. Now, Derwie, don’t you know when a thing has to be done
     somebody must do it?”</p>
    <p>“Yes, I know,” said Derwie, “perfectly well. When mamma says <hi>must</hi> I always go
     directly—don’t I, mamma?—and if I were as big as you I wouldn’t mind being killed either. When
     you were killed, Bertie—that time you know when everybody thought so—oh, what a crying there
     was!”</p>
    <p>“Was there?” asked Bertie, with a softened tone, putting his arm round the eager child.</p>
    <p>But a new point of interest in those human studies which were so dear to him had suddenly
     seized upon Derwie’s imagination. He turned abruptly to me.</p>
    <p>“Mamma, didn’t Alice come once and cry? I saw her go away with such red eyes; and she never
     came again, and never looked like her own self when she did come,” said my boy, with a
     courageous disregard of grammar. “What is that for? Wasn’t she glad when Bertie came alive
     again, and it was only poor Captain Hughes?”</p>
    <p>“Hush, Derwie, my boy—you don’t understand
     <pb n="201"/> these things. I was deeply grieved for that poor Captain Hughes, Bertie—I almost
     felt as if, in our great anxiety for you, his fall was our fault.”</p>
    <p>But Bertie was not thinking of Captain Hughes. He was looking intently at me with that
     wavering color in his cheeks and an eager question in his eyes. When I spoke, my words recalled
     him a little, and he put on a grave look, and murmured something about the “poor fellow!” or
     “brave fellow!” I could not tell which—then looked at me again, eager, with a question hovering
     on his lips. The question of all others which I was resolute not to answer. So I gathered up my
     work remorselessly, put it away in my work-table, jingled my keys, told him I would see if the
     newspaper had come yet, and left the room without looking round. He might find that out at
     Alice’s own hands if he wished it—he should not receive any clandestine information from me.
     <pb n="202"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XXIII.</head>
    <p><hi>The</hi> first visit which Bertie was able to make was to the cottage—to see Mrs. Harley,
     as he said, gravely—but I fear he did not get a very satisfactory reception. He told me he
     thought Alice greatly changed when he returned; but he was not communicative on the subject,
     and had a decided inclination to go back again. Perhaps the wavering, pleasant, half-conscious
     sentiment, and tender youthful reminiscence, with which Bertie came home, was the better of a
     little opposition to warm it into independent life; and Alice had reason enough for a double
     share of perversity and caprice, though Bertie knew nothing of that. She had betrayed herself
     to me, and, for a moment, to Maurice. She thought, no doubt, that everybody had suspected that
     secret of hers—and with unconscious self-importance, that it was whispered throughout the
     country with secret smiles over all her former unmarried-woman superiority to vulgar
     love-affairs. Her credit was consequently very deeply
     <pb n="203"/> involved—she would not have smiled upon Bertie Nugent now had it been to save his
     life.</p>
    <p>Still, however, Bertie, in the pleasant leisure of his convalescence, betook himself to Mrs.
     Harley’s cottage; and came home talking of Johnnie and little Kate, and the letters from
     Maurice—but very little about Alice, save chance words now and then, which showed a singularly
     close observation of her habits. Sometimes he asked me puzzled questions about those opinions
     of hers. Bertie, though he had been cheated once, was not contemptuous of womenkind. He did not
     understand these new views about the vulgarity of being married, and the propriety of
     multiplying female occupations. I suspect he entertained the natural delusion that, while he
     himself stood there, most ready and anxious, to share with her the common course of life,
     private projects of her own, which turned her aside from that primitive and ancient occupation
     of wife, were a little fantastical, and extremely perplexing. But Bertie was not like Mr.
     Reredos—he wanted simply to be at the bottom of it, and find out what she meant. He was not the
     man to worry any woman into marrying him, or to lay insidious siege to her friends. Ancient
     kindness, a lingering recollection of her youthful sweetness and beauty, which had come softly
     back to
     <pb n="204"/> Bertie after his early love-troubles, and which had been kept alive by the
     fascination of a secret delicious wonder, whether, perhaps, <hi>he</hi> might have anything to
     do with the fact of her remaining unmarried, had combined to direct Bertie’s thoughts towards
     Alice, and to connect her image with all the plans and intentions of his return home. In short,
     the feeling upon both sides was very much alike—with both it was a certain captivating
     imaginary link, far more subtle and sweet than an understood engagement, which warmed their
     hearts to each other. But for those tragical possibilities which had so deeply excited Alice,
     all would have gone as smoothly as possible when our hero came home. Now the obstacles on each
     side were great. On Alice’s, that dread idea of having betrayed a secret, unsought, unreturned
     affection for the distant soldier, along with the lesser but still poignant remembrance of Lady
     Greenfield’s malicious report that Bertie himself had expected Cousin Clare to have somebody in
     her pocket for him to marry. On Bertie’s part, the equally dangerous chance that, deeply
     mortified by finding his hope of having some share in her thoughts so entirely unfounded, as it
     appeared, he might turn away sorrowfully from the theories which influenced her, but which his
     simple intelligence did not comprehend.
     <pb n="205"/> Never matchmaker was more perplexed than I was between these two; I dared not say
     a word to either—I looked on, trembling, at the untoward course of affairs. It was Bertie who
     disappointed me once; for all I could see, it was most likely to be Alice now.</p>
    <p>When we began—which was not till another autumn restored us to Hilfont—to be able to give
     some entertainments to our country neighbors, in honor of our soldier, Alice, most cleverly and
     cunningly avoided coming. She had always some admirable excuse—some excuse so unquestionable
     that it would have been quite cruel to have grumbled at it. I do not think she had been once
     within our house since Bertie returned. She sent me her love, and the most dutiful messages.
     She was so sorry, but she was sure her dear Mrs. Crofton would not be displeased when she knew.
     I was displeased, however, and had hard ado with myself to keep from saying as much, and
     declaring my conviction that she was very unkind to Bertie. I daresay I might have done so with
     advantage, though prudence and the fear of something coming of it, restrained me—for the idea
     of being unkind to Bertie would, doubtless, have been balm to Alice’s soul.</p>
    <p>They met, however, though she would not come to Hilfont—Clara Sedgwick, who was as
     <pb n="206"/> bold to give Bertie welcome as she had been to weep her free sisterly tears,
     which there was no need to conceal, over his supposed grave, arranged one of her very largest
     and grandest dinner-parties for Bertie as soon as it was practicable. Everybody was there—Lady
     Greenfield and her husband, who had all at once grown an old man, his wife having stopped his
     fox-hunting long ago—and Miss Polly, and all the Croftons, far and near, and such Nugents as
     could be picked up handily; and finally, all the great people of the county, to glorify our
     hero. I cannot tell by what ingenious process of badgering Alice had been driven out of her
     retirement, and produced that night in the Waterflag drawing-room. I will not even guess what
     cruel sisterly sarcasms and suggestions of what people might say, had supplemented the sisterly
     coaxing which were, no doubt, ineffectual; but there Alice was—there she stood by the side of
     Clara’s dazzling toilette and rosy tints, pale and clouded, in her brown silk dress—her
      <hi>old</hi> brown silk dress, made in a fashion which “went out” at least three years ago;
     without a single ornament about her anywhere—her hair braided as plainly as though she had just
     come down-stairs to make the tea, and superintend the breakfast table—not even the pretty
     bouquet of delicate flowers at her breast,
     <pb n="207"/> which made so pretty a substitute for jewels on little Kate’s white dress—not a
     bracelet nor a ring—nothing to diversify the entire plainness of her appearance, nor a single
     sparkle or gleam of reflection on neck, finger, or arm. I confess that I was both annoyed and
     disappointed. Instead of doing her womanly utmost to look well and young, as became her, Alice
     had exhausted all her perverse pains in making a dowdy of herself. I cannot say she had
     succeeded. It was the crisis of her life, and mind and heart were alike full of movement and
     agitation. She could not prevent the excitement of her circumstances from playing about her
     with a gleaming fitful light, which made her expressive face wonderfully attractive. She could
     not but betray, in despite of her cold, unadorned appearance, and the almost prim reserve which
     she affected, the tumult and contest within her—extreme emotion, so restrained that the effort
     of self-control gave a look of power and command to her face, and somehow elevated and dilated
     her entire figure, and so contradictory that it flashed a hundred different meanings in a
     moment out of those eyes which were defiant, sarcastic, tender, and proud, all in a glance. I
     am not sure even that her plain dress did not defeat its purpose still more palpably; it
     distinguished her, singularly enough,
     <pb n="208"/> from other people—it directed everybody’s attention to her—it suggested reasons
     for that prim and peculiar attire—all which, if Alice had guessed them, would have thrown her
     into an agony of shame.</p>
    <p>Miss Reredos was also one of Clara’s great party—much against little Mrs. Sedgwick’s
     will—only because it could not be helped, Mrs. Harley being still pertinacious in favor of the
     Rector, who had all but given up his own cause. And we were still engaged in the mysteries of
     dinner, and there still remained all the long evening to operate in, when I perceived that this
     indefatigable young lady had seriously devoted herself to the entertainment of Bertie. He was
     doing his best to be polite, the good fellow; but it was a long time before he could be warmed
     into a flirtation. At last some very decided slight from Alice irritated my poor soldier. He
     turned to the play beside him, and began to amuse himself with it as so many other men had
     done. Thanks to Miss Reredos, it speedily became a notable flirtation, witnessed and observed
     by all the party. Alice watched it with a gradual elevation of her head, paling of her cheeks,
     and look of lofty silent indignation, which was infinitely edifying to me. What had she to do
     with it?—she who would not bestow a single glance upon Colonel
     <pb n="209"/> Nugent—who called him perpetually by that ceremonious name—who was blind and deaf
     to all his deprecating looks and allusions to youthful days. If he should flirt or even fall in
     love with and marry Miss Reredos, what was that to Alice? But, to be sure, most likely that
     indignation of hers was all for Johnnie’s sake.</p>
    <p>Poor Johnnie! He sat glaring at Bertie with furious eyes. Johnnie’s little bit of bookish
     distinction disappeared and sank to nothing in presence of Bertie’s epaulettes. Nobody felt the
     least interest to-day in Mrs. Harley’s clever cripple-boy. His Laura indeed had kept him in
     life, when she first arrived, by some morsels of kindness, but Laura too had gone over to the
     enemy. Laura was visibly disposed to charm into her own train that troublesome interloper, and
     Johnnie, who had resented and forgiven fifty violent flirtations of his lady-love since he
     himself first found new life, as he said, in her eyes, was more bitterly resentful of this
     defection than he had been of any previous one. If she and the other culprit, Bertie, could
     have been consumed by looks, we should have had only two little heaps of ashes to clear away
     from the Sedgwicks’ dinner-table that day in place of those two unfortunate people; but Miss
     Reredos was happily non-combustible. She swept away in all the fulness
     <pb n="210"/> of crinoline when the inevitable moment came and we womenkind were dismissed,
     insulting her unhappy young lover by a little nod and smile addressed to him across the table,
     which would have been delicious an hour ago, but was wormwood and bitterness now. Bertie, I
     think, at the same moment caught Alice’s lofty, offended, indignant glance, and brightened to
     see the quiet resentment in that perverse young woman’s face. It had all the effect of sunshine
     upon our soldier. At that crisis we left affairs, when we went to the drawing-room. I confess I
     don’t share the often-expressed sentiment about the dulness and absurdity of that little
     after-dinner interval. The young ladies and the young gentlemen may not like it, perhaps, but
     when could we maturer womenkind snatch a comfortable moment for that dear domestic talk which
     you superior people call gossip, if it were not in the pleasant relaxation of this interregnum,
     when the other creatures are comfortably disposed of downstairs? But for once in my life, being
     profoundly interested in the present little drama—there is always one at least going on in a
     great house in the country full of visitors—I did long that day for the coming of the
     gentlemen, or of Bertie, at least, the hero at once of the situation and of the day.
     <pb n="211"/></p>
    <p>The first to come upstairs was Johnnie Harley. For some time past he had rather affected, as
     a manly practice, the habit of sitting to the last after dinner. This day he was burning to
     discharge the fulness of his wrath upon Miss Reredos, so he lost no time, anxious to be
     beforehand with his new rival. Miss Reredos had already posed herself at a table, covered with
     a wealth of prints and photographs, these sentimental amusements being much in her way.</p>
    <p>“I have come to have my turn,” said Johnnie, savagely. I was seated within hearing, and, I
     confess, felt no very strong inducement to withdraw from my position. Perhaps Johnnie did not
     see me—Miss Reredos did, and certainly did not care. “I am come to have my turn, and to tell
     you that I can’t be content to take turns—especially with that empty fellow Nugent, whom you
     seem, like all the rest, to have taken so great a fancy to.”</p>
    <p>“Colonel Nugent is not an empty fellow—he is a very agreeable man,” said Miss Reredos,
     calmly.</p>
    <p>“Oh! and I am not, I suppose?” cried the reckless and embittered boy.</p>
    <p>“You certainly are not always agreeable,” answered poor Johnnie’s false
     <pb n="212"/>love, quite blandly; “and as for being a <hi>man</hi> at all—— We have really had
     quite enough of this, thank you, Master Harley. One tires of these scenes—they don’t answer
     when they are repeated every day.”</p>
    <p>“No—not when there is better sport going!” cried poor Johnnie. “I see it all now—you have
     only been making game of me all the time.”</p>
    <p>“Did you ever suppose anything else?” asked the witch coldly. I think it must have been
     Johnnie’s transport of passion which made the floor thrill, as I felt under my chair. I heard a
     furious muttered exclamation—then a long pause. The passion changed, and a great sob came out
     of Johnnie’s boyish heart.</p>
    <p>“You don’t mean what you say—Laura, Laura!” groaned the poor lad. I could have—— well, to be
     sure I am only a vindictive woman, as women are. I don’t know what I could not have done to
     her, sitting calm and self-satisfied there.</p>
    <p>“It is quite time this should be over,” said the virtuous Miss Reredos; “I was not making
     game of you; but I certainly was amusing myself, as I thought you were doing, also. Why, I am
     three or four years older than you—you silly boy!—don’t you know?”</p>
    <p>She might have said five or six years, which would have been nearer the truth, but it
     mattered nothing to Johnnie.
     <pb n="213"/></p>
    <p>“I could be as good a man as <hi>him</hi> for your sake,” he cried, with a gasp. Miss Reredos
     only played with the fan which dangled from her wrist.</p>
    <p>“Say you did not mean it, Laura,” whispered the unfortunate boy again.</p>
    <p>But Laura shook her head.</p>
    <p>“No, no—it has gone quite far enough. Oh! I’m not angry—but, dear, dear, don’t you see it’s
     no use. You are a great deal—at least you are younger than I am—and we have nothing, neither of
     us—and besides”——</p>
    <p>“Besides I am a cripple, and you don’t love me!” cried Johnnie, wildly.</p>
    <p>“I can’t contradict it,” said Circe with a toss of her head.</p>
    <p>Another fierce exclamation, a hurried dash across the room, a wondering little scream from
     Clara, across whose ample skirts her brother plunged, as he rushed half frantic away, ended
     this episode. Clara rose up, startled and nervous, to look after him—and I had to restrain
     myself from the same impulse; but Circe sat calm among her photographs, and made no sign. After
     a few moments’ interval Clara went tremulously after him. I could only settle myself on my
     chair again. The poor cripple boy—tenderest and merriest of the flock—whom all the rest had
     <pb n="214"/> guarded so jealously!—they could do nothing for him now. He, too, like all the
     rest of us, had his burden to bear alone.</p>
    <p>But I sat on thorns, fearing to see Bertie, when he came upstairs, resume his flirtation with
     “that witch from the Rectory,” whom Maurice had so truly named. He did not, to my great
     satisfaction—but remained very quiet, refusing, great lion as he was, to roar—and looking as
     plaintive and pathetic as it was possible for Bertie’s honest face, unused to simulation of any
     kind, to look. I fancy the poor fellow imagined—a forlorn hope of that good, simple mind of
     his, which certainly was not original in its expedients—that Alice might possibly be influenced
     more favorably by his pitiful looks.</p>
    <p>Seeing this, I undertook a little management of that very refractory young person myself.</p>
    <p>“Alice, you will come to Hilfont on my birthday, as you have always done—won’t you?—that will
     be in a fortnight,” said I.</p>
    <p>“If you please, Mrs. Crofton,” said Alice, very demurely.</p>
    <p>“You know I please; but I don’t please that you should promise, and then send me such a
     clever, pretty, reasonable excuse when the time comes, that I cannot say a word against it, but
     only feel secretly that it is very unkind.”
     <pb n="215"/></p>
    <p>“Unkind! to <hi>you</hi>, Mrs. Crofton!” cried Alice, with a little blush and start.</p>
    <p>“To me—who else?—it is for <hi>my</hi> birthday that I ask you to come,” said I, with an
     artful pretense of feeling offended; “but really, if you treat me as you have done before, I
     shall be disposed to believe there is <hi>some reason</hi> why you refuse so steadily to
     come.”</p>
    <p>“You may be quite sure I will not stay away,” said Alice, with great state.</p>
    <p>She sat by me for half an hour longer, but we did not exchange a dozen words. She said
     “nothing to nobody” all the remainder of the evening; she looked just a little cross as well,
     if the truth must be told.
     <pb n="216"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER XXIV.</head>
    <p><hi>A fortnight</hi> after came my birthday, and a family festival.</p>
    <p>Mr. Crofton was greatly given to keeping birthdays; he was not a man to be daunted by that
     coldest and vulgarest commonplace, which warns us with lugubrious mock solemnity that these
     birthdays are hastening us to the grave. The grave out of which our Lord rose was no devouring,
     irresponsible monster to Derwent—it was a Christian institution, blessed and hallowed by Him
     who triumphed over it. So he kept his birthdays with thanks and a celebration of love; and I
     was well content in this, as in many another kind suggestion of his genial nature, that my
     husband should have his way.</p>
    <p>Bertie was to leave us shortly after, to look after the fitting up of his own house—the
     Estcourt jointure-house, which he was to occupy during my lifetime. It was a very sufficient,
     comfortable house, and he was to fit it up according to his own taste. But he was very slow
     <pb n="217"/> to talk of his intentions. Any suggestions which I made to him on the subject he
     received in silence, or with a confused assent. Good Bertie!—he meant that somebody else should
     decide these questions for him; and somebody else was so perverse, so unaccountable, so
     unsatisfactory. He sighed, and held his peace.</p>
    <p>Johnnie Harley wandered off from Waterflag that night, after his explanation with Miss
     Reredos. For a week the unfortunate lad was not heard of, and the family spent that interval in
     the wildest anxiety, making every kind of search after him, from Maurice’s hunt through London,
     whither they thought it likely he would go, to fruitless dragging in the pretty Est river,
     which mudded its pleasant pools, but fortunately had no other result. At the end of a week he
     came home—where he had been he never would tell. He returned ill, remorseful, and penitent,
     with all his little money gone, and his watch—his father’s watch—a catastrophe which quite
     completed Mrs. Harley’s misery. Renewed and increased ill health followed this sad escapade of
     poor Johnnie; but the boy was happy in his unhappiness—nothing could part from him that
     all-forgiving home-love which forgot every fault of the poor cripple boy.</p>
    <p>And in that fortnight Bertie made a brief
     <pb n="218"/> journey to London—a journey which thrilled the whole household with the highest
     excitement, and warmed every individual in it with a touch of the reflected glory. Bertie was
      <hi>decoré</hi> when he returned; but no, there is no French word in existence which deserves
     to be used in connection with that supremest badge of modern chivalry, which our boy, with a
     modest and shame-faced delight, impossible to describe in words, received from his Queen.</p>
    <p>Bertie wore his prize with a swelling breast, but an abashed cheek; indeed, he did not wear
     it at all, reserving it for his private triumph, and, as I supposed, for my birthday feast. But
     our hero had something else in his mind.</p>
    <p>The day came at last, and at last, most earnestly looked for, in a carriage filled with the
     Sedgwick children, and, I believe, all the flowers in Clara’s conservatory, and all that could
     be come by honestly or dishonestly within ten miles of country—Alice Harley made her
     appearance. To show emphatically how much I was mistaken in supposing that <hi>any reason</hi>
     could keep her away from Hilfont when her dear Mrs. Crofton wished her to be there, Alice with
     rash temerity had volunteered to take charge of the children, and come with them early and
     alone. In the same spirit she had actually taken a little
     <pb n="219"/> trouble with her dress, which was new, full, soft, and delicate—if not white, as
     nearly so as Alice’s conscience and profound conviction of her grave years could permit it to
     be. She was on her defence, but not exactly defiant as yet—a little melted in spite of herself
     by sundry associations of the place and time—by good news from Maurice, which she whispered in
     my ear, news of an appointment which her brother had got after much exertion, and which would
     enable him to marry; and perhaps a little by the honor which she knew her “old playfellow” had
     come to. I saw her cast a momentary but somewhat eager look at Bertie’s breast when she saw him
     first, but to my disappointment, as to hers, his decoration was not there.</p>
    <p>And then Alice had a present for me. I had by me a little present to be given to her on the
     same occasion—an old ornament of my own, which I thought, for that reason at least, the prim
     Alice might perhaps be induced to wear. The children had gone away with their attendants, to be
     extricated out of the many wrappings in which their mother’s care had enveloped them. Only
     Derwie stayed with us in the breakfast-room; the child was extremely anxious about these two, I
     could not tell why. Some unconscious link of association, or acute childish observation,
     <pb n="220"/> connected them in little Derwent’s mind. He stood by my side on pretence of
     waiting till Clary and the rest were ready, but I believe in my heart from sheer curiosity and
     interest in these affairs of life and humanity which were so deeply attractive to my son.</p>
    <p>Alice was seated near the great window, her pretty figure visible against the light, looking
     fresher and more youthful than she had done for a long time, and the soft breadth of landscape
     without, making a pleasant background to the picture. A little more in the shade stood Bertie,
     and Derwie and I were opposite Alice, with a little table between us, all full in the light of
     the large bow-window, from which all curtains and obscuring influences—such was my husband’s
     cheerful pleasure—were always drawn as much back as possible. My present to Alice was a little
     gold chain for the neck. I like that fashion of ornament. This one was long enough to encircle
     that pretty throat twice, or to hang loose upon her breast if she pleased. I said it wanted a
     pendant, as I threw it loosely round her neck.</p>
    <p>Alice had been a little nervous and tremulous before; this made her rather more so—she kissed
     me in a trembling, breathless way. She could not help feeling conscious of that shadow behind
     her, and of a certain want of air and cloud
     <pb n="221"/> which betokened a crisis. She knew something was coming, and faltered—it was
     quite a secret, close, appealing touch which her arms gave me for the moment. Alice was afraid.
     When she sat down again she played with the clasp of the chain and unloosed it, and continued
     so, unconsciously dangling that loose end in her hand.</p>
    <p>“It should have a heart at it, mamma—like Clary’s,” said little Derwent.</p>
    <p>“Yes,” said I, “certainly it wants a pendant—a locket—or, as Derwie says, a heart, or a
     cross, or——”</p>
    <p>“For once let me supply what it wants,” said Bertie, suddenly starting forward with one of
     those long, noiseless steps which people only make when they are almost past speaking. He took
     the end of the chain from Alice’s fingers, slid his own matchless decoration on it, clasped it,
     let it fall. “Heart and Cross!” said Bertie, breathless with feelings he could not speak. Alice
     had not looked up—did not see what it was, so rapidly was all done, till it lay dark upon the
     white bosom of her dress, moving with the palpitations of her heart—cold, ugly, glorious—a gift
     far beyond all Bertie’s fortune—more precious to him than his life.</p>
    <p>She gazed at it astonished for a moment, then glanced round at us all with an amazed, inquiring
     <pb n="222"/> glance—then faltering, and making the utmost efforts to control herself, took it
     in her hands, put it to her lips, and burst into an irrestrainable passion of tears.</p>
    <p>Little Derwie and I, like sensible people, took each other’s hands, and marched away.</p>
    <p>Alice did not wear her hero’s cross that night to her chain. He wore it himself, as was
     fit—but it did not much matter. She had taken the other invaluable and invisible appendage
     which Bertie offered with his glorious badge—had consented to be solemnly endowed with all his
     worldly goods, cross and heart included, and humbly put her chain round her neck without any
     pendant, in token of the unwilling bondage to which she had yielded at last.</p>
    <p>So ended, after eight years of disappointment, and <hi>that</hi> early love-affair, which
     Colonel Bertie had long ago forgotten, my solitary enterprise in match-making. Let nobody
     despair. I am secure now that Estcourt shall have no alien mistress, and that all Huntingshire
     will not hold a happier household than that of Bertie Nugent, my heir, who has already added
     the highest distinction of modern chivalry to the name of his fathers and mine.</p>
    <trailer>THE END.</trailer>

   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>
