<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <?xml-model href="../../Schemas/eltec-1.rng" type="application/xml" 
            schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
    <?xml-model href="../../Schemas/eltec-1.rng" type="application/xml" 
            schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:t="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="ENG19190" xml:lang="en">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>Living Alone : ELTeC edition</title>
    <author ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/90724564/">Benson, Stella (1892-1933)</author>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>ELTeC conversion</resp>
     <name>Lou Burnard</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="words">43395</measure>
    <measure unit="pages">264</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
<publisher ref="https://distant-reading.net">COST Action "Distant Reading for European Literary History" (CA16204)</publisher>
<distributor ref="https://zenodo.org/communities/eltec/">Zenodo.org</distributor><date when="2021-04-09"/>
<availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/></availability>
<ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3462435">ELTeC</ref>
<ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4662444">ELTeC release 1.1.0</ref>
<ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3533868">ELTeC-eng</ref>
<ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4662490">ELTeC-eng release 1.0.1</ref>
</publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc><bibl type="digitalSource"><title>The Project Gutenberg eBook of Living Alone, by Stella
      Benson.</title><ref target="http://www.gutenberg.org/files/14907/14907-h/14907-h.htm">Gutenberg</ref></bibl><bibl type="firstEdition" n="B0"><title>Living Alone</title><author>Stella
      Benson</author><publisher>Macmillan</publisher><date>1919</date></bibl><bibl type="printSource">
     <title>Living Alone</title><publisher>Macmillan</publisher><date>1920</date><ref target="http://archive.org/details/livingalone00bensiala"/>
    </bibl></sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc n="eltec-1">
   <p/>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
   </langUsage>
   <textDesc>
    <authorGender xmlns="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns" key="F"/>
    <size xmlns="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns" key="short"/>
    <reprintCount xmlns="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns" key="low"/>
    <timeSlot xmlns="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns" key="T4"/>
   </textDesc>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-04-09">Converted by checkUp script for new release</change>
<change when="2020-11-14">Converted by checkUp script for new release</change>
   <change when="2019-11-09">Checked by releaseChecker script</change>
   <change when="2019-02-27">LB convert to ELTeC-1</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text type="T4FSU">
  <front>
   <div type="titlepage">
    <p>LIVING ALONE</p>
    <p>BY</p>
    <p>STELLA BENSON</p>
    <p>AUTHOR OF "I POSE," "THIS IS THE END"</p>
    <p>MACMILLAN AND CO., LIMITED</p>
    <p>ST. MARTIN'S STREET, LONDON</p>
    <p>1920</p>
    <p><hi>First Edition 1919</hi><hi>Reprinted 1920 (twice)</hi></p>
   </div>
   <div type="liminal">
    <p>This is not a real book. It does not deal with real people, nor should it be read by real
     people. But there are in the world so many real books already written for the benefit of real
     people, and there are still so many to be written, that I cannot believe that a little alien
     book such as this, written for the magically-inclined minority, can be considered too assertive
     a trespasser.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="liminal">
    <p>I have to thank the Editor of the <hi>Athenæum</hi> for allowing me to reprint the poem
     "Detachment" and the first chapter of this book. The courtesy of the Editor of the <hi>Pall
      Mall Gazette</hi> in permitting me to use again any of my contributions to his paper also
     enables me to include in the fifth chapter the tragic incident of the Mad 'Bus.</p>
    <p>S.B.</p>
   </div>
   <div type="liminal">
    <head>THE DWELLER ALONE</head>
    <quote>
     <l>My Self has grown too mad for me to master.</l>
     <l>Craven, beyond what comfort I can find,</l>
     <l>It cries: "Oh, God, I am stricken with disaster."</l>
     <l>Cries in the night: "I am stricken, I am blind...."</l>
     <l>I will divorce it. I will make my dwelling</l>
     <l>Far from my Self. Not through these hind'ring tears</l>
     <l>Will I see men's tears shed. Not with these ears</l>
     <l>Will I hear news that tortures in the telling.</l>
     <l>I will go seeking for my soul's remotest</l>
     <l>And stillest place. For oh, I starve and thirst</l>
     <l>To hear in quietness man's passionate protest</l>
     <l>Against the doom with which his world is cursed.</l>
     <l>Not my own wand'rings — not my own abidings — </l>
     <l>Shall give my search a bias and a bent.</l>
     <l>For me is no light moment of content,</l>
     <l>For me no friend, no teller of the tidings.</l>
     <l>The waves of endless time do sing and thunder</l>
     <l>Upon the cliffs of space. And on that sea</l>
     <l>I will sail forth, nor fear to sink thereunder,</l>
     <l>Immeasurable time supporting me:</l>
     <l>That sea — that mother of a million summers,</l>
     <l>Who bore, with melody, a million springs,</l>
     <l>Shall sing for my enchantment, as she sings</l>
     <l>To life's forsaken ones, and death's newcomers.</l>
     <l>Look, yonder stand the stars to banish anger,</l>
     <l>And there the immortal years do laugh at pain,</l>
     <l>And here is promise of a blessed languor</l>
     <l>To smooth at last the seas of time again.</l>
     <l>And all those mothers' sons who did recover</l>
     <l>From death, do cry aloud: "Ah, cease to mourn us.</l>
     <l>To life and love you claimed that you had borne us,</l>
     <l>But we have found death kinder than a lover."</l>
     <l>I will divorce my Self. Alone it searches</l>
     <l>Amid dark ruins for its yesterday;</l>
     <l>Beats with its hands upon the doors of churches,</l>
     <l>And, at their altars, finds it cannot pray.</l>
     <l>But I am free — I am free of indecision,</l>
     <l>Of blood, and weariness, and all things cruel.</l>
     <l>I have sold my Self for silence, for the jewel</l>
     <l>Of silence, and the shadow of a vision....</l>
    </quote>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>
     <pb n="1"/>CHAPTER I</head>
    <head>MAGIC COMES TO A COMMITTEE</head>
    <p>
     <pb n="2"/>
     <pb n="3"/>There were six women, seven chairs, and a table in an otherwise unfurnished room in
     an unfashionable part of London. Three of the women were of the kind that has no life apart
     from committees. They need not be mentioned in detail. The names of two others were Miss Meta
     Mostyn Ford and Lady Arabel Higgins. Miss Ford was a good woman, as well as a lady. Her hands
     were beautiful because they paid a manicurist to keep them so, but she was too righteous to
     powder her nose. She was the sort of person a man would like his best friend to marry. Lady
     Arabel was older: she was virtuous to the same extent as Achilles was invulnerable. In the
     beginning, when her soul was being soaked in virtue, the heel of it was fortunately left dry.
     She had a husband, but no apparent tragedy in her life. These two women were obviously
     <pb n="4"/>not native to their surroundings. Their eyelashes brought Bond Street — or at least
     Kensington — to mind; their shoes were mudless; their gloves had not been bought in the sales.
     Of the sixth woman the less said the better.</p>
    <p>All six women were there because their country was at war, and because they felt it to be
     their duty to assist it to remain at war for the present. They were the nucleus of a committee
     on War Savings, and they were waiting for their Chairman, who was the Mayor of the borough. He
     was also a grocer.</p>
    <p>Five of the members were discussing methods of persuading poor people to save money. The
     sixth was making spots on the table with a pen.</p>
    <p>They were interrupted, not by the expected Mayor, but by a young woman, who came violently in
     by the street door, rushed into the middle of the room, and got under the table. The members,
     in surprise, pushed back their chairs and made ladylike noises of protest and inquiry.</p>
    <p>"They're after me," panted the person under the table.
     <pb n="5"/></p>
    <p>All seven listened to thumping silence for several seconds, and then, as no pursuing outcry
     declared itself, the Stranger arose, without grace, from her hiding-place.</p>
    <p>To anybody except a member of a committee it would have been obvious that the Stranger was of
     the Cinderella type, and bound to turn out a heroine sooner or later. But perception goes out
     of committees. The more committees you belong to, the less of ordinary life you will
     understand. When your daily round becomes nothing more than a daily round of committees you
     might as well be dead.</p>
    <p>The Stranger was not pretty; she had a broad, curious face. Her clothes were much too good to
     throw away. You would have enjoyed giving them to a decayed gentlewoman.</p>
    <p>"I stole this bun," she explained frankly. "There is an uninterned German baker after
     me."</p>
    <p>"And why did you steal it?" asked Miss Ford, pronouncing the H in "why" with a haughty and
     terrifying sound of suction.</p>
    <p>The Stranger sighed. "Because I couldn't afford to buy it."
     <pb n="6"/></p>
    <p>"And why could you not afford to buy the bun?" asked Miss Ford. "A big strong girl like
     you."</p>
    <p>You will notice that she had had a good deal of experience in social work.</p>
    <p>The Stranger said: "Up till ten o'clock this morning I was of the leisured classes like
     yourselves. I had a hundred pounds."</p>
    <p>Lady Arabel was one of the kindest people in the world, but even she quivered at the
     suggestion of a common leisure. The sort of clothes the Stranger wore Lady Arabel would have
     called "too dretful." If one is well dressed one is proud, and may look an angel in the eye. If
     one is really shabby one is even prouder, one often goes out of one's way to look angels in the
     eye. But if one wears a squirrel fur "set," and a dyed dress that originally cost two and a
     half guineas, one is damned.</p>
    <p>"You have squandered all that money?" pursued Miss Ford.</p>
    <p>"Yes. In ten minutes."</p>
    <p>A thrill ran through all six members. Several mouths watered.</p>
    <p>"I am ashamed of you," said Miss Ford.
     <pb n="7"/> "I hope the baker will catch you. Don't you know that your country is engaged in
     the greatest conflict in history? A hundred pounds ... you might have put it in the War
     Loan."</p>
    <p>"Yes," said the Stranger, "I did. That's how I squandered it."</p>
    <p>Miss Ford seemed to be partially drowned by this reply. One could see her wits fighting for
     air.</p>
    <p>But Lady Arabel had not committed herself, and therefore escaped this disaster. "You behaved
     foolishly," she said. "We are all too dretfully anxious to subscribe what we can spare to the
     War Loan, of course. But the State does not expect more than that of us."</p>
    <p>"God bless it," said the Stranger loudly, so that everybody blushed. "Of course it doesn't.
     But it is fun, don't you think, when you are giving a present, to exceed expectations?"</p>
    <p>"The State — " began Lady Arabel, but was nudged into silence by Miss Ford. "Of course it's
     all untrue. Don't let her think we believe her."
     <pb n="8"/></p>
    <p>The Stranger heard her. Such people do not only hear with their ears. She laughed.</p>
    <p>"You shall see the receipt," she said.</p>
    <p>Out of her large pocket she dragged several things before she found what she sought. The
     sixth member noticed several packets labelled MAGIC, which the Stranger handled very carefully.
     "Frightfully explosive," she said.</p>
    <p>"I believe you're drunk," said Miss Ford, as she took the receipt. It really was a War Loan
     receipt, and the name and address on it were: "Miss Hazeline Snow, The Bindles, Pymley,
     Gloucestershire."</p>
    <p>Lady Arabel smiled in a relieved way. She had not long been a social worker, and had not yet
     acquired a taste for making fools of the undeserving. "So this is your name and address," she
     said.</p>
    <p>"No," said the Stranger simply.</p>
    <p>"This is your name and address," said Lady Arabel more loudly.</p>
    <p>"No," said the Stranger. "I made it up. Don't you think 'The Bindles, Pymley,' is too
     darling?"
     <pb n="9"/></p>
    <p>"Quite drunk," repeated Miss Ford. She had attended eight committee meetings that week.</p>
    <p>"S — s — s — sh, Meta," hissed Lady Arabel. She leaned forward, not smiling, but pleasantly
     showing her teeth. "You gave a false name and address. My dear, I wonder if I can guess
     why."</p>
    <p>"I dare say you can," admitted the Stranger. "It's such fun, don't you think, to get no
     thanks? Don't you sometimes amuse yourself by sending postal orders to people whose addresses
     look pathetic in the telephone book, or by forgetting to take away the parcels you have bought
     in poor little shops? Or by standing and looking with ostentatious respect at boy scouts on the
     march, always bearing in mind that these, in their own eyes, are not little boys trotting
     behind a disguised curate, but British Troops on the Move? Just two pleased eyes in a crowd,
     just a hundred pounds dropped from heaven into poor Mr. Bonar Law's wistful hand...."</p>
    <p>Miss Ford began to laugh, a ladylike yet nasty laugh. "You amuse me," she said,
     <pb n="10"/>but not in the kind of way that would make anybody wish to amuse her often.</p>
    <p>Miss Ford was the ideal member of committee, and a committee, of course, exists for the
     purpose of damping enthusiasms.</p>
    <p>The Stranger's manners were somehow hectic. Directly she heard that laughter the tears came
     into her eyes. "Didn't you like what I was saying?" she asked. Tears climbed down her
     cheekbones.</p>
    <p>"Oh!" said Miss Ford. "You seem to be — if not drunk — suffering from some form of
     hysteria."</p>
    <p>"Do you think youth is a form of hysteria?" asked the Stranger. "Or hunger? Or magic? Or —
     "</p>
    <p>"Oh, don't recite any more lists, for the Dear Sake!" implored Miss Ford, who had caught this
     rather pretty expression where she caught her laugh and most of her thoughts — from
     contemporary fiction. She had a lot of friends in the writing trade. She knew artists too, and
     an actress, and a lot of people who talked. She very nearly did something clever herself. She
     continued: "I wish you could see yourself, trying to
     <pb n="11"/>be uplifting between the munches of a stolen bun. You'd laugh too. But perhaps you
     never laugh," she added, straightening her lips.</p>
    <p>"How d'you mean — laugh?" asked the Stranger. "I didn't know that noise was called laughing.
     I thought you were just saying 'Ha — ha.'"</p>
    <p>At this moment the Mayor came in. As I told you, he was a grocer, and the Chairman of the
     committee. He was a bad Chairman, but a good grocer. Grocers generally wear white in the
     execution of their duty, and this fancy, I think, reflects their pureness of heart. They spend
     their days among soft substances most beautiful to touch; and sometimes they sell
     honest-smelling soaps; and sometimes they chop cheeses, and thus reach the glory of the
     butcher's calling, without its painfulness. Also they handle shining tins, marvellously
     illustrated.</p>
    <p>Mayors and grocers were of course nothing to Miss Ford, but Chairmen were very important. She
     nodded curtly to the Mayor and grocer, but she pushed the seventh chair towards the Chairman.
     <pb n="12"/></p>
    <p>"May I just finish with this applicant?" she asked in her thin inclusive committee voice, and
     then added in the direction of the Stranger: "It's no use talking nonsense. We all see through
     you, you cannot deceive a committee. But to a certain extent we believe your story, and are
     willing, if the case proves satisfactory, to give you a helping hand. I will take down a few
     particulars. First your name?"</p>
    <p>"M — m," mused the Stranger. "Let me see, you didn't like Hazeline Snow much, did you? What
     d'you think of Thelma ... Thelma Bennett Watkins?... You know, the Rutlandshire Watkinses, the
     younger branch — — "</p>
    <p>Miss Ford balanced her pen helplessly. "But that isn't your real name."</p>
    <p>"How d'you mean — real name?" asked the Stranger anxiously. "Won't that do? What about Iris
     ... Hyde?... You see, the truth is, I was never actually christened ... I was born a
     conscientious objector, and also — — "</p>
    <p>"Oh, for the Dear Sake, be silent!" said Miss Ford, writing down "Thelma Bennett
     <pb n="13"/> Watkins," in self-defence. "This, I take it, is the name you gave at the time of
     the National Registration."</p>
    <p>"I forget," said the Stranger. "I remember that I put down my trade as Magic, and they
     registered it on my card as 'Machinist.' Yet Magic, I believe, is a starred profession."</p>
    <p>"What is your trade really?" asked Miss Ford.</p>
    <p>"I'll show you," replied the Stranger, unbuttoning once more the flap of her pocket.</p>
    <p>She wrote a word upon the air with her finger, and made a flourish under the word. So flowery
     was the flourish that it span her round, right round upon her toes, and she faced her watchers
     again. The committee jumped, for the blind ran up, and outside the window, at the end of a
     strange perspective of street, the trees of some far square were as soft as thistledown against
     a lemon-coloured sky. A sound came up the street....</p>
    <p>The forgotten April and the voices of lambs pealed like bells into the room....
     <pb n="14"/></p>
    <p>Oh, let us flee from April! We are but swimmers in seas of words, we members of committees,
     and to the song of April there are no words. What do we know, and what does London know, after
     all these years of learning?</p>
    <p>Old Mother London crouches, with her face buried in her hands; and she is walled in with her
     fogs and her loud noises, and over her head are the heavy beams of her dark roof, and she has
     the barred sun for a skylight, and winds that are but hideous draughts rush under her door.
     London knows much, and every moment she learns a new thing, but this she shall never learn —
     that the sun shines all day and the moon all night on the silver tiles of her dark house, and
     that the young months climb her walls, and run singing in and out between her chimneys....</p>
    <p>Nothing else happened in that room. At least nothing more important than the ordinary
     manifestations attendant upon magic. The lamp had tremulously gone out. Coloured flames danced
     about the
     <pb n="15"/> Stranger's head. One felt the thrill of a purring cat against one's ankles, one
     saw its green eyes glare. But these things hardly counted.</p>
    <p>It was all over. The Mayor was heard cracking his fingers, and whispering "Puss, Puss." The
     lamp relighted itself. Nobody had known that it was so gifted.</p>
    <p>The Mayor said: "Splendid, miss, quite splendid. You'd make a fortune on the stage." His
     tongue, however, seemed to be talking by itself, without the assistance of the Mayor himself.
     One could see that he was shaken out of his usual grocerly calm, for his feverish hand was
     stroking a cat where no cat was.</p>
    <p>Black cats are only the showy properties of magic, easily materialised, even by beginners, at
     will. It must be confusing for such an orderly animal as the cat to exist in this intermittent
     way, never knowing, so to speak, whether it is there or not there, from one moment to
     another.</p>
    <p>The sixth member took a severely bitten pen from between her lips, and said: "Now you mention
     it, I think I'll go down there
     <pb n="16"/>again for the week-end. I can pawn my ear-rings."</p>
    <p>Nobody of course took any notice of her, yet in a way her remark was logical. For that
     singing Spring that had for a moment trespassed in the room had reminded her of very familiar
     things, and for a few seconds she had stood upon a beloved hill, and had looked down between
     beech trees on a far valley, like a promised land; and had seen in the valley a pale river and
     a dark town, like milk and honey.</p>
    <p>As for Miss Ford, she had become rather white. Although the blind had now pulled itself down,
     and dismissed April, Miss Ford continued to look at the window. But she cleared her throat and
     said hoarsely: "Will you kindly answer my questions? I asked you what your trade was."</p>
    <p>"It's too dretful of me to interrupt," said Lady Arabel suddenly. "But, do you know, Meta, I
     feel we are wasting this committee's time. This young person needs no assistance from us." She
     turned to the Stranger, and added: "My dear, I am dretfully ashamed. You must meet
     <pb n="17"/>my son Rrchud.... My son Rrchud knows...."</p>
    <p>She burst into tears.</p>
    <p>The Stranger took her hand.</p>
    <p>"I should like awfully to meet Rrchud, and to get to know you better," she said. She grew
     very red. "I say, I should be awfully pleased if you would call me Angela."</p>
    <p>It wasn't her name, but she had noticed that something of this sort is always said when
     people become motherly and cry.</p>
    <p>Then she went away.</p>
    <p>"Lawdy," said the Mayor. "I didn't expect she'd go out by the door, somehow. Look — she's
     left some sort of hardware over there in the corner."</p>
    <p>It was a broomstick.
     <pb n="18"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>
     <pb n="19"/>CHAPTER II</head>
    <head>THE COMMITTEE COMES TO MAGIC</head>
    <p>
     <pb n="20"/>
     <pb n="21"/>I don't suppose for a moment that you know Mitten Island: it is a difficult place
     to get to; you have to change 'buses seven times, going from Kensington, and you have to cross
     the river by means of a ferry. On Mitten Island there is a model village, consisting of several
     hundred houses, two churches, and one shop.</p>
    <p>It was the sixth member who discovered, after the committee meeting, that the address on the
     forsaken broomstick's collar was: Number 100 Beautiful Way, Mitten Island, London.</p>
    <p>The sixth member, although she was a member of committees, was neither a real expert in, nor
     a real lover of, Doing Good. In Doing Good, I think, we have got into bad habits. We try in
     groups to do good to the individual, whereas, if good is to be done, it would seem more likely,
     and more consonant with precedent, that the
     <pb n="22"/>individual might do it to the group. Without the smile of a Treasurer we cannot
     unloose our purse-strings; without the sanction of a Chairman we have no courage; without
     Minutes we have no memory. There is hardly one of us who would dare to give a flannelette
     nightgown to a Factory Girl who had Stepped Aside, without a committee to lay the blame on,
     should the Factory Girl, fortified by the flannelette nightgown, take Further Steps Aside.</p>
    <p>The sixth member was only too apt to put her trust in committees. Herself she did not trust
     at all, though she thought herself quite a good creature, as selves go. She had come to London
     two years ago, with a little trunk and a lot of good intentions as her only possessions, and
     she had paid the inevitable penalty for her earnestness. It is a sad thing to see any one of
     naturally healthy and rebellious tendency stray into the flat path of Charity. Gay heedless
     young people set their unwary feet between the flowery borders of that path, the thin air of
     resigned thanks breathed by the deserving poor mounts to their heads
     <pb n="23"/>like wine; committees lie in wait for them on every side; hostels and settlements
     entice them fatally to break their journey at every mile; they run rejoicing to their doom, and
     I think shall eventually find themselves without escape, elected eternal life-members of the
     Committee that sits around the glassy sea.</p>
    <p>The sixth member was saved by a merciful inefficiency of temperament from attaining the
     vortex of her whirlpool of charity. To be in the vortex is, I believe, almost always to see
     less. The bull's eye is generally blind.</p>
    <p>The sixth member was a person who, where Social Work was concerned, did more or less as she
     was told, without doing it particularly well. The result, very properly, was that all the work
     which a committee euphemistically calls "organising work" was left to her. Organising work
     consists of sitting in 'buses bound for remote quarters of London, and ringing the bells of
     people who are almost always found to be away for a fortnight. The sixth member had been
     ordered to organise the return of the broomstick to its owner.
     <pb n="24"/></p>
    <p>Perhaps it would be more practical to call the sixth member Sarah Brown.</p>
    <p>The bereaved owner of the broomstick was washing her hair at Number 100 Beautiful Way, Mitten
     Island. She was washing it behind the counter of her shop. She was the manageress of the only
     shop on Mitten Island. It was a general shop, but made a speciality of such goods as Happiness
     and Magic. Unfortunately Happiness is rather difficult to get in war-time. Sometimes there was
     quite a queue outside the shop when it opened, and sometimes there was a card outside, saying
     politely: "Sorry, it's no use waiting. I haven't any." Of course the shop also sold Sunlight
     Soap, and it was with Sunlight Soap that the shop-lady was washing her hair, because it was
     Sunday, and this was a comparatively cheap amusement. She had no money. She had meant to go
     down to the offices of her employer after breakfast, to borrow some of the salary that would be
     due to her next week. But then she found that she had left her broomstick somewhere. As a rule
     Harold — for that was the broomstick's
     <pb n="25"/>name — was fairly independent, and could find his way home alone, but when he got
     mislaid and left in strange hands, and particularly when kindly finders took him to Scotland
     Yard, he often lost his head. You, in your innocence, are suggesting that his owner might have
     borrowed another broomstick from stock. But you have no idea what arduous work it is, breaking
     in a wild broomstick to the saddle. It sometimes takes days, and is not really suitable work
     for a woman, even in war-time. Often the brutes are savage, and always they are obstinate. The
     shop-lady could not afford to go to the City by Tube, not to mention the ferry fare, which was
     rather expensive and erratic, not being L.C.C. Of course a flash of lightning is generally
     available for magic people. But it is considered not only unpatriotic but bad form to use
     lightning in war-time.</p>
    <p>The shop was not expecting customers on Sunday, but its manageress had hardly got her head
     well into the basin when somebody entered. She stood up dripping.</p>
    <p>"Is Miss Thelma Bennett Watkins at
     <pb n="26"/>home?" asked Sarah Brown, after a pause, during which she made her characteristic
     effort to remember what she had come for.</p>
    <p>"No," said the other. "But do take a seat. We met last night, you may remember. Perhaps you
     wouldn't mind lending me one-and-twopence to buy two chops for our luncheon. I've got an extra
     coupon. There's tinned salmon in stock, but I don't advise it."</p>
    <p>"I've only got sevenpence, just enough to take me home," answered Sarah Brown. "But I can
     pawn my ear-rings."</p>
    <p>I dare say you have never been in a position to notice that there is no pawn-shop on Mitten
     Island. The inhabitants of model villages always have assured incomes and pose as lilies of the
     field. Sarah Brown and her hostess sat down on the counter without regret to a luncheon
     consisting of one orange, found by the guest in her bag and divided, and two thin captain
     biscuits from stock. They were both used to dissolving visions of impossible chops, both were
     cheerfully familiar with the feeling of light tragedy which invades you towards six
     <pb n="27"/>o'clock P.M., if you have not been able to afford a meal since breakfast.</p>
    <p>"Now look here," said Sarah Brown, as she plunged her pocket-knife into the orange. "Would
     you mind telling me — are you a fairy, or a third-floor-back, or anything of that sort? I won't
     register it, or put it on the case-paper, I promise, though if you are superhuman in any way I
     shall be seriously tempted."</p>
    <p>"I am a Witch," said the witch.</p>
    <p>Now witches and wizards, as you perhaps know, are people who are born for the first time. I
     suppose we have all passed through this fair experience, we must all have had our chance of
     making magic. But to most of us it came in the boring beginning of time, and we wasted our best
     spells on plesiosauri, and protoplasms, and angels with flaming swords, all of whom knew magic
     too, and were not impressed. Witches and wizards are now rare, though not so rare as you think.
     Remembering nothing, they know nothing, and are not bored. They have to learn everything from
     the very beginning, except magic, which is the
     <pb n="28"/>only really original sin. To the magic eye, magic alone is commonplace, everything
     else is unknown, unguessed, and undespised. Magic people are always obvious — so obvious that
     we veteran souls can rarely understand them, — they are never subtle, and though they are new,
     they are never Modern. You may tell them in your cynical way that to-day is the only real day,
     and that there is nothing more unmentionable than yesterday except the day before. They will
     admire your cleverness very much, but the next moment you will find the witch sobbing over
     Tennyson, or the wizard smiling at the quaint fancies of Sir Edwin Landseer. You cannot really
     stir up magic people with ordinary human people. You and I have climbed over our thousand lives
     to a too dreadfully subtle eminence. In our day — in our many days — we have adored everything
     conceivable, and now we have to fall back on the inconceivable. We stand our idols on their
     heads, it is newer to do so, and we think we prefer them upside down. Talking constantly, we
     reel blindfold through eternity, and perhaps if
     <pb n="29"/>we are lucky, once or twice in a score of lives, the blindfolding handkerchief
     slips, and we wriggle one eye free, and see gods like trees walking. By Jove, that gives us
     enough to talk about for two or three lives! Witches and wizards are not blinded by having a
     Point of View. They just look, and are very much surprised and interested.</p>
    <p>All witches and wizards are born strangely and die violently. They are descended always from
     old mysterious breeds, from women who wrought domestic magic and perished for its sake, and
     from men who wrought other magic among lost causes and wars without gain, and fell and died,
     still surprised, still interested, with their faces among flowers. All men who die so are not
     wizards, nor are all martyred and adventuring women witches, but all such bring a potential
     strain of magic into their line.</p>
    <p>"A witch," said Sarah Brown. "Of course. I have been trying to remember what broomsticks
     reminded me of. A witch, of course. I have always wished to be friends with a witch."
     <pb n="30"/></p>
    <p>The witch was unaware that the proper answer to this was: "Oh, my Dear, <hi>do</hi> let's. Do
     you know I had quite a <hi>crush</hi> on you from the first minute." She did not answer at all,
     and Sarah Brown, who was tired of proper answers, was not sorry. Nevertheless the pause seemed
     a little empty, so she filled it herself, saying pedantically: "Of course I don't believe
     friendship is an end in itself. Only a means to an end."</p>
    <p>"I don't know what you mean," said the witch, after wrestling conscientiously with this
     remark for a minute. "Do tell me — do you know yourself, or are you just saying it to see what
     it means?"</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown was obviously damped by this, and the witch added kindly: "I bet you twopence you
     don't know what this place is."</p>
    <p>"A shop," said Sarah Brown, who was sitting on the counter.</p>
    <p>"It is a sort of convent and monastery mixed," replied the witch. "I am connected with it
     officially. I undertook to manage it, yet I forget what the proper word for me is. Not
     undertaker, is it?"
     <pb n="31"/></p>
    <p>"Superintendent or secretary," suggested Sarah Brown moodily.</p>
    <p>"Superintendent, I think," said the witch. "At least I know Peony calls me Soup. Do you live
     alone?"</p>
    <p>"Yes."</p>
    <p>"Then you ought to live here. This is the only place in the world of its kind. The name of
     this house is Living Alone. I'll read you the prospectus."</p>
    <p>She fell suddenly upon her knees and began fighting with a drawer. The drawer was evidently
     one of the many descendants of the Sword Excalibur — none but the appointed hand could draw it
     forth. The witch, after a struggle, passed this test, and produced a parchment covered with
     large childish printing in red ink.</p>
    <p>"My employer made up this," said the witch. "And the ferryman wrote it out for us."</p>
    <p>This is the prospectus:</p>
    <quote>
     <p>The name of this house is Living Alone.</p>
     <p>It is meant to provide for the needs of those who dislike hotels, clubs, settlements,
      hostels, boarding-houses, and lodgings only less than their own
      <pb n="32"/>homes; who detest landladies, waiters, husbands and wives, charwomen, and all
      forms of lookers after. This house is a monastery and a convent for monks and nuns dedicated
      to unknown gods. Men and women who are tired of being laboriously kind to their bodies, who
      like to be a little uncomfortable and quite uncared for, who love to live from week to week
      without speaking, except to confide their destinations to 'bus-conductors, who are weary of
      woolly decorations, aspidistras, and the eternal two generations of roses which riot among
      blue ribbons on hireling wall-papers, who are ignorant of the science of tipping and thanking,
      who do not know how to cook yet hate to be cooked for, will here find the thing they have
      desired, and something else as well.</p>
     <p>There are six cells in this house, and no common sitting-room. Guests wishing to address
      each other must do so on the stairs, or in the shop. Each cell has whitewashed walls, and
      contains a small deal table, one wooden chair, a hard bed, a tin bath, and a little
      inconvenient fireplace. No guest may bring into the house more than can be carried out again
      in one large suit-case. Carpets, rugs, mirrors, and any single garment costing more than three
      guineas, are prohibited. Any guest proved to have made use of a taxi, or to have travelled
      anywhere first class, or to have bought cigarettes or sweets costing more than
      <pb n="33"/>three shillings a hundred or eighteenpence a pound respectively, or to have paid
      more than three and sixpence (war-tax included) for a seat in any place of entertainment, will
      be instantly expelled. Dogs, cats, goldfish, and other superhuman companions are
      encouraged.</p>
     <p>Working guests are preferred, but if not at work, guests must spend at least eighteen hours
      out of the twenty-four entirely alone. No guest may entertain or be entertained except under
      special license obtainable from the Superintendent.</p>
     <p>There is a pump in the back yard. There is no telephone, no electric light, no hot water
      system, no attendance, and no modern comfort whatever. Tradesmen are forbidden to call. There
      is no charge for residence in this house.</p>
    </quote>
    <p>"It certainly sounds an unusual place," admitted Sarah Brown. "Is the house always full?"</p>
    <p>"Never," said the witch. "A lot of people can swallow everything but the last clause. We have
     at present one guest, called Peony."</p>
    <p>She replaced the prospectus in the drawer, which she then tried to shut. While she was
     engaged in this thundering endeavour, Sarah Brown noticed that the drawer was
     <pb n="34"/>full of the little paper packets which she had seen the day before in the witch's
     possession.</p>
    <p>"What do you do with your magic?" she asked.</p>
    <p>"Oh, many things. Chiefly I use it as an ingredient for happiness, sometimes to remind
     people, and sometimes to make them forget. It seems to me that some people take happiness
     rather tragically."</p>
    <p>"I find," said Sarah Brown, rather sententiously, "that I always owe my happiness to earth,
     never to heaven."</p>
    <p>"How d'you mean heaven?" said the witch. "I know nothing about heaven. When I used to work in
     the City, I bought a little book about heaven to read in the Tube every morning. I thought I
     should grow daily better. But I couldn't see that I did."</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown was naturally astonished to meet any one who did not know all about heaven. But
     she continued the pursuit of her ideas on happiness. Sarah Brown meant to write a book some
     day, if she could find a really inspiring exercise-book to start
     <pb n="35"/>in. She thought herself rather good at ideas — poor Sarah Brown, she simply had to
     be confident about something. She was only inwardly articulate, I think, not outwardly at all,
     but sometimes she could talk about herself.</p>
    <p>"Heaven has given me wretched health, but never gave me youth enough to make the wretchedness
     adventurous," she went on. "Heaven gave me a thin skin, but never gave me the natural and
     comforting affections. Heaven probably meant to make a noble woman of me by encrusting me in
     disabilities, but it left out the necessary nobility at the last moment; it left out, in fact,
     all the compensations. But luckily I have found the compensations for myself; I just had to
     find something. Men and women have given me everything that such as I could expect. I have
     never met with reasonless enmity, never met with meanness, never met with anything more
     unbearable than natural indifference, from any man or woman. I have been, I may say, a burden
     and a bore all over the world; I have been an ill and fretful stranger within all men's
     <pb n="36"/>gates; I have asked much and given nothing; I have never been a friend. Nobody has
     ever expected any return from me, yet nothing was grudged. Landladies, policemen, chorus girls,
     social bounders, prostitutes, the natural enemies, one would say, of such as I, have given me
     kindness, and often much that they could not easily spare, and always amusement and
     distraction...."</p>
    <p>"Ah, how you interest and excite me," said the witch, whose attention had been frankly
     wandering. "You are exactly the sort of person we want in this house."</p>
    <p>"But — ill?" said Sarah Brown pessimistically. "Oh, witch, I have been so wearisome to every
     one, so constantly ill. The first thing I get to know about a new hostess or a landlady is
     always the colour of her dressing-gown by candlelight, or whether she has one."</p>
    <p>"Illnesses are never bad here," said the witch. "I bet you twopence I've got something in the
     shop that would make you well. Three fingers of happiness, neat and hot, at night — "</p>
    <p>"But, witch — oh, witch — this is the worst
     <pb n="37"/>of all. My ears are failing me — I think I am going deaf...."</p>
    <p>"You can hear what I say," said the witch.</p>
    <p>"Yes, I can hear what you say, but when most people talk I am like a prisoner locked up; and
     every day there are more and more locked doors between me and the world. You do not know how
     horrible it is."</p>
    <p>"Oh, well," said the witch, "as long as you can hear magic you will not lack a key to your
     prison. Sometimes it's better not to hear the other things. You are the ideal guest for the
     House of Living Alone."</p>
    <p>"I'll go and fetch David my Dog and Humphrey my Suit-case," said Sarah Brown.</p>
    <p>At that moment a taxi was heard to arrive at the other side of the ferry, and the ferryman's
     voice was heard shouting: "All right, all right, I'll be there in half a tick."</p>
    <p>"I hope this isn't Peony in a taxi," said the witch. "I get so tired of expelling guests.
     She's been drawing her money, which may have been tempting."</p>
    <p>They listened.</p>
    <p>They heard someone alight from the
     <pb n="38"/>ferry-boat, and the voice of Miss Meta Mostyn Ford asking the ferryman: "Do you
     know anything about a young woman of the name of Watkins, living at Number 100 Beautiful Way —
     — "</p>
    <p>"No, he doesn't," shouted the witch, opening the shop door. "But do step in. We met
     yesterday, you may remember. I'll ask the ferryman to get half-a-dozen halfpenny buns for tea,
     if you will be so kind as to lend me threepence. We don't bake ourselves."</p>
    <p>"I have had tea, thank you," said Miss Ford. "I have just come from a little gathering of
     friends on the other side of the river, and I thought I would call here on my way home. I had
     noted your address — — "</p>
    <p>She started as she came in and saw Sarah Brown, and added in her committee voice: "I had
     noted your address, because I never mind how much trouble I take in following up a promising
     case."</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown, on first hearing that trenchant voice, had lost her head and begun to hide under
     the counter. But the biscuit-
     <pb n="39"/>tins refused to make room, so she drew herself up and smiled politely.</p>
    <p>"How good of you to go to a little gathering of friends," said the witch, obviously trying to
     behave like a real human person. "I never do, except now and then by mistake. And even then I
     only stay when there are grassy sandwiches to eat. Once there were grassy sandwiches mixed with
     bits of hard-boiled egg, and then I stayed to supper. You didn't have such luck, I see, or you
     would look happier."</p>
    <p>"I don't go to my friends for their food, but for their ideas," said Miss Ford.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown was gliding towards the door.</p>
    <p>"Oh, don't go," said the witch, who did not recognise tact when she met it. "I have sent
     Harold the Broomstick for your Dog David and your Suit-case Humphrey. He is an excellent packer
     and very clean in his person and work. Please, please, don't go. Do you know, I live in
     constant dread of being left alone with a clever person."</p>
    <p>"I must apologise for my intrusion, in that case," said Miss Ford, with dignity.
     <pb n="40"/> "I repeat, I only came because I saw yours was an exceptional case."</p>
    <p>There was a very long silence in the growing dusk. The moon could already be seen through the
     glass door, rising, pushing vigorously aside the thickets of the crowded sky. A crack across
     the corner of the glass was lighted up, and looked like a little sprig of lightning, plucked
     from a passing storm and preserved in the glass.</p>
    <p>Miss Ford suddenly began to talk in a very quick and confused way. Any sane hearer would have
     known that she was talking by mistake, that she was possessed by some distressingly Anti-Ford
     spirit, and that nothing she might say in parenthesis like this ought to be remembered against
     her.</p>
    <p>"Oh, God," said Miss Ford, "I have come because I am hungry, hungry for what you spoke of
     last night, in the dark.... You spoke of an April sea — clashing of cymbals was the expression
     you used, wasn't it? You spoke of a shore of brown diamonds flat to the ruffled sea ... and
     <pb n="41"/>white sandhills under a thin veil of grass ... and tamarisks all blown one
     way...."</p>
    <p>"Well?" said the witch.</p>
    <p>"Well," faltered Miss Ford. "I think I came to ask you ... whether you knew of nice lodgings
     there ... plain wholesome bath ... respectable cooking, hot and cold ..."</p>
    <p>Her voice faded away pathetically.</p>
    <p>There was a sudden shattering, as the door burst open, and a dog and a suit-case were swept
     in by a brisk broomstick.</p>
    <p>"I am so sorry, Miss Watkins," said Miss Ford stiffly. Her face was scarlet — neat and formal
     again now, but scarlet. — "I am so sorry if I have talked nonsense. I am rather run down, I
     think, too much work, four important meetings yesterday. I sometimes think I shall break down.
     I have such alarming nerve-storms."</p>
    <p>She looked nervously at Sarah Brown. It is always tiresome to meet fellow-members of
     committees in private life, especially if one is in a mood for having nerve-storms. People may
     be excellent in a philanthropic way, of course, and yet impossible socially.
     <pb n="42"/></p>
    <p>But Sarah Brown had heard very little. She always found Miss Ford's voice difficult. She was
     on her knees asking her dog David what it had felt like, coming. But David was still too much
     dazed to say much.</p>
    <p>"You must not think," said Miss Ford, "that because I am a practical worker I have no
     understanding of Inner Meanings. On the contrary, I have perhaps wasted too much of my time on
     spiritual matters. That is why I take quite a personal and special interest in your case. I had
     a great friend, now in the trenches, alas, who possessed Power. He used to come to my
     Wednesdays — at least I used to invite him to come, but he was dreamy like you and constantly
     mistook the date. He helped me enormously, and I miss him.... Well, the truest charity should
     be anything but formal, I think, and I saw at a glance that your case was exceptional, and that
     you also were Occult — — "</p>
    <p>"How d'you mean — occult?" asked the witch. "Do you mean just knowing magic?"</p>
    <p>"A strange mixture," mused Miss Ford
     <pb n="43"/>self-consciously. It is impossible to muse aloud without self-consciousness. "A
     strange and rather interesting mixture of naïveté and power. The question is — power to what
     extent? Miss Watkins, I want you to come to one of my Wednesdays to meet one or two people who
     might possibly help you to a job — lecturing, you know. Lectures on hypnotism or spiritualism,
     with experiments, are always popular. You certainly have Power, you only want a little
     advertisement to be a real help to many people."</p>
    <p>"How d'you mean — advertisement?" asked the witch. "This new advertisement stunt is one of
     the problems that tire my head. I am awfully worried by problems. The world seems to be ruled
     by posters now. People look to the hoardings for information about their duty. Why don't we
     paste up the ten commandments on all the walls and all the 'buses, and be done with it?"</p>
    <p>"Now listen, Miss Watkins," persisted Miss Ford. "I want you to meet Bernard Tovey, the
     painter, and Ivy MacBee, who founded the Aspiration Club, and Frere, the editor of <hi>I
      Wonder</hi>, and several other
     <pb n="44"/>regular Wednesday friends of mine, all interested in the Occult. It would be a real
     opportunity for you."</p>
    <p>"I am afraid you will be very angry with me," said the witch presently in a hollow voice. "If
     I was occult last night — I'm awfully sorry, but it must have been a fluke. I seem to have said
     so much last night without knowing it. I'm afraid I was showing off a little."</p>
    <p>The painful tears of confession were in her eyes, but she added, changing the subject: "Do
     you live alone?"</p>
    <p>"Yes, absolutely," said Miss Ford. "My friends call me a perfect hermit. I hardly ever have
     visitors in my spare room, it makes so much work for my three maids."</p>
    <p>"I suppose you wouldn't care to divorce your three maids and come and live here," suggested
     the witch. "I could of course cure you of the nerve-storms you speak of. Or rather I could help
     you to have nerve-storms all the time, without any stagnant grown-upness in between. Then you
     wouldn't notice the nerve-storms. This
     <pb n="45"/>house is a sort of nursing home and college combined. I'll read you the
     prospectus."</p>
    <p>"Very amusing," said Miss Ford, after waiting a minute to see if there was any more of the
     prospectus. She had quite recovered herself, and was wearing the brisk acute expression that
     deceived her into claiming a sense of humour. "But why all those uncomfortable rules? And why
     that discouragement of social intercourse? I am afraid the average person of the class you
     cater for does not recognise the duty of social intercourse."</p>
    <p>"This house," replied the witch, "caters for people who are outside averages. The ferryman
     says that people who are content to be average are lowering the general standard. I wish you
     could have met Peony, the only guest up to now, but she is out, and may be a teeny bit drunk
     when she comes in. She has gone to draw her money."</p>
    <p>"What sort of money?" asked Miss Ford, who was always interested in the sources of income of
     the Poor.
     <pb n="46"/></p>
    <p>"Soldier's allotment. Unmarried wife."</p>
    <p>The expression of Miss Ford's face tactfully wiped away this bald unfortunate statement from
     the surface of the conversation. "And how do you make your boarding-house pay," she asked, "if
     there is no charge for residence?"</p>
    <p>"How d'you mean — pay?" asked the witch. "Pay whom? And what with? Look here, if you will
     come and live here you shall have a little Wednesday every week on the stairs, under license
     from me. Harold the Broomstick is apt to shirk cleaning the stairs, but as it happens, he is
     keeping company with an O-Cedar Mop in Kentish Town, and I've no doubt she would come over and
     do the stairs thoroughly every Tuesday night. Besides, we have overalls in stock at only two
     and eleven three — — "</p>
    <p>"Oh, I like your merry mood," said Miss Ford, laughing heartily. "You must remember to talk
     like that when you come to my Wednesdays. Most of my friends are utter Socialists, and believe
     in bridging as far as possible the gulf between
     <pb n="47"/>one class and another, so you needn't feel shy or awkward."</p>
    <p>The splashing of the ferry-boat was once more heard, and then the shop quaked a little as a
     heavy foot alighted on the landing-stage. The ferryman was heard saying: "I don't know any
     party of that name, but I believe the young woman at the shop can help you."</p>
    <p>Lady Arabel Higgins entered the shop.</p>
    <p>"What, Meta, you here? And Sarah Brown? What a too dretfully funny coincidence. Well, Angela
     dear, I made a note of your address yesterday, and then lost the note — too dretfully like me.
     So I rang up the Mayor, and he said he also had made a note, and he would come and show me the
     way. But I didn't wait for him. I wanted to talk to you about — — "</p>
    <p>"Well, I must truly be going," interrupted Sarah Brown. "I'll just nip across to the Brown
     Borough and find a pawn-shop, being hungry."</p>
    <p>"There is no need for any one to move on my account," said Lady Arabel. "You all heard what
     Angela said last night in her
     <pb n="48"/>little address to the committee in the dark. I don't know why she addressed her
     remarks particularly at me, but as she did so, there is no secret in the matter. Of course,
     just at first, it seemed dretful to me that any one should know or speak about it. I cannot
     understand how you knew, Angela; I am trying not to understand...."</p>
    <p>She took up a thin captain biscuit and bit it absent-mindedly. It trembled in her hand like a
     leaf.</p>
    <p>"Yes, it is true that Rrchud isn't like other women's boys. You know it, Meta. Angela
     evidently knows it, and — at least since yesterday — I know that I know it. His not being able
     to read or write — I always knew in my heart that my old worn-out tag — 'We can't all be
     literary geniuses' — didn't meet the case. His way of disappearing and never explaining.... Do
     you know, I have only once seen him with other boys, doing the same as other boys, and that was
     when I saw him marching with hundreds of real boys ... in 1914.... It was the happiest day I
     ever had, I thought after all that I had borne a real boy. Well,
     <pb n="49"/>then, as you know, he couldn't get a commission, couldn't even get his stripe, poor
     darling. He deserted twice — pure absence of mind — it was always the same from a child — 'I
     wanted to see further,' he'd say, and of course worse in the trenches. Why, you know it all,
     Angela dear — at least, perhaps not quite all. I should like to tell you — because you said
     that about the splendour of being the mother of Rrchud....</p>
    <p>"Pinehurst — my husband, he is a doctor, you know — had that same passion for seeing further.
     He was often ill in London. I said it was asthma, but he said it was not being able to see far
     enough. We were in America for Rrchud's birth, and Pinehurst insisted on going West. I took the
     precaution of having a good nurse with me. Pinehurst said the East was full of little
     obstacles, and people's eyes had sucked all the secrets out of the horizon, he said. I like
     Cape Cod, but he said there was always a wall of sea round those flat wet places. We stayed in
     a blacksmith's spare room on the desert of Wyoming, but even that
     <pb n="50"/>horizon seemed a little higher than we, and one clear day, in a pink sunrise, we
     saw something that might have been a dream, my dears, and might have been the Rockies.
     Pinehurst couldn't stand that, we pushed west — so tahsome. We climbed a little narrow track up
     a mountain, in a light buggy that a goldminer lent us. Oh, of course, you'll think us mad,
     Meta, but, do you know, we actually found the world's edge, a place with no horizon; we looked
     between ragged pine trees, and saw over the shoulders of great old violet mountains — we saw
     right down into the stars for ever.... There was a tower of rocks — rose-red rocks in sloping
     layers — sunny hot by day, my dears, and a great shelter by night. You know, the little dark
     clouds walk alone upon the mountain tops at sunset — as you said, Angela — they are like trees,
     and sometimes like faces, and sometimes like the shadows of little bent gipsies.... I used to
     look at the mountains and think: 'What am I about, to be so worried and so small, in sight of
     such an enormous storm of mountains under a gold sky?' I think
     <pb n="51"/>of those rocks often at night, standing just as we left them, all by themselves,
     under that unnatural moon, — it was an unnatural moon on the edge of the world there, — all by
     themselves, with no watching eyes to spoil them, as Pinehurst used to say, not even one's own
     eyes.... You'll say that adventure — my one adventure — was impossible, Meta. Yes, it was.
     Rrchud was an impossible boy, born on an impossible day, in an impossible place. Ah, my poor
     Rrchud.... My dears, I am talking dretful nonsense. We were mad. You'd have to know Pinehurst,
     really, to understand it. Ah, we can never find our mountain again. I can never forgive
     Pinehurst...."</p>
    <p>"You can never repay Pinehurst," said the witch.</p>
    <p>Lady Arabel did not seem to hear. For a long time there was nothing to be heard but Sarah
     Brown, murmuring to her Dog David. You must excuse her, and remember that she lived most
     utterly alone. She was locked inside herself, and the solitary barred window in her prison wall
     commanded only a view of the Dog David.
     <pb n="52"/></p>
    <p>Rrchud's mother said at last: "I really came to tell you that Rrchud came back on leave
     unexpectedly last night. Of course you must meet him — "</p>
    <p>"Rrchud home!" exclaimed Miss Ford. "How odd! I was just telling Miss Watkins about his
     Power, and how strongly she reminded me of him. Do tell him to keep Wednesday afternoon
     free."</p>
    <p>Lady Arabel, ignoring Miss Ford by mistake, said to the witch: "Will you come on Tuesday to
     tea or supper?"</p>
    <p>"Supper, please," said the witch instantly. Tact, I repeat, was a stranger to her, so she
     added: "I will bring Sarah Brown too. I bet you twopence she hasn't had a decent meal for
     days."</p>
    <p>And then the Mayor arrived. The witch saw at once that there was some secret understanding
     between him and her that she did not understand. Her magic escapades often left her in this
     position. However, she winked back hopefully. But she was not a skilled winker. Everybody —
     even the Dog David — saw her doing it, and Miss Ford looked a little offended.
     <pb n="53"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER III</head>
    <head>THE EVERLASTING BOY</head>
    <p>
     <pb n="54"/>
     <pb n="55"/>Mitten Island is a place of fine weather, its air is always like stained glass
     between you and perfection. Always you will find in the happy ways of Mitten Island a
     confidence that the worst is left behind, and that even the worst was not so very bad. You can
     afford to remember the winter, for even the winter was beautiful; you can smile in the sun and
     think of the grey flush that used to overspread the island under its urgent crises of snow, and
     it seems that always there was joy running quickly behind the storms, joy looking with the sun
     through a tall window in a cloud. Even the most dreadful curtain of a winter's day was always
     drawn up at sunset; its straight edge rose slowly, disclosing flaming space, and the dramatic
     figures of the two island churches, exulting and undying martyrs in the midst of flames.
     <pb n="56"/></p>
    <p>It is a place of fine weather, and this is a book of fine weather, a book written in Spring.
     I will not remember the winter and the rain. It was the Spring that brought Sarah Brown to
     Mitten Island, and the Spring that first showed her magic. It was the Spring that awoke her on
     her first morning in the House of Living Alone.</p>
    <p>She awoke because it was so beautiful outside, and because there was a beautiful day coming.
     You could see the day secretly making preparations behind a shining mist. She heard a sound of
     breathless singing, and the whipping of stirred grass in the garden, the sound of some one
     unbearably happy, dancing. Now there is hardly anything but magic abroad before seven o'clock
     in the morning. Only the disciples of magic like getting their feet wet, and being furiously
     happy on an empty stomach.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown went to her window. The newborn trembling slants of smoke went up from the houses
     of the island. There was a sky of that quiet design which suffices half a day unchanged. A
     garden of quite a good many yards lay behind the house;
     <pb n="57"/>it contained no potatoes or anything useful, only long, very green grass, and a may
     tree, and a witch dancing. The extraordinary music to which she was dancing was partly the
     braying of a neighbouring donkey, and partly her own erratic singing. She danced, as you may
     imagine, in a very far from grown-up way, rather like a baby that has thought of a new funny
     way of annoying its Nana; and she sang, too, like a child that inadvertently bursts into loud
     tuneless song, because it is morning and yet too early to get up. A little wandering of the
     voice, a little wandering of the feet.... The may tree in the middle of the garden seemed to be
     her partner. A small blot moved up and down the chequered trunk of the tree, and that was the
     shadow of a grey squirrel, watching the dancing. The squirrel wore the same fur as the
     two-and-a-half-guinea young lady wears, and sometimes it looked with a tilted head at the
     witch, and sometimes it buried its face in its hands and sat for a while shaken with secret
     laughter. There was certainly something more funny than beautiful about the witch's dancing.
     She
     <pb n="58"/>laughed herself most of the time. She was wearing a mackintosh, which was in itself
     rather funny, but her feet were bare.</p>
    <p>A voice broke in: "Good for you, cully."</p>
    <p>It was Sarah Brown's fellow-lodger leaning from her window.</p>
    <p>The squirrel rippled higher up the may tree.</p>
    <p>The pleasure of the thing broke like an eggshell. Sarah Brown turned back towards her bed. It
     was too early to get up. It was too late to go to sleep again. Eunice, her hot-water bottle,
     she knew, lay cold as a serpent to shock her feet if she returned. Besides, the Dog David was
     asleep on the middle of the counterpane, and she was too good a mother to wake him. There are a
     good many things to do when you find yourself awake too early. It is said that some people sit
     up and darn their stockings, but I refer now to ordinary people, not to angels. Utterly
     resourceless people find themselves reduced to reading the penny stamps on yesterday's letters.
     There is a good deal of food for thought on a penny stamp, but nothing
     <pb n="59"/>really uplifting. Some people I know employ this morning leisure in scrubbing their
     consciences clean, thus thriftily making room for the sins of the coming day. But Sarah Brown's
     conscience was dreadfully receptive, almost magnetic; little sins like smuts lay always deep
     upon it. There were a few regrettable seconds in every minute she lived, I think, though she
     never enjoyed the compensations attached to a really considerable sin. Anyway her conscience
     would have been a case for pumice-stone, and when she was happy she always tried to forget it.
     Yet she was not without a good many very small and unessential resources for sleepless moments.
     Often she wrote vague comments on matters with which she was not familiar, in an exercise-book,
     always eventually mislaid. She would awake from dear and unspeakable dreams full of hope, and
     tell herself stories about herself, trying on various lives and deaths like clothes. The result
     was never likely enough even to laugh at.</p>
    <p>To-day she had watched magic dancing in a mackintosh, and she was at a loss.</p>
    <p>There was a knock upon her door, and
     <pb n="60"/>a voice: "Hi, cocky, could you oblige me with a loan of a few 'alfpence for the
     milkman. I 'aven't a bean in me purse."</p>
    <p>"Nor have I," said Sarah Brown, opening the door. "But I can pawn — "</p>
    <p>"Ow, come awf it, Cuffbut," said the fellow-lodger. "This is a respectable 'ouse, more or
     less, and you ain't goin' out to pawn nothink in your py-jams. I'll owe it to the milkman
     again. Not but what I 'adn't p'raps better pay 'im after all. I got me money paid yesterday,
     on'y I 'ad thought to put it away for Elbert."</p>
    <p>"Are you Peony, the other lodger?"</p>
    <p>"Thet's right, dearie."</p>
    <p>Peony was not in her first youth, in fact she was comfortably into her second. Her voice was
     so beautiful that it almost made one shy, but her choice of language, tending as it did in the
     other direction, reassured one. She had fine eyes of an absolute grey, and dark hair parted in
     the middle and drawn down so as to make a triangle of a face which, left to itself, would have
     been square. Her teeth spoilt her; the gaps among them looked like the front row of
     <pb n="61"/>the stalls during the first scene of a revue, or the last scene of a play by
     Shakspere. On the whole, she looked like the duckling of the story, serenely conscious of a
     secret swanhood. She showed unnatural energy even in repose, and lived as though she had a taxi
     waiting at the door.</p>
    <p>"Who's Elbert?" asked Sarah Brown, and then wished she had not asked, for even without
     Peony's flush she should have guessed.</p>
    <p>"'Arf a mo, kiddie, till I get rid of the milkman. Come an' sit on the stairs, an' I'll tell
     you a tale. I like no end tellin' this tale."</p>
    <p>Harold the Broomstick was desultorily sweeping the stairs. He worked harder when first
     conscious of being watched, but seeing that they intended to stay there, on the top step, he
     made this the excuse to disappear indolently, leaving little heaps of dust on several of the
     lower steps.</p>
    <p>"I come across Elbert first when I was about eight an' twenty," said Peony, when Sarah Brown,
     in rather a loud dressing-gown, had taken her seat on the stairs beside her.
     <pb n="62"/> "Elbert was the ideel kid, an' me — nothing to speak of. Nothin' more than a lump
     o' mud, I use to say. All my life, if you'll believe me, cully, I've lived in mud — an' kep' me
     eye on the moon, so to say. I worked in a factory all day, makin' mud, as it were, for muddy
     Jews, an' every Saturday night I took 'ome twelve shillin's-worth o' mud to keep meself alive
     in a city o' mud until the Saturday after. But o' nights there was the moon, or else the stars,
     or else the sunset, an' anyway all the air between to look at. I 'ad a back room, 'igh up, and
     o' nights I use to sit an' breave there, an' look at the sky. Believe me, dearie, I was mad
     about breavin' — it was me only recreation, so to say. By Gawd, it's a fair wonder 'ow the sky
     an' the air keeps on above the mud, and 'ow we looks at it, an' breaves it, an' never pays no
     rent for it, when all's said an' done. There ain't never a penny put in the slot for the
     moonlight, when you come to think of it, yet still it all goes on. Well, in those days, I never
     spoke to a soul, an' 'ated everybody, an' I got very queer, queerer nor
     <pb n="63"/>many as is locked up in Claybury this minute. I got to thinkin' as 'ow there was a
     debt 'anging over us all, some'ow the sky seemed like a sort of upper floor to all our 'ouses,
     with the stars an' the moon for windows, an' it seemed like as if there did oughter be some
     rent to pay, though the Landlord was a reel gent and never pressed for it. There might be
     people 'oo lived among flowers in the sunlight, an', so to say, rented the parlour floor, but
     not me. I 'ad the upper floor, an' breaved the light o' the moon. As for flowers — bless you,
     I'd never 'ardly seen a flower stuck proper to the ground until a year ago. Well, dearie, I use
     to make believe as 'ow we'd all get a charnce, all to ourselves, to pay what we owed. Some
     people, I thought, runs away from the debt, an' some pays it in bad money, but, I ses to
     meself, if ever my charnce come, I'll pay it the very best I can. Lawd, 'ow I 'ated everybody
     in those days. It seemed like people was all rotten, an' as if all the churches an' all the
     cherities was the rottenest of all the lot. Well, then, dearie, Elbert blew in. You know what
     <pb n="64"/>kids is mostly like in the Brown Borough, but Elbert — 'e never was. Straight legs
     'e 'ad, an' never a chilblain nor a sore, an' a small up-lookin' face, an' yallery 'air — what
     you could see of it, for of course I always made 'im keep it nicely cropped to the pink. You
     never see sich a clean boy, you never see 'im but what 'e seemed to 'ave sponged 'is collar
     that minute, an' the little seat to 'is breeks always patched in the right colour, an' all. Yet
     'e wasn't one of them choir-boy kinds, 'e could 'ave 'is little game with the best of 'em, an'
     often kicked up no end of a row when we was playin' pretendin' games of a wet Sunday. 'E 'ad
     one little game 'e loved best of all — not marbles, it wasn't, nor peg-tops — but there, I
     won't tell you what it was, for you'd laugh like the gal at the shop did when I spoke of it. I
     don't often get talkin', but I'd 'ad a nip of brandy at the time. Laugh fit to bust, she did —
     'avin' 'ad a nip of the same 'erself — an' as't if Elbert wasn't blind as well, an' if 'e wore
     any clothes besides wings.... The funny thing was thet Elbert did 'ave bad sight, it always
     seemed odd to me thet with 'is
     <pb n="65"/>weak eyes 'e should choose to play the little game 'e did. I use to take 'im to the
     'Eath of a summer Sunday, an' 'e use to stand on them little ridges below the Spaniards Road,
     with 'is eyes shut against the sun, never botherin' to take no aim. I can see 'im now,
     a-pulling of the string of 'is bow — it 'ad an 'igh note, like the beginnin' of a bit o' music
     — an' then awf 'e'd go like a rebbit, to see where the arrer fell. It was always a marvel to me
     'e didn't put somebody's eye out, but I didn't mind — I 'ated everybody. 'E didn't live with
     me, 'e just came in an' out. 'E never tol' me 'is name was Elbert — I just called 'im thet, the
     prettiest name I knew. 'E never tol' me 'oo 'is people were; I shouldn't think they could 'ave
     bin Brown Borough people, for Elbert seemed to 'ave bin about a lot, seen mountains an' oceans
     an' sichlike, an' come acrost a lot of furriners — even Germans. 'E talked a lot about people —
     as good as a novelette 'is stories was, but bloody 'igh-flavoured. Children knows a lot in the
     Brown Borough. 'Ow 'e'd noticed the things 'e 'ad with them blindish eyes of
     <pb n="66"/> 'is, I don't know. I got to count on that boy no end. Fair drunk with
     satisfaction, I use to feel. Call me a fool if you like, cully, but it was three or four year
     before I got the idee that there was anythink funny about Elbert. It was when it begun to look
     as if the War 'ad come to stop, an' one couldn't look at any boy without countin' up to see 'ow
     long 'e 'ad before the Army copped 'im. An' then I calc'lated that Elbert should be rising
     fourteen now, an' I saw then thet 'e 'adn't grown an inch since I first see 'im, nor 'e hadn't
     changed 'is ways, but still 'e run about laughin', playin' 'is little kiddy-game, with 'is face
     to the sun. An' then I remembered 'ow often 'e'd tol' me things thet seemed too 'istorical for
     sich as 'im to come by honest, tales about blokes in 'istory — nanecdotes 'e'd use to pass
     acrost about Admiral Nelson, or Queen Bess — she use to make 'im chuckle, she did — an' a chap
     called Shilly or Shally, 'oo was drownded. An' I got struck all of an 'eap, to think 'e was
     some sort of an everlasting boy, an' p'raps 'e was a devil, I thought, an' p'raps I'd sold me
     soul without knowin' it. I never took
     <pb n="67"/>much stock of me soul, but I always 'ad that debt o' mine in me mind, an' I wanted
     to pay it clean. For them London mists agin the sky in the Spring, an' for the moonlight, an'
     for the sky just before a thunderstorm — all them things seemed to 'ave come out of the same
     box, like, an' I didn't like feelin' as 'ow they was all jest charity.... 'Owever, I got this
     idee about Elbert, an' I didn't sleep a wink thet night, an' couldn't enjoy me starlight. In
     the mornin' 'e come as usual, with 'is pretty blind smile, an' I ses to 'im: 'Elbert,' I ses,
     'You ain't a crool boy, are you? You wouldn't do anythink to 'urt me?' Lookin' at 'im, I
     couldn't believe it. ''Urt you?' 'e ses quite 'appily; 'an' why wouldn't I 'urt you? I'd as
     lief send you to the Devil as not,' 'e ses. Well, cocky, I don't mind tellin' you I lost me
     'ead at that. I run awiy — run awiy from my Elbert — Oh, Gosh! I bin an' give up me bits o'
     sticks to a neighbour, an' got a place, an' went into service. I sneaked out one night, when
     Elbert 'ad gone 'ome. I got a place up Kilburn way, an ol' couple, retired from the pawnbrokin'
     <pb n="68"/> line. The ol' man 'ad softening in 'is brain, an' said one thing all the blessed
     time, murmurin' like a bee. The ol' woman never spoke, never did no work, lef' it all to me.
     She was always a-readin' of 'er postcard album, shiftin' the cards about — she 'ad thousands,
     besides one 'ole book full of seaside comics. A beautiful collection. Well, I was dishin' up
     the tea one night in the kitchen, an' I 'eard a laugh — Elbert's laugh, like three little bells
     — an' there was Elbert lookin' in at the window. I run after 'im — there wasn't nobody there.
     When I come back the tripe was burnt an' I lef' it on the fire an' run away, thet minute. They
     owed me wages, but I didn't stop for nothink. I was frightened. I got a place afterwards up
     Islington, three ol' sisters, kep' a fancy shop, fought with each other every minute of their
     lives. I 'adn't bin there two days before Elbert walked in, jest as laughin' an' lovin' as
     ever. I see then it was no use, good or bad 'e'd got me. I let 'im sit in my kitchen, an' give
     'im some sugar-bread. An' one of the ol' cat-sisters come in. ''Oo's this?' she ses.
     <pb n="69"/> 'A young friend o' mine,' I ses. 'You're a liar,' she ses, 'I seed from the first
     minute as you wasn't no respectable gal,' she ses, 'an' now per'aps me sisters'll believe me.
     So out I 'ad to go, an' I wasn't sorry. It seemed like there wasn't nothink in the world
     mattered but Elbert, like as if damnation was worth while. 'Ow, Elbert,' I ses, 'I'd go to the
     Devil for you, an' smile all the way.' 'E laughed an' laughed. 'Come on,' 'e ses, 'to-day's an
     'oliday.' Though it wasn't, it was a Tuesday in August. 'Come on,' 'e ses, 'get yer best 'at
     on,' an' 'e gives me a yaller rose, for me button-'ole. A year ago come August, thet was. I
     follered Elbert at a run all up the City Road, an' near the Angel we took a taxi. 'Tell 'im
     Euston Station,' ses Elbert, an' so I did. You know the 'uge top o' thet station from the 'ill
     by the Angel — well, kid, I tell you I saw a reel mountain for the first time, when I saw thet.
     It was the 'eat mist, an' a sort o' pink light made a reel 'ighland landscape out of it. I paid
     the taxi-man over 'alf of all the money I 'ad, an' we went to the ticket-awfice. 'Elbert,' I
     ses, 'where
     <pb n="70"/>shell we book to,' I ses, like that, though I 'adn't 'ardly a bloody oat in me
     purse. 'Take a platform ticket,' 'e ses, an' so I did. But 'e run on to the platform without no
     ticket, an' begun dancin' up an' down among the people like a mad thing, but nobody seemed to
     mind 'im. I set down on a seat to watch 'im. I thought: 'Blimey,' I thought, 'if I ain't under
     thet blinkin' mountain now, an' all these people,' I ses, 'is the Little People they tell of,
     that lives inside 'ills, an' on'y comes out under the moon.' I remembered thet moonlight debt
     o' mine, an' I thought — 'I'm done with the mud now, I'm comin' alive now,' I ses, 'and this'll
     be my charnce.' Presently Elbert come back to me, an' 'e was draggin' a soldier by the 'and.
     'This is a magic man,' ses Elbert, 'come back from livin' under the sky. Can't you feel the
     magic?' 'e ses.</p>
    <p>"Well, dearie, take it 'ow you will, thet's 'ow I met my Sherrie. A magic man 'e was, for 'e
     'ad my ticket taken, an' never seemed surprised. Ten days leave 'e 'ad, an' we spent it at an
     inn in a village on a moor, jest a mile out o' sound of the sea.
     <pb n="71"/> The moor an' the sea, touchin' each other. ... Oh Gawd!... The sea was like my sky
     at night come nearer — come near enough to know better, like. In between the moor an' the sea
     there was the beach — it looked like a blessed boundary road between two countries, an' it led
     away to where you couldn't see nothing more except a little white town, sort of built 'igh upon
     a mist, more like a star.... Oh Gawd!...</p>
    <p>"Anyway, Cuffbut, thet was me charnce, an' thet's 'ow I come to know 'ow my debt was goin' to
     be paid. Sherrie understood all thet. 'E was a magic man, 'e was. At least, 'e was mostly
     magic, but some of 'im was nothin' but a fool when all's said an' done — like any other man. I
     couldn't 'ave done with an all-magic bloke. Ow, 'e was a fool.... All the things 'e might 'ave
     bin able to do, like polishin' 'is equipment, or findin' 'is clean socks, 'e use to forever be
     askin' me to do. I loved doin' it. But all the things 'e couldn't do at all, like drawin' me
     likeness, or cuttin' out a blouse for me, 'e was forever tryin' to do."</p>
    <p>She spoke of Sherrie as a naturalist
     <pb n="72"/>would speak of a new animal, gradually finding out the pretty and amusing ways of
     the creature.</p>
    <p>"I called 'im Sherrie because thet's what 'e called me. A French word it was, 'e ses, meaning
     'dearie,' as it were. 'E was a reel gent, was Sherrie. I as't 'im once why 'e took up with a
     woman like me, instead of with a reel young lady. 'E ses as 'ow 'e'd never met before anybody
     'oo seed themselves from outside an' yet was fairly honest. I know what 'e meant, for I was
     always more two people than one, an' I watch meself sometimes as if I was a play. I wouldn't be
     tellin' you this story, else. Well, dearie, Elbert was always in an' out, an' always
     a-hollerin' an' a-laughin' an' a-playin' 'is game. 'E stayed with us all them ten days, an' 'e
     come with me to Victoria, to see Sherrie off to France. It's Sherrie's allotted money what I
     fetch every week. But I won't touch it, I puts it away for Elbert. I don't want to owe nothin'
     to nobody, for I'm payin' sich a big debt. Elbert, when 'e comes back to me, 'e's going to be
     my payment to the world, an'
     <pb n="73"/> it's got to be good money. For Elbert left me after Sherrie went. 'E said as 'ow
     'e was going 'ome, an' as 'ow 'e would come back to me in the Spring, an' stay with me always.
     It wasn't like partin', e' ses, 'im an' me could never do thet. I know what 'e meant,
     now...."</p>
    <p>"And what about Sherrie?" asked Sarah Brown.</p>
    <p>"Oh, Sherrie, 'e never writes to me. But 'e promised too to come back in the Spring, an' so
     'e will, for there ain't no Boche bullet that can 'it a magic man."</p>
    <p>"It's springtime now," said Sarah Brown.</p>
    <p>"It's springtime now," repeated Peony. "Ow, it's wonderful, seems like as if I was gettin'
     too much given me, so as I can never repay. But I'm keepin' count, I'm not forgettin'. It ain't
     long now before I'll pay my debt. Come the middle o' May...."
     <pb n="74"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>
     <pb n="75"/>CHAPTER IV</head>
    <head>THE FORBIDDEN SANDWICH</head>
    <p>
     <pb n="76"/>
     <pb n="77"/>While Sarah Brown's unenviable leisure was spent in acting as slave to committees,
     she had at the same time a half-time profession which, when she was well enough to follow it,
     brought twenty shillings a week to her pocket. She was in the habit of sitting every morning in
     a small office, collecting evidence from charitable spies about the Naughty Poor, and, after
     wrapping the evidence in mysterious ciphers, writing it down very beautifully upon little
     cards, so that the next spy might have the benefit of all his forerunners' experience. Sarah
     Brown never thought about the theory of this work, because the different coloured inks and the
     beautiful writing pleased her so.</p>
    <p>There are people to whom a ream of virgin paper is an inspiration, who find the first
     sharpening of a pencil the most lovable
     <pb n="78"/>of all labours, who see something almost holy in the dedication of green and red
     penholders to their appropriate inks, in whose ears and before whose eyes the alphabet is like
     a poem or a prayer. Touch on stationery and you touched an insane spot in Sarah Brown's mind.
     Her dream of a perfect old age was staged in a stationer's shop in a quiet brown street; there
     she would spend twilit days in stroking thick blotting-paper, in drawing dogs — all looking one
     way — with new pen-nibs, in giving advice in a hushed voice to connoisseur customers, who
     should come to buy a diary or a book-plate or a fountain-pen with the same reverence as they
     now show who come to buy old wine.</p>
    <p>Therefore Sarah Brown's hand had found ideal employment on a charity register. As for her
     mind, it usually shut its eye during office hours. Her Dog David liked the work too, as the
     hearth-rug was a comfortable one, and Charity, though it may suffer long in other directions,
     is rather particular about its firing.</p>
    <p>On the Monday after her change of
     <pb n="79"/>home, Sarah Brown found that the glory had gone out of the varied inks, and even a
     new consignment of index-cards, exquisitely unspotted from the world, failed to arouse her
     enthusiasm. This was partly because the first name in the index that she looked up was that of
     Watkins, Thelma Bennett, single, machinist. The ciphers informed the initiated that Watkins had
     called on the War Association, to ask for Help and Advice, See Full Report. Sarah Brown felt
     sad and clumsy, and made two blots, one in green on the Watkins card, and the other in ordinary
     Stephens-colour on the card of one Tonk, chocolate-box-maker, single, to whom a certain charity
     was obstinately giving a half-pint of milk daily, regardless of the fact that last month she
     had received a shilling's-worth of groceries from the Parish.</p>
    <p>The air of that office rang with the name of Tonk that morning. Hardly had the industrious
     Sarah Brown finished turning the blot upon her card into the silhouette of a dromedary by a few
     ingenious strokes of the pen, when the lady representing the
     <pb n="80"/>obstinate charity came in, her lips shaped to the word Tonk.</p>
    <p>"Tonk," she said. "Late of Mud Street. She has changed her address. I am the Guild of Happy
     Hearts. She still comes to fetch her half-pint of milk daily, and only yesterday I learnt from
     a neighbour that she had left Mud Street three weeks ago. It really is disgraceful the way
     these poor people conceal important facts from us. Have you her new address?"</p>
    <p>"Our last address for Tonk was 12 Mud Street," answered Sarah Brown coldly. "But we have
     already notified you three times that the woman is not entitled to milk from the Happy Hearts,
     as she has been having parish relief, as well as an allotment."</p>
    <p>"Tonk is — hm — hm," said the Happy Heart delicately in an undertone, so that the blushing
     masculine ear of the Dog David might be spared. "After Baby Week, you know, we feel bound to
     help all hm — hm women as far as we can, regardless of other considerations — "</p>
    <p>"Really you oughtn't to. Tonk is
     <pb n="81"/>posing as a single chocolate-box-maker." Sarah Brown was rapidly becoming
     exasperated with everybody concerned, but not least with the evidently camouflaging Tonk.</p>
    <p>"She has a soldier at the Front," said the Happy Heart. "I am sorry to say that she will not
     promise to marry him, even if he does come home. But even so — "</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown wrote down on Miss Tonk's card the small purple cipher that stood for hm — hm. "I
     will make enquiries about her address," she said.</p>
    <p>But that was not the last of Tonk. Presently the red face of the Relieving Officer loomed
     over the index.</p>
    <p>"In the case of Plummett — " he began loudly.</p>
    <p>"In the case of Tonk — " interrupted Sarah Brown, to whom, in her present mood, Plummett
     could only have been a last straw. She hated the Relieving Officer unjustly, because he knew
     she was deaf and raised his voice, with the best intentions, to such a degree that the case
     papers on the index were occasionally blown away. "We have already notified you three times
     that Tonk
     <pb n="82"/>is having a half-pint of milk daily from the Happy Hearts, as well as an allotment
     from a soldier."</p>
    <p>"We stopped the groceries," roared the Relieving Officer. "But in the case of Plummett —
     "</p>
    <p>"In the case of Tonk — " persisted Sarah Brown. "She has moved from Mud Street, can you tell
     me her last address?"</p>
    <p>"She is living in a sort of private charitable institution, somewhere on the outskirts of the
     district — Mitten Island, I fancy. I don't know the exact address, because we have stopped the
     groceries, she paying no rent now. In the case of Plummett, I thought you might be interested
     to know that she got a month this morning for assaulting the Sanitary Inspector — pulling his
     nose, I hear. She told the magistrate it struck her as being a useless nose if it didn't notice
     anything wrong with her drains. The children came into the House this morning."</p>
    <p>"What is Tonk's Christian name?" asked Sarah Brown, who had been a changed woman since Mitten
     Island was mentioned.
     <pb n="83"/></p>
    <p>"I forget. Some flower name, I think. Probably Lily or Ivy. In the case of M'Clubbin, the
     woman is said to have fallen through a hole in the floor of the room she and her three children
     slept in. She was admitted into the Infirmary last night, and her furniture will be sold to pay
     her rent — "</p>
    <p>"It begins with P," said Sarah Brown. "P. Tonk, unmarried wife, of Mitten Island...."</p>
    <p>The Relieving Officer went away, for it was dinner-time. Sarah Brown absently unwrapped the
     little dinner which she had brought hanging by a thin string from a strangled finger. Mustard
     sandwiches with just a flavouring of ham, and a painfully orthodox 1918-model bun, made of
     stubble. Sarah Brown almost always forgot the necessity of food until she was irrevocably in
     the 'bus on her way to work. But this morning, as she had taken her seat with David in the
     bouncing ferry-boat, there had been a panting rustling noise behind her, and Harold the
     Broomstick had swept a little packet of sandwiches into her lap. He had disappeared before she
     had been
     <pb n="84"/>able to do more than turn over in her mind the question whether or no broomsticks
     ever expect to be tipped.</p>
    <p>Now I could not say with certainty whether the witch, in making up this packet of sandwiches,
     had included the contents of one of her own little packets of magic. Sarah Brown would have
     been very susceptible to such a drug; her mind was always on the brink of innocent
     intoxication. Perhaps she was only half a woman, so that half a joy could make her heart reel
     and sing, and half a sorrow break it. She was defenceless against impressions, and too many
     impressions make the heart very tired. Therefore, I think, she was a predestined victim of
     magic, and it seems unlikely that the witch should have missed such an opportunity to dispense
     spells.</p>
    <p>After the first bite at the first sandwich, Sarah Brown was conscious of a Joke somewhere.
     This feeling in itself was akin to delirium, for there are no two facts so remote as a Joke and
     a Charity Society. The office table confronted Sarah Brown, and she wondered that she could
     ever have seen
     <pb n="85"/>it as anything but a butt. She wondered how she had been able to sit daily in front
     of that stout and earnest index without poking it in the ribs and making a fool of it. The
     office clock, alone among clocks, had never played a practical joke. The sad fire below it,
     conscious of a Mission, was overloaded with coal and responsibility.</p>
    <p>The second bite, ten minutes later, caused Sarah Brown to be tired and distrustful of a room
     that had no smile. Her eyes turned to seek the hidden Joke beyond the limits of that lamentable
     room. There was a spring-coloured tree in the school-ground opposite, and above the tree a
     rough blue and silver sky contradicted all the doctrines preached in offices. There was in the
     wind something of the old raw simplicity and mirth that always haunts the sea, and penetrates
     inland only on rare spring days. The high white clouds crossed the sky like galleons, like old
     stories out of the innocent Eden-like past of the sea, before she learnt the ways of steam and
     secret killing. Old names of ships came to Sarah Brown's mind ... Castle-of-Comfort ...
     Cloud-i'-the-Sun....
     <pb n="86"/></p>
    <p>"I am doing wrong," said Sarah Brown. She took a third bite.</p>
    <p>And then she felt the spirit of the Naughty Poor in the room; there was laughter, as of the
     registered, in the ears of the Registrar. It is not really permissible for the Naughty Poor to
     invade offices which exist to do them good. The way of charity lies through suspicion, but the
     suspicion of course must be all on one side. We have to judge the criminal unheard; if we
     called him as a witness in his case we might become sentimental. The Charity Society may be
     imagined as keeping two lists of crimes, a short one for Registrars and Workers, and a very
     long one for the registered. High on the list of crimes possible to Registrars and Workers is
     Sentimentality. It is sentimental to feel personal affection for a Case, or to give a child of
     the Naughty Poor a penny without full enquiry, or to say "A-goo" to a grey pensive baby eating
     dirt on the pavement, or to acknowledge the right of a Case to ask questions sometimes instead
     of answering them, or to disapprove of spying and tale-bearing,
     <pb n="87"/>or to believe any statement made by any one without an assured income, or to quote
     any part of the New Testament, or in fact to confuse in any way the ideas of charity and love.
     Christ, who, by the way, unfortunately omitted to join any reputable philanthropic society,
     commanded seekers of salvation to be poor and to despise themselves. But this was sentimental,
     and the Charity Society decrees that only the prosperous and the self-respectful shall deserve
     a hearing.</p>
    <p>"I am sentimental," said Sarah Brown to her Dog David in a broken voice. She turned again to
     her enchanted sandwich.</p>
    <p>There was increased laughter in the air, and through it she heard the hoarse and happy
     shouting of the sparrows in the spring-coloured tree opposite. Sparrows are the ideal Naughty
     Poor, the begging friars, the gypsies of the air, they claim alms as a right and as a seal of
     friendship; with their mouths full of your crumbs they share with you their innocent and vulgar
     wit, they give you in return no I.O.U., and no particulars for your case-paper. When they have
     got from you all that you will give, they wink
     <pb n="88"/>and giggle and shake the dust of your window-sill from off their feet.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown opened the office window, and the air of the office began at once to dance with
     life and the noise of children and birds. She thought perhaps these were magic noises, for she
     heard them so clearly. She broke her second sandwich upon the window-sill, and the sparrows
     crossed the street and stood on the area railing in a row below her, all speaking at once in an
     effort to convey to her the fact that a retreat on her part would be tactful.</p>
    <p>The sparrow obviously buys all his clothes ready-made, probably at Jumble Sales, and he
     always seems to choose clothes made for a stouter bird. There is no reason why he should never
     look chic; he has a slimmer figure than the bullfinch, for instance, who always manages to look
     so well-tailored. It is just arrogance, pure Londonism, on the part of the sparrow, just that
     impudent socialistic spirit that makes it so difficult for us to reform the Naughty Poor.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown retreated one step. "I'm not going farther away. Either you eat
     <pb n="89"/>that sandwich with me looking on, or you leave it."</p>
    <p>The sparrows whispered together for a moment, saying to each other, "You go first." They
     obviously knew that it was a charity window-sill, and were afraid Sarah Brown might intend to
     rebuke them for not shutting their beaks while chewing, or for neglecting to put any crumbs
     into the Savings Bank. But after a minute one sparrow moistened his beak and came.... He ate,
     they all ate, and did not seek to escape as the door of the office opened and the witch came
     in. She went straight to the window and picked up from among the stooping sparrows a piece of
     the broken sandwich, and ate it. The Dog David was making sure that there was no surviving
     crumb on the floor to tell the tale of his mother's sentimental weakness. Almost instantly,
     therefore, that sandwich was but a memory, a fading taste in about twenty beaks and two mouths.
     But still the window stood open, and the air danced, and the white reflections of the ship-like
     clouds lay on the oilcloth floor.
     <pb n="90"/></p>
    <p>Sarah Brown in the meanwhile, disregarding the witch, had returned to the index, and had
     taken from its drawer a notification form. In the space given for Name of Case she had written
     in her irreproachable printing hand:</p>
    <p>"CHARITY, Cautionary Case, 12 Pan Street, Brown Borough. With reference to the above case, I
     have to report that it seems unsatisfactory. There are indeed grave suspicions that the above
     name is only an alias, the address being also probably false, for the genuine Charity's place
     of origin is said to be the home rather than the office. The present registrar is at a loss to
     identify with certainty this case. It would seem to be one of the Habits that haunt the world,
     collecting Kudos under assumed names...."</p>
    <p>"It puzzles me," said the witch, looking out of the window, "why one never sees two birds
     collide. If there were as many witches in the air as there are birds, I bet you twopence there
     would be constant accidents. Do you think they have any sort of a rule of the road, or do they
     indicate with their beaks — "
     <pb n="91"/></p>
    <p>"Witch," said Sarah Brown, "I have got to say something."</p>
    <p>"Oh, have you?" said the witch, a little disappointed at being interrupted. "Oh, well, I can
     sympathise, I know what that feels like. Get on and say it."</p>
    <p>The Dog David, who was really a good and attentive son to Sarah Brown, came and laid his
     chin, with an exaggerated look of interest, on her knee-cap.</p>
    <p>"Is it any use," said Sarah Brown, "fighting against the Habits in the world, there are so
     many. Who set these strange and senseless deceivers at large? Religion which has forgotten
     ecstasy.... Law which has forgotten justice.... Charity which has forgotten love.... Surely
     magic has suffered at the stake for saner ideals than these?"</p>
    <p>"Why, of course," said the witch impatiently. "Magic generally suffered <hi>because</hi> it
     was so sane. I thought everybody knew that."</p>
    <p>"All habits. All habits," chanted Sarah Brown. "What is this Charity, this clinking of money
     between strangers, and when did
     <pb n="92"/> Charity cease to be a comforting and secret thing between one friend and another?
     Does Love make her voice heard through a committee, does Love employ an almoner to convey her
     message to her neighbour?"</p>
    <p>"Not that I know of," sighed the witch. "Sarah Brown, how long do you want me to keep quiet,
     while you say things that everybody surely knows?"</p>
    <p>But Sarah Brown went on. "The real Love knows her neighbour face to face, and laughs with him
     and weeps with him, and eats and drinks with him, so that at last, when his black day dawns,
     she may share with him, not what she can spare, but all that she has."</p>
    <p>The Dog David grunted a little, by way of rather dubious applause. Sarah Brown, with her own
     voice printed loud and stark upon the retina of her hearing, felt a little abashed. But
     presently she added in a whisper: "Listen. I am a spy. I am a lover of specially recommended
     neighbours only. I am here to help to give the black cloud Tyranny a rather dirty silver
     lining. I am the False Steward, in the interest of
     <pb n="93"/>the Superfluously Comfortable. My Masters sit upon the King's Highway, taking toll
     in bitterness and humiliation from every traveller along that road. For surely comfort is every
     man's heritage, surely the happy years should come to every man — not doled out, not meanly
     dependent on his moral orthodoxy, but as his right. The fat philanthropist is a debtor, but he
     behaves like a creditor; he distributes obligations with his gold, yet he has no right to the
     gold he gives. He makes his brother beg upon his knees for the life and the health and the dear
     opportunity that should have been that brother's birthright."</p>
    <p>"You are possessed, dear Sarah Brown," said the witch. "Don't be frightened, it will soon
     pass off. I knew a girl who had an attack very much like this; while she was under its
     influence she made up a psalm pretty nearly as good as one of David's. Her mother was much
     alarmed about her. But she recovered quite quickly, except that she left her job as typist in a
     mind-improving institute and went to sea as a stewardess."</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown talked on, louder and louder.
     <pb n="94"/> "Too long I have been a servant in the house of this stranger, this greedy
     Charity; too long have I sat — a silly proxy for the Too-Fortunate — in this narrow
     stiff-backed judgement-seat from ten till three daily. There is Love and April outside the
     window, there is too much wind and laughter outside to allow of the forming of Habits. I have
     seen Love and the Spring only through the glass of a charity office window, the rude voices of
     children and sparrows and other inheritors of opportunity have been dulled for me by grey
     panes. The white ships ... Castle-of-Comfort ... Cloud-i'-the-Sun have sailed into port from
     the open sky without a cargo for me...."</p>
    <p>"Good God!" said Sarah Brown, pushing David from her. "What has happened to me? I have become
     sentimental."</p>
    <p>The room seemed to her wild imagination to be full of the spirits of parsons and social
     workers with flaming swords, pointing at the door.</p>
    <p>"Well, that's the end of that job," said the witch. "I'll tell you what, let's go and sit on
     the Swing-leg Seat on the
     <pb n="95"/> Heath. The air there and the look of Harrow church steeple'll do you good."</p>
    <p>"I am damned. I am a Cautionary Case," cried Sarah Brown, and she slunk behind the witch
     through the frowning gate of her Eden of fair inks and smooth white surfaces. She had shared
     with David the remains of her Sandwich of Knowledge; she had left on the table her puny paper
     defiance. David, except that he had required but little temptation, had played Adam's part very
     creditably in the affair. For him Eden had been a soft warm place, and he was anxious to blame
     somebody — the woman for choice — for the loss of his comfort. He followed her out into the
     cold, to become, as you shall hear, like Adam, a tiller of the soil.
     <pb n="96"/>
     <pb n="97"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER V</head>
    <head>AN AIR RAID SEEN FROM BELOW</head>
    <p>
     <pb n="98"/>
     <pb n="99"/>Magic is a disconcerting travelling companion. While seldom actually conspicuous,
     it seems to have a mysterious and varying effect on the surrounding public. I have met
     travellers by Tube who tell of strange doings in those regions, when the conductor of one
     compartment fell suddenly in love with the conductress of the next, and they ran to each other
     and met in the middle of the car. As nobody opened the gates or rang the bells, the bewildered
     train stood for hours at Mornington Crescent before any member of the watching public could
     find the heart to interrupt the pretty scene. It is patent that a magic person must have been
     the more or less deliberate cause of this episode. Then again, there is the story of the 'bus
     that went mad, just as it was leaving its burrow at Dalston. It got the idea that the kindly
     public was its enemy.
     <pb n="100"/> You should have seen the astonishment of Liverpool Street and the Bank as it
     rushed by them. Old ladies about to ask it whether it went to Clapham — its label said it was
     bound for Barnes — stood aghast, and their questions died on their lips. Policemen put up their
     hands against it, — it ran over them. It even learned the trick of avoiding the nimble business
     man by a cunning little skid just as he thought he had caught it. You will hardly believe me,
     but that 'bus ran seven times round Trafalgar Square, until the lions' tails twisted for
     giddiness, and Nelson reeled where he stood. I don't know where it went to that day, certainly
     not to Barnes, but late in the evening it burst into another 'bus's burrow at Tooting, its
     sides heaving, its tyres worn to the quick, its windows streaming with perspiration, and a
     great bruise on its forehead where a chance bomb had struck it. I believe the poor thing had to
     be put out of its misery in the end. And what was the reason of all this? It was found that a
     wizard, called Innocent, of Stoke Newington, had been asleep on the top all the time, having
     forgotten to alight
     <pb n="101"/>the night before, on his return from the City.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown, on the night of Lady Arabel's supper party, was unaware of the risk she ran in
     entering a public conveyance in company with a witch. But she was spared to a merciful extent,
     for nothing happened on any of the 'buses they boarded, except that, as they crossed the Canal,
     a cloud of sea-gulls swooped and swirled into the 'bus, resting awhile on the passengers'
     willing shoulders before disappearing again. Also the passengers on the Baker Street stretch
     sang part-songs, all the way down to Selfridge's. The conductor turned out to have rather a
     pleasing tenor voice.</p>
    <p>The witch and Sarah Brown knocked at the Higgins' door five minutes before supper-time. Lady
     Arabel herself opened it.</p>
    <p>"My dears, isn't it too dretful. All our servants are gone. It's an extraordinary thing, they
     never can stand Rrchud and his ways."</p>
    <p>The tactful Sarah Brown nudged the witch. "Better not stay," she murmured.</p>
    <p>"Of course we'll stay," replied the witch
     <pb n="102"/>loudly. "I'm horribly hungry, and there's sure to be some supper."</p>
    <p>"Certainly there is," added Lady Arabel. "I cooked it myself. Do you know, I've never seen a
     cookery book before, and the little pictures of animals with the names of joints written all
     over them shocked me dretfully. I feel I could have a too deliciously intimate conversation
     with a bullock now."</p>
    <p>The house of Higgins had an enormous hall to which a large number of high windows gave the
     impression of a squint. I should think two small Zeppelins could have danced a minuet under its
     dome. Sarah Brown and the witch put on their cathedral look at once, by mistake, and propping
     their chins upon their umbrellas gazed reverently upward.</p>
    <p>"Too dretful, a house of this size without servants," said Lady Arabel. "The fourth footman
     was the last to go. He said even the Army would be better than this. He liked spooks, he said,
     at second hand, but not otherwise. Too funny how people take dear Rrchud seriously. I'm glad to
     say
     <pb n="103"/>the orchestra has stayed with us. Come into Rrchud's study, won't you, while I
     just go and help the first violin to dish up the soup."</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown and the witch were left in a small room that opened on to the great hall. It was
     furnished rather like a lodging-house parlour. There was a thermometer elaborately disguised as
     a model of the Eddystone Lighthouse on the mantelpiece, flanked on each side by a china boot in
     pink, with real bootlaces, and a pig looking out of the top of each. There were pictures on the
     walls, mostly representing young ladies, more or less obviously in love, supported by rustic
     properties. I have noticed that the girl's first love is the monopoly of the Victorian painter,
     whereas the boy's is that of the novelist, but I do not know the reason of this.</p>
    <p>There was a slight clap of thunder and Richard entered. He would have been very obviously a
     wizard even without the thunder, and seemed much less innocent about his magic than the witch.
     He had pale hair, a pale face, and eyes that did not
     <pb n="104"/>open wide without a certain effort on the part of the brows.</p>
    <p>"You are despising my ornaments," he said to Sarah Brown. "I admire them awfully. I don't
     like really clever art. Do you know, it makes me sneeze."</p>
    <p>Directly he spoke, one saw that he was making the usual effort of magic to appear real.
     Witches and wizards lead difficult lives because they have no ancestry working within them to
     prompt them in the little details. Whenever you see a person being unusually grown-up, suspect
     them of magic. You can always notice witches and wizards, for instance, after eight o'clock at
     night, pretending that they are not proud of sitting up late. It is all nonsense about witches
     being night birds; they often fly about at night, indeed, but only because they are like
     permanent children gloriously escaped for ever from their Nanas.</p>
    <p>"This picture," added Richard, "seems to me very beautiful." The picture might have cost a
     shilling originally, framed, or it might have been attached to a calendar once. It was a
     landscape so thick in
     <pb n="105"/>colouring and so lightless that it failed to give an outdoor impression at all.
     There was a river and waterfall like well-combed hair in the middle, and a dozen leaden
     mountains lying about with — apparently — pocket-handkerchiefs on their tops, and a
     dropsical-looking stag drinking. "I can't imagine," insisted Richard, "that there could be a
     more beautiful picture than that, but perhaps it appeals to me specially because father and
     mother and I so often talk about the place together — the place like that, near to the mountain
     where I was born. That was in the Rockies, you know, and just below our mountain I am sure
     there was a canyon like that — I dream of it — with milky-green water running under and over
     and round the most extraordinary shapes of ice, and cactuses like green hedgehogs in the
     crevices of the rocks, and great untidy pine-trees clinging to an ounce of earth on an inch of
     flat surface. And the rocks are a most splendid rose-red, and lie in steep layers, and break
     out into shapes that are so deliberate, they look as if they must mean something. Indeed they
     do...."
     <pb n="106"/></p>
    <p>A stave played by a 'cello called them to supper, and, as they returned to the hall, a burst
     of earnest music from the whole orchestra partially drowned the clap of thunder that again
     marked Richard's passage through the door. Sarah Brown felt sure that Lady Arabel arranged this
     on purpose. The wizard's mother obviously had great difficulty in not noticing the phenomena
     connected with her son, and she wore a striving smile and a look of glassy and well-bred
     unconsciousness whenever anything magic happened.</p>
    <p>At the end of the hall the orchestra, arranged neatly in a crescent, was busily employing its
     violins in a unanimous melody of so rude and destructive a nature that it seemed as if every
     string must be broken. This mania spread until even the outlying bassoons, triangles, and
     celestas were infected. A piercing note of command, however, from a clarinet caused a
     devastating dumbness to fall suddenly on every instrument except the piano, which continued
     self-consciously alone. The pianist looked at the ceiling mostly, but one note seemed
     <pb n="107"/>to be an especial favourite with him, and whenever he played it he looked closely
     and paternally at it, almost indeed applying his nose to it. All at once, just as Sarah Brown
     was beginning to imagine that she could catch the tune and the time, the music ceased,
     apparently in the middle of a bar. Richard sneezed once or twice. That unsophisticated wizard
     was evidently enjoying himself in the practice of his art. One felt that magic was not
     encouraged in the Army, and that the supernatural orgy in which he was now indulging was the
     accumulated reaction after long self-control. Strange noises of unnatural laughter, for
     instance, proceeded from distant corners of the hall, and each of the electric lights in turn
     winked facetiously. The string of the double bass broke loudly, and the new string which its
     devotee laboriously inserted also broke at once. The performer looked appealingly at Lady
     Arabel, but she refrained from meeting his eye. A blizzard of butterflies enveloped the table.
     This was evidently rather a difficult trick, for the spell collapsed repeatedly, and from one
     <pb n="108"/>second to another Sarah Brown was never quite sure whether there were really
     Purple Admirals drowning in her soup or not.</p>
    <p>"You are so lucky," sighed the witch, "plenty of room and every facility. I myself am so
     dreadfully cramped and hampered. I often have to boil my incantations over a spirit lamp, and
     even that is becoming difficult — no methylated."</p>
    <p>"Not really lucky," said Richard. "In France the smallest pinch of magic seems to make the
     N.C.O. sick, and that's why I never got my stripe. To keep my hand in, I once did a little
     stunt with the sergeant's cigarette: it grew suddenly longer as he struck a match to light it,
     and went on growing till he had to ask me to light it for him, and then it shrank up and burnt
     his nose. Of course he couldn't really bring the thing home to me, but somehow — well, as I
     say, I never got my stripe."</p>
    <p>To this discussion, and indeed to all the enchantments, Lady Arabel paid no attention, but
     continued to talk a little nervously on very insipid subjects. Her eyes had the pathetic look
     often seen in
     <pb n="109"/>stupid people's eyes, the "Don't-listen-to-me" look, "I am not saying what I
     should like to say. The real Me is better than this."</p>
    <p>Finally Richard indulged in a trick that was evidently a stock joke among magic people, for
     the witch laughed directly it began. Just as the hostess, with poised fork and spoon, was about
     to distribute the whitebait, the round table began to spin, and the whitebait were whisked away
     from her. The table continued to spin for a moment, with a deep thrilling organ sound, and when
     it stopped, the whitebait were found to have assembled opposite to Richard's place. He
     distributed them gravely. Lady Arabel turned scarlet, and murmured to Sarah Brown: "So
     dretfully ingenious, and so merry."</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown took pity on her, and began talking at random. The orchestra was busy again, and
     to the tune of a loud elusive rag-time, she shouted: "Do you know, I gave my job the sack this
     morning. I shall be on the brink of starvation in three and a half days' time. That's counting
     a box
     <pb n="110"/>of Oxo Cubes I have by me. You don't happen to know of a suitable job. I can't
     cook, and if I sew a button on it comes off quicker than if I hadn't. But I once learnt to play
     the big drum."</p>
    <p>"My dear," said Lady Arabel, instantly motherly. "How too dretful. I wish I knew of something
     suitable. But — war-time you know, — I'm afraid I shan't be justified in keeping on the
     orchestra, certainly not in adding to it. Besides, of course, although women are simply too
     splendid nowadays, don't you think the big drum — just a wee bit unwomanly, my dear. However —
     — "</p>
    <p>"Are you clever?" asked Richard.</p>
    <p>"Yes, she is," said the witch proudly. "She writes Minor Poetry. I saw a bit by her in a
     magazine that had no pictures, — the bit of poetry was between an article on Tariff Reform and
     a statement of the Coal Situation, and it began 'Oh my beloved....' I thought it was a very
     beautiful bit of Minor Poetry, but somehow I couldn't make it fit in with the two articles.
     That worried me a little."</p>
    <p>"If you'd try your best not to be clever
     <pb n="111"/> I'd give you a job," said Richard, who with a rather tiresome persistence was now
     levitating the chicken, so that, invisibly suspended at a height of eighteen inches above the
     middle of the table, it dripped gravy into a bowl of daffodils. "In fact I will give you a job.
     I have a farm called Higgins Farm, just about half-way between sea-level and sky-level. You can
     be a Hand, if you like, at sixpence an hour. You can get there from Mitten Island every day
     quite easily, and I'll tell you how. It's just the other side of the Parish of Faery, on your
     right as you reach the mainland from Mitten Island. You follow the Green Ride through the
     Enchanted Forest, until you come to the Castle where the Youngest Prince — who rescued one of
     the Fetherstonhaugh girls from a giant and married her — used to live. The Castle's to let now;
     she is an ambulance driver in Salonika, and he a gunner — just got his battery, I believe.
     Below the outer wall of the Castle you will see the Daisified Path, and that leads you straight
     to the gate of Higgins Farm, under a clipped box archway."
     <pb n="112"/></p>
    <p>"I haven't got a land outfit," said Sarah Brown. "But I saw a pair called Mesopotamian
     Officer's Model, with laces and real white buckskin collision mats between the knees, that
     would fit me, and I can pawn my — — "</p>
    <p>At that moment there was a loud report. Every one looked at the double bass, but all his
     strings were for the moment intact.</p>
    <p>"A maroon," said the witch.</p>
    <p>"My dears," exclaimed Lady Arabel, much relieved to hear that this new sensation was not
     supernatural. "How too dretfully tahsome with the sweet and the savoury still to come. Do you
     know, I promised Pinehurst — my husband — never to remain in this house during an air-raid. It
     was his own fault, the dear thing; he had a craze for windows; this house has more glass space
     than wall, I think, and Pinehurst, in his spare time, used always to be making plans for
     squeezing in more windows. Our room is like a conservatory — so dretfully embarrassing. So I
     always take my knitting across the road to the crypt of St. Sebastian's, and I'm sure you won't
     mind coming too.
     <pb n="113"/> You might have brought a box of spellicans, or a set of table croquet, but I'm
     afraid the Vicar wouldn't like it. A nice man but dretfully particular. We must wait for the
     end of this piece, the first violin is so touchy."</p>
    <p>They all waited patiently while the piece continued. It was a plain uneventful piece,
     composed by a Higgins relative and therefore admired in the household.</p>
    <p>"A thing that puzzles me," said the witch, taking advantage of an emotional pause while one
     violin was wheezing a very long small note by itself, "is why only ugly songs are really
     persistent. Haven't you noticed, for instance, that a peacock, or a cat on the wall, or a baby
     with a tin trumpet, will give their services most generously for hours on end, while a robin on
     a snowy tree, or a nightingale, or a fairy — — "</p>
    <p>She was interrupted by a scuffling sound in the umbrella-stand, and Harold the Broomstick,
     after a moment's rather embarrassing entanglement with a butterfly net, approached,
     panting.</p>
    <p>"I must go," said the witch. "I bet you twopence we shall have some fun
     <pb n="114"/>to-night. Sarah Brown, I'll come back and fetch you when it's all over."</p>
    <p>Lady Arabel and Sarah Brown crossed the road to the church, Richard following a few yards
     behind.</p>
    <p>"I'm afraid my little dinner-party wasn't a great success," said Lady Arabel confidentially.
     "Rrchud and Angela didn't get that good talk on occult subjects as Meta Ford said they would.
     Of course Rrchud, as you noticed, was dretfully restless and lighthearted; all boys are like
     that for the first few hours of their leave. He is naturally of a quiet disposition, though you
     wouldn't think it from to-night."</p>
    <p>There was a distant blot of gunfire on the air, just as they reached the door of the crypt.
     The very stout dog of the Vicar (are not all reverend dogs fat?) was waiting there with a bored
     look.</p>
    <p>"The Vicar allows no animals inside the crypt. So hard on Mrs. Perry's canary which has fits.
     I was here once when the Vicar's youngest son brought in a rabbit under his coat. A dretful
     scene, my dear."</p>
    <p>That district of London happened to be
     <pb n="115"/>rather a courageous one. The inhabitants felt that if the War had to be brought
     home to them, common politeness dictated that it should find them at home. There were not more
     than a dozen people in the crypt therefore. Most of them were old ladies from the district's
     less respectable quarter, knitting. The Vicar was trying to press comfort upon them, but
     without much success, for they were all quite content, discussing the deaths in their
     families.</p>
    <p>The noise of gunfire was coming nearer, shaking the ground like the uneven tread of a drunken
     giant. Sarah Brown concentrated on an evening newspaper, busily reading again and again one of
     those columns of confidential man-to-man advertisement, which everybody reads with avidity
     while determining the more never to buy the article advertised. But presently the fidgeting
     hands of Richard caught her eye, and she looked at him. He was sitting next to his mother on a
     stone step. He seemed to be in a quieter mood and attempted no manifestation. Sarah Brown
     thought he was suppressing excitement, however, and indeed
     <pb n="116"/>he presently said: "I say, won't it be fun lying about all this to posterity and
     Americans, and other defenceless innocents."</p>
    <p>Opposite to them, on two campstools, sat a young bridling mother of fifty, with her old hard
     daughter of sixteen or so. Hard was that daughter in every way; you would have counted her age
     in winters, not in summers, so obviously untender were her years. An iron plait of hair lay for
     about six inches down her spine; her feet and ankles made the campstool on which she sat,
     looking pathetically ethereal. Of such stuff as this is the backbone of England made, which is
     perhaps why the backbone of England sometimes seems so sadly inflexible.</p>
    <p>There was a screeching noise outside, followed by an incredible crash. It seemed to cleave a
     bottomless abyss between one second and the next, so that one seemed to be conscious for the
     first time in an astonished and astonishing world.</p>
    <p>Lady Arabel said: "Boys will be boys, of course I know, but really this is going a little too
     far. Pinehurst's one hobby was his windows."
     <pb n="117"/></p>
    <p>The campstooled mother gave a luxurious little shriek as soon as the crash was safely over.
     "The villains," she said kittenishly. "Aiming at places of worship as usual. I am absolutely
     paralysed with terror. Mary, darling, I don't believe you turned a hair."</p>
    <p>"Pas un cheval," replied her firm daughter, in not unnatural error. One could easily see that
     she was beloved at home, and one wondered why.</p>
    <p>The sound of the guns seemed only a negative form of sound after the bomb, and clearly above
     the firing could be heard a howl. The Vicar's dog, still howling, ran into the crypt.</p>
    <p>"RUPERT!" said the Vicar, in a terrible voice, interrupting himself in the middle of a
     cheering platitude. But he had no time to say anything more, for behind Rupert came a
     procession of perhaps a dozen people, all dressed in sheets. Everybody saw at one pitiful
     glance that these were unfortunate householders, so suddenly roused from oblivion as to forget
     all their ordinary suburban dignity, probably barely escaping from ruined homes with their
     lives and a
     <pb n="118"/>sheet each. There was a very old man, a middle-aged spinster, and then an enormous
     group of children of ages varying from two months to twenty years, followed by their parents,
     teachers, or guardians.</p>
    <p>A nearer gun began to fire, and one of the old ladies on the other side of the crypt suddenly
     threw down her knitting and began confessing her sins. "Ow, I shall go to 'ell," she shouted
     dramatically. "I bin sich a wicked ol' woman. I nearly done in me first ol' man by biffin' the
     chopper at 'is nob, and Lawd, the lies I bin an' tol' me second only yesterday."</p>
    <p>"This is indeed a solemn moment," said the sheeted spinster sitting down beside Lady Arabel.
     "I hope I am meeting it in a proper spirit, but of course one is still only human, and
     naturally nervous. I have learned my statement by heart."</p>
    <p>"What statement?" asked Lady Arabel, who was rather deeply engrossed in turning the heel of
     the sock she was knitting.</p>
    <p>"The statement I shall make when the sheep are divided from the goats."</p>
    <p>"Oh, come, come," said kind Lady
     <pb n="119"/> Arabel. "Things are not so bad as that, surely. You must not be so dretfully
     pessimistic."</p>
    <p>"You mistake me," said the sheeted lady, bridling. "There is, I am confident, no cause
     whatever for pessimism on my part. I have no misgivings as to the verdict. But not being used
     to courts of law, I thought it best to learn my statement, as I say, by heart."</p>
    <p>The old knitter had been rather annoyed to find her confession interrupted. "A wicked ol'
     woman I may be," she said with more dignity. "But I'll never regret givin' that bloody speshul
     a bit o' me mind this mornin' when 'e turned saucy to the sugar queue. I ses to 'im — — "</p>
    <p>"We all have our faults," Lady Arabel's neighbour broke in. "But I think, at this solemn
     moment, I may feel thankful that hastiness of recrimination was never one of mine. All my life
     I have made it an unalterable rule never to make a statement without first asking myself: Is it
      <hi>TRUE</hi>? Is it <hi>JUST</hi>? Is it <hi>KIND</hi>?"</p>
    <p>"You may well say so," replied Lady Arabel pleasantly. "I only wish the younger
     <pb n="120"/>generation would follow your example. Nowadays it is much more likely to be: Is it
     true? No. Is it just? No. Is it kind? No. Is it <hi>FUNNY</hi>? Yes. And out it comes."</p>
    <p>"Be that as it may," said the ladylike creature. (One could see she was a Real Lady even
     through the sheet. Obviously she read the <hi>Morning Post</hi> daily.) "Be that as it may,
     perhaps you can help me in one little matter which is intriguing me slightly even at this
     solemn moment. Do you suppose the sheep will be allowed to hear the trial of the goats, or will
     the court be cleared? I must say I should be so interested to hear the defence of the late
     churchwarden who eloped with — — "</p>
    <p>"Ah, please, please," said Lady Arabel, "don't talk in that dretful way. Don't let your mind
     dwell on the worst. I assure you that you will be all right."</p>
    <p>"Of course I shall be all right, as you put it," said the elderly lady, coldly drawing
     herself up. "Everybody can be my witness that I have kept my candle burning in my small corner
     — — "
     <pb n="121"/></p>
    <p>"Good gracious," shrieked the kittenish mother. "A candle burning to-night. And probably
     unshaded. Don't you know that those fiends in the sky are always on the watch for the slightest
     illumination?"</p>
    <p>"Fiends in the sky!" exclaimed the sheeted lady. "Do you mean to say they are abroad even at
     this solemn moment?"</p>
    <p>"Oh, don't talk such rot," implored the hard flapper. "Who the dickens do you suppose was
     responsible for that crash?"</p>
    <p>"Responsible for the crash!" said the other, whose tones were becoming more and more alive
     with exclamation marks. "Is then the solemn work of summoning us entrusted to the minions of
     the Evil One?"</p>
    <p>A series of crashes interrupted her, the work of the adjacent gun. The earth shook, and each
     report was followed by the curious ethereal wail of shells on their way.</p>
    <p>"What, again?" exclaimed Lady Arabel's sheeted neighbour. "I should have thought one would
     have been ample. But still, one cannot be too careful, and some people are heavy sleepers. I
     heard the first myself without any possibility of mistake, and rose
     <pb n="122"/>at once, though the slab lay heavy on my chest — — "</p>
    <p>"Most unwise," said Lady Arabel, "to touch that sort of thing late at night. I always have a
     little Benger myself."</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown happened to look at Richard. His eyes were shut, but he was smiling very broadly
     with tight lips, and his face was turned towards the ceiling. His fingers were very tense and
     busy on his lap, as though he were still fidgeting with magic. But her study of him was
     interrupted by the loud denouncing voice of the very venerable man who had led the procession
     of late-comers.</p>
    <p>"A dog in this hallowed place," he said, pointing at the deeply disconcerted Rupert who was
     weaving himself nervously in and out of his master's legs. "Never in all the forty years of my
     ministration here have I allowed such an outrage — — "</p>
    <p>"Gently, gently, my dear sir," protested the Vicar, a little roused. "I am the minister of
     this church, and the dog is mine. I was indeed about to turn it out when you entered, after
     which I lost sight of it for a moment. Rupert, go home."
     <pb n="123"/></p>
    <p>Rupert howled again, and lay down as if about to faint.</p>
    <p>"Forty years have I been Vicar of this parish," said the veteran, "and never — — "</p>
    <p>"What?" interrupted the Vicar, "Forty years Vicar of this parish. Then you must be Canon
     Burstley-Ripp. How very extraordinary, I always understood that he passed away quite ten years
     ago."</p>
    <p>He approached the old man and strove to button-hole him. The sheet at first foiled him in
     this intention, but he presently contented himself with seizing a little corner of it, by which
     he led his aged brother vicar into a corner. There they could be heard for some time
     misunderstanding each other in low earnest tones.</p>
    <p>"Ow, what a wicked ol' woman I bin an' bin," suddenly burst forth again the repentant
     knitter. "I bin an' stole 'arf a pound o' sugar off of the Eelite 'Atshop where I does a bit o'
     cleanin'. Ef I get out o' this alive, I swear I'll repay it an 'undredfold — that is ef I can
     get that much awf me sugar card...."</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown was becoming sleepy. A
     <pb n="124"/>blankness was invading her mind, and the talk in the crypt seemed to lose its
     meaning, and to consist chiefly of S's. She pondered idly on the family of children with their
     elders, all of whom were now studying each other with a certain look of disillusionment. It was
     a group whose relationships were difficult to make out, the ages of many of the children being
     unnaturally approximate. There seemed to be at least seven children under three years old, and
     yet they all bore a strong and regrettable family likeness. Several of the babies would hardly
     have been given credit for having reached walking age, yet none had been carried in. The woman
     who seemed to imagine herself the mother of this rabble was distributing what looked like
     hurried final words of advice. The father with a pensive eye was obviously trying to remember
     their names, and at intervals whispering to a man apparently twenty years his senior, whom he
     addressed as Sonny. It was all very confusing.</p>
    <p>A long dim stretch of time seemed to have passed when suddenly the note of a
     <pb n="125"/>bugle sprang out across space. Somehow the air at once felt cooler and more
     wholesome, the sound of the All-clear had something akin to the sight of the sun after a
     thunderstorm, lighting up a crouching whipped world.</p>
    <p>"The Trump at last," said Lady Arabel's garrulous neighbour, rising with alacrity, and
     twitching her sheet into more becoming folds. "I was just wondering — — "</p>
    <p>But at that moment the two Vicars approached, and the elder one, including both the spinster
     and the mysterious family in one glance, spoke in a clerical yet embarrassed voice.</p>
    <p>"Dear friends, a slight but inconvenient mistake has occurred, and I am afraid I must ask you
     to submit blindly to my guidance in a matter strangely difficult to explain, even as I — myself
     in much confusion — bow to the advice of my reverend friend here. It would be out of place — —
     "</p>
    <p>The spinster interrupted, and, by the way she did it, one saw that she was Chapel. "Excuse
     me, Canon," she said acidly, "but is not all discussion out of place at this solemn moment?"
     <pb n="126"/></p>
    <p>"Believe me, madam," replied the aged Burstley-Ripp. "You overrate the solemnity of the
     moment. I must earnestly ask you all to return with me to the places whence — labouring under
     an extraordinary error — we came to-night. I see that Mrs. Parachute trusts me, and is prepared
     to lead her little flock to rest again. You, madam — — "</p>
    <p>"Where Mrs. Parachute leads, far be it from me to seem behindhand," said the other, much
     ruffled, as she gathered her sheet about her. By the way she said it, one saw that she and Mrs.
     Parachute did not call. She bowed to Lady Arabel, and became satirical, even arch. "Good
     afternoon, Mrs. — er — , I am assured that the moment is not solemn, and therefore solemn it
     shall not be. To turn to lighter subjects, I hope I shall have the pleasure of meeting you and
     your delightful son and daughter again at no distant date, the moment then being genuinely
     solemn. I fear I have no visiting card on me, but — er — perhaps my slab just outside — very
     superior granite — would do as a substitute...."
     <pb n="127"/></p>
    <p>The pale party filed out of the crypt and disappeared. The remaining Vicar smote his brow,
     and addressed the now calm Rupert in a low voice, but with such unaccountable warmth that that
     harassed animal disappeared precipitately in the direction of his home.</p>
    <p>Lady Arabel, Sarah Brown, and Richard crossed the churchyard together.</p>
    <p>"Oh, my dears, look," said Lady Arabel. "How too too dretful, that bomb fell quite close to
     us. Do look how it has disturbed the graves...."
     <pb n="128"/>
     <pb n="129"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER VI</head>
    <head>AN AIR RAID SEEN FROM ABOVE</head>
    <p>
     <pb n="130"/>
     <pb n="131"/>The moonlight lay like cream upon the pavement when the witch and Harold her
     broomstick left the Higgins' doorstep. London was a still Switzerland in silver and star-grey,
     unblotted by people. There was a hint of pale green about the moonlight, and the lamps with
     their dim light downcast were like daffodils in faery fields.</p>
    <p>The witch mounted. Harold, who was every inch a thoroughbred and very highly strung, trembled
     beneath her, but not with fear. They reached Piccadilly Circus with supernatural speed, and
     flashed across it. The sound of people singing desultorily while taking shelter in the Tube
     floated up to them. Here the witch said "Yoop" to Harold, and he reared and shot upwards,
     narrowly missing the statue of One In A Bus-catching Attitude, which marks the middle of the
     Circus.
     <pb n="132"/></p>
    <p>As soon as the witch had out-distanced the noise of expectant London, she heard quite
     distinctly the approach of London's guests. They came with a chorus of many notes, all deep and
     dangerous.</p>
    <p>There were a few clouds wandering about among the stars, and to one of these the witch and
     her faithful Harold repaired. A cloud gives quite reasonable support to magic people, and most
     witches and wizards have discovered the delight of paddling knee-deep about those quicksilver
     continents. They wander along shining and changing valleys under a most ardent sky; they climb
     the purple thunderclouds, or launch the first snowflake of a blizzard; they spring from pink
     stepping-stone to pink stepping-stone of clouds each no bigger than a baby's hand, across great
     sunsets. Often when in London I am battling with a barrage of rain, or falling over unseen
     strangers into gutters during fogs, I think happily of the sunlit roof of cloud above my head,
     and of the witches and wizards, lying on their backs with their coats off, among cloud-meadows
     in a glory of perfect summer and sun.
     <pb n="133"/></p>
    <p>The witch, with one soothing hand on the bristling mane of her Harold, lay on her front on
     the cloud she had chosen, and looked down through a little hole in it. It was practically the
     only cloud present that would have afforded reasonable cover; the others were mere wisps of
     sky-weed floating in the moonlight.</p>
    <p>There was a greater chorus of aeroplanes below her now; the whole sky was ringing with it.
     The witch could hear a deep bass-voiced machine, a baritone, a quavering tenor, and — thin and
     sharp as a pin — a little treble sound that made Harold rear and struggle to be free.</p>
    <p>"Another witch," said the witch. "I was wondering why the Huns hadn't got their magic
     organised by now." She mounted her Harold and slipped off the cloud.</p>
    <p>The guns were shouting now, and the shells wailed and burst not so very far below them, but
     Harold trembled no longer. More quickly than a falling star he swooped, and in a second the
     alien witch was in sight, an unwieldy figure whose broomstick sounded
     <pb n="134"/>rather broken-winded, probably owing to the long-distance flight and to the
     fourteen stone of Teutonic magic on its back. There was a wicked-looking apparatus attached to
     the collar of the German broomstick, obviously designed to squirt unpleasant enchantments
     downward. This contrivance was apparently giving some trouble, for the German was so busy
     attending to it that at first she did not see or hear the approach of Harold and his rider. She
     was aroused to her danger by a heavy chunk of magic which struck and nearly unseated her. In a
     second, however, she was ready with a parrying enchantment, and the fight began. The two
     broomsticks reared and circled round each other, and over and under each other. From their
     riders' finger-tips magic of the most explosive kind crackled, and incantations of such potency
     were exchanged that, I am told, the tiles and chimney-pots of the streets below suffered a good
     deal. Round and round and over and under whirled the broomsticks, till the very spaces went
     mad, and London seemed to rush down nightmare slopes into a stormy sky, while
     <pb n="135"/>its lights swung from pole to pole and were entangled with the stars.</p>
    <p>Both broomsticks were by now so uproariously excited that neither witch was able to aim her
     magic missiles very carefully, and indeed it was not long before Harold passed entirely beyond
     control. After bucking violently once or twice, he gave a wild high cry that was like the wind
     howling through the fierce forest past of his race, and fell upon the other broomstick, fixing
     his bristles into its throat. The shock of the collision was too much for both witches. Our
     witch — if I may call her so — was shot over Harold's head, and landed on the ample breast of
     her adversary, who, in consequence, lost her balance. They fell together into space.</p>
    <p>"Oh, lost, lost, ..." cried our witch, and thoughts rushed through her mind of green safe
     places, and old safe years, and the little hut in a pale bluebell wood, where she was born. She
     had time to remember the blue ground, dimpled and starred with sunlight, and the way the bees
     pulled over the bluebells and swung on them to the
     <pb n="136"/>tune of cuckoos in a May mist; she had time to think of the green globe ghosts of
     the bluebells that haunted the wood after the spring was dead. Bluebells and being young were
     in all her thoughts, and it was some time before she noticed how slowly she and her enemy were
     falling.</p>
    <p>For they were locked together. And the enemy witch's cloak, an orthodox witch cloak except
     for its colour, which was German field-grey instead of red, was spread out like a parachute,
     and was supporting them upon their peaceful and almost affectionate descent.</p>
    <p>For all I know they might have alighted gently in the Strand, and the authorities might by
     now be regretting the capture of a most embarrassing and unaccountable prisoner. But something
     intervened. The cloud, like a sheep suffering from the lack of other sheep to follow, had not
     yet quitted the scene. The witches' battle had tended upward, and it had ended several hundred
     feet above the level of the cloud, which was apparently sinking. The downward course of the
     combatants' fall was therefore arrested,
     <pb n="137"/>and they found themselves still interlocked, prostrate and embedded, with their
     eyes and mouths full of woolly wisps of cloud.</p>
    <p>Our witch was the first to recover herself. She stood up and brushed herself, remarking: "By
     jove, that parachute cloak of yours is a great dodge. I wish I'd thought of it. I always keep
     my full-dress togs put away, like the ass that I am. A stitch or two, and a few lengths of
     whalebone would have done the trick."</p>
    <p>The German was an older woman, and less adaptable to the strange chances of War. She was
     silent for a few minutes, seated in the small crater made in the cloud by her fall. She was not
     exactly ugly. She had the sort of face about which one could not help feeling that one could
     have done it better oneself, or at least that one could have taken more trouble. It seemed
     moulded — even kneaded — carelessly, in very soft material. Beneath her open cloak her dress
     was of the ordinary German <hi>Reform-Kleid</hi> type, and her figure had the rather jelloid
     appearance of those who affect this style. Her regulation witch's hat was by
     <pb n="138"/>now, probably, in the Serpentine, and her round head was therefore disclosed, with
     two stout sand-coloured plaits pursuing each other round it.</p>
    <p>The witches faced each other for some seconds. A long way away they could hear the spitting
     and crackling sound of the two broomsticks fighting. Looking up, they could see the combatants,
     like black comets in collision. Our witch, who had good sight, saw that the enemy broomstick
     was upper-most, and that the writhing Harold was being shaken like a mouse. Their bristles were
     interlocked. One twig floated down between the witches, and our witch recognised it as coming
     from her poor Harold's mane. As, for this purpose, she brought her eyes to her immediate
     surroundings, it seemed to her suddenly that the sky was growing larger, and then she realised
     that this was because their refuge was growing smaller. The edges of the cloud were dissolving.
     She saw at last her peril and her disadvantage. If Harold should be killed or disabled she
     could never reach the earth again, except by means of a fatal fall of several thousand
     <pb n="139"/>feet. The enemy witch, with her ingenious cloak contrivance strapped securely
     about her, stood a reasonable chance of escape. But our witch was an amateur in War, she was
     without support, forlornly dressed in her faithful blue serge three-year-old, and her little
     squirrel tippet.</p>
    <p>Magic, as you know, has limitations. Fire is of course a plaything in magic hands. Water has
     its docile moments, the earth herself may be tampered with, and an incantation may call man or
     any of his possessions to attention. But space is too great a thing, space is the inconceivable
     Hand, holding aloft this fragile delusion that is our world. There is no power that can mock at
     space, there is no enchantment that is not lost between us and the moon, and all magic people
     know — and tremble to know — that in a breath, between one second and another, that Hand may
     close, and the shell of time first crack and then be crushed, and magic be one with nothingness
     and death and all other delusions. This is why magic, which treats the other elements as its
     servants,
     <pb n="140"/>bows before space, and has to call such a purely independent contrivance as a
     broomstick to its help in the matter of air-travel.</p>
    <p>The witches faced each other on their little unstable sanctuary in the kingdom of space. Our
     witch felt secretly sick, and at the same time she tore fear from her mind, and knew that death
     was but an imperfectly kept secret, and that not an evil one. After all, we have condemned it
     unheard.</p>
    <p>Both witches could talk a magic tongue, and make themselves mutually understood. Neither knew
     the other's natural tongue. But when our witch noticed several large ferocious tears rolling
     down her opponent's cheeks, she was able, by means of magic, to say: "Great Scott, my good
     person, what are you crying for?"</p>
    <p>"I am not crying," replied the German witch. "I would not allow one tear of mine to fall upon
     and water one possible grain of wheat in this accursed country of yours. Certainly I am not
     crying."</p>
    <p>"Accursed country?" echoed the astounded English witch. "How d'you mean — accursed? This is
     England, you
     <pb n="141"/>know. England hasn't done anything accursed. Aren't you muddling it up with
     Germany?"</p>
    <p>"England is the World Enemy," said the German, evidently pleased to meet someone to whom this
     information was fresh. "Throughout the ages she has been the Robber State, crushing the weaker
     nations, adding to her own wealth by treachery, and now forcing this war of aggression upon her
     peace-loving neighbours."</p>
    <p>Our witch laughed. She was forgetting her danger. "This is really rather funny," she said.
     "Do you know what's happened? You've been reading the <hi>Daily Mail</hi> and misunderstanding
     it. The whole of that quotation applied to Germany, not England. It's Germany that's being
     naughty. You made a mistake, but never mind, I won't repeat it."</p>
    <p>The German took no notice of this. The past three years had made her an adept in taking no
     notice.</p>
    <p>"And now," she added. "After all these weary months of hoping, and long-distance broomstick
     practice, and of
     <pb n="142"/>parachute practice, and of conflict with narrow officialdom, I have come — and
     this is the result. I am separated from my broomstick, which has all the germ-bombs hanging
     from its collar — the germs are those of dissension and riot — I am marooned upon an English
     cloud, with no enemy at my mercy but a paltry and treacherous non-combatant — — "</p>
    <p>"At your mercy," breathed our witch, remembering. She looked up. The broomsticks were closer
     now, and through the breathless air, amidst the dream-like firing of the guns below, she could
     hear the difficult gasping of the hard-pressed Harold, still fighting bravely but with hardly a
     twig on his head.</p>
    <p>The tide of space was coming in. The edge of the cloud was barely six inches from her hand.
     Our witch's mind overflowed with the thought of invasions and the coming in of tides. It seemed
     that all her life she had been living on a narrowing shore. She remembered all her dawns as
     precarious footholds of peace on a threatened rock, and all her evenings as golden sands
     sloping
     <pb n="143"/>down into encroaching sleep. She realised Everything as a little hopeless garrison
     against the army of Nothing.</p>
    <p>She clutched a pinch of cloud nervously, and it broke off in her hand. She recalled her
     senses with a devastating effort.</p>
    <p>"Do you mean to say," she said, after a moment, "that poor dear Germany really believes that
     she is right and we are wrong? I suppose, when you come to think of it, a man-eating tiger
     feels the same way. It fights with a high heart, and a hot reproach, just as we do — — "</p>
    <p>"We are Crusaders," said the German. "Crusaders at War with Evil."</p>
    <p>"Why, how funny — so are we," said our witch. "But then how very peculiar that two Crusaders
     should apparently be fighting each other. Where then is the Evil? In No Man's Land?"</p>
    <p>"We are fighting," recited the German glibly, "because England is the World Enemy. Throughout
     the ages she has been the Rob — — "</p>
    <p>There was a violent explosion quite close to them, and the cloud reeled and shook.
     <pb n="144"/> About a foot of the German end of it broke off and was dissolved.</p>
    <p>"We're within range of our guns," said our witch, looking down. "This cloud must be
     sinking."</p>
    <p>"It will never sink enough to save you," said the German, trying to conceal the nervousness
     with which she rearranged her rigid-looking cloak round her. She seemed to be sinking herself
     to a certain extent; perhaps the warmth of her emotions was melting the cloud beneath her.
     Certainly she now sat, apparently squat as an idol, her figure submerged in cloud to the
     waist.</p>
    <p>The English witch looked down, singing a little to keep up her <hi>morale</hi>. London looked
     exactly like the maps you buy for sixpence from sad-looking gentlemen in the Strand, only it
     was sown with a thin crop of lights, and was chiefly designed in grey and darker grey, and the
     Tubes did not show so indecently. With surprising clearness the rhythmic whispering of the
     trains and the scanty traffic could be heard, and once even the shrill characteristic voice of
     an ambulance. Somehow space did not
     <pb n="145"/>seem disturbed by these sounds; its quietness pressed upon the listeners' minds
     like a heavy dream, and there was no real believing in anything but space. Our witch felt she
     could have smudged London off the face of space with her finger, and the thought of seven
     million lives involved in the fate of that sliding chart carried no conviction to her. She
     forced into her mind the realisation of humanity, and of little lives lived in little
     rooms.</p>
    <p>"As one Crusader to another," she said, "do you find it does much good in the war against
     Evil to drop bombs on people in their homes? After all, every baby is good in bed, and even
     soldiers when on leave are anti-militarist."</p>
    <p>"It always does good to exterminate vermin in their lair," said the German, trying restlessly
     to raise herself more to the level of her lighter companion, who was still perched on the
     surface of the cloud. "It is at home that Evil is originated, it is at home that English women
     conceive and bear a new generation of enemies of the Right, it is at home that English children
     <pb n="146"/>are bred up in their marauding ways. It is on the home, the vital place of Evil,
     that the scourge should fall."</p>
    <p>"Oh, but surely not," said our witch eagerly. "It is at home that people are kindly and think
     what they will have for supper, and bathe their babies. Men come home when they are hurt or
     hungry, and women when they are lonely or tired. Nobody is taught anything stupid or
     international at home. You can bring death to a home, but never a righteous scourge. Nobody
     feels scourged or instructed by a bomb in their parlour, they just feel dead, and dead without
     a reason."</p>
    <p>The cloud was very small now. The filmy edges of it were faintly rising and falling like the
     seaweed frill of a rock in the sea. The witch kept her eyes on her opponent's face, because to
     look anywhere else gave her a white feeling in her head.</p>
    <p>"Crusades of the high explosive kind," she said, "can work only on battle-fields. Indeed,
     even on battle-fields — ah, what are we about, what are we about? We are
     <pb n="147"/>neither of us killing Evil, we are killing youth...."</p>
    <p>"I know, I know," wept the German witch. "My wizard fell at Vimy Ridge...."</p>
    <p>"You are talking magic at last," said our witch. "Dear witch, why don't you go home and ask
     how it can be a good plan for one Crusader against Evil to blow up another? How can two people
     be righteously scourging each other at the same time? It is like the old problem of two
     serpents eating each other, starting at the tail. There must be some misunderstanding
     somewhere. Or else some real Evil somewhere."</p>
    <p>"There is," said the German, recovering herself. "England is Evil. England is the World
     Enemy. Throughout the ages she has been the Robber State, crushing — — "</p>
    <p>But she had little luck. Once more she was interrupted by an explosion, a much louder one,
     directly above them. Our witch hardly heard the noise; she seemed suddenly to have found the
     climax of her life, and the climax was pain. There was pain and
     <pb n="148"/>a feeling of terrible change all over her, smothering her, and a super-pain in her
     shoulder. After a second or two as long as death, she realised dimly that she was all tensely
     strung to an attitude, like a marionette. Her hands were up trying to shield her head, her chin
     was pressed down to her drawn-up knees. Her blue serge shoulder was extraordinarily wet and
     immovable. She looked along the cloud. Her enemy was not there. There was a round hole in the
     cloud, and as she leaned painfully towards it, she could see a few of the lights of London, and
     something falling spasmodically towards them.</p>
    <p>The cloud had been shaken to its foundations by the two explosions, and the German witch, who
     had been seated perhaps on a seam in the material, or at any rate on one of the less stable
     parts of the fabric, had fallen through. Her parachute cloak, in passing through the hole in
     the cloud, had been turned inside out above her head, and rendered useless. Over and about her
     falling figure her broomstick darted helplessly, uttering curious sad cries, like a seagull's.
     <pb n="149"/></p>
    <p>Even as the English witch watched her enemy's disaster, the larger part of the cloud,
     weakened by all the shock and movement, broke away with a hissing sound. The witch's feet hung
     now over space, she dared not move; she had difficulty in steadying herself with her unwounded
     arm, for her hand could find only a quicksand of dissolving cloud to lean on. She had no
     thoughts left but thoughts of danger and of pain.</p>
    <p>But Harold the Broomstick came back. The witch heard a rustling sound close to her, and it
     startled her more than all the noise of the guns, which had come, as it seemed, from the
     forgotten other side of eternity. The rough head of Harold appeared over the cloud's edge, and
     insinuated itself pathetically under her arm. Very carefully and very painfully the witch
     reached a kneeling position, damaging her refuge with every movement in spite of her care. She
     gasped with pain, and Harold tried to look very strong and hopeful to comfort her. He
     straightened his back, and she crawled into the saddle. The tremor of their launching split the
     cloud into several parts, which
     <pb n="150"/>disintegrated. There was no more foot-hold on it; the tide had come up and
     submerged it.</p>
    <p>Harold the Broomstick was crippled, he stumbled as he flew, sometimes he dropped a score of
     feet, and span. He did stunts by mistake.</p>
    <p>They had not strength enough between them to get home. They made a forced landing in the
     silver loneliness of Kensington Gardens. It was a fortunate place, for there is much magic
     there. Wherever there are children who pretend, there grows a little magic in the air, and
     therefore the wind of Kensington Gardens thrills with enchantment, and the Round Pond, full of
     much pretence of great Armadas, crossed and re-crossed with the abiding wakes of ships full of
     treasure and romance, is a blessed lake to magic people.</p>
    <p>The witch bathed Harold, her broomstick, in the Round Pond. He evidently felt its healing
     quality at once, for after the first minute of immersion, he swam about exultantly, and shook
     drops full of moonlight out of his mane.
     <pb n="151"/></p>
    <p>The bugles sounded All-clear in many keys all round the ear's horizon; their sound matched
     the waning moonlight.</p>
    <p>The witch bathed her shoulder, and then she found her way to a little quiet place she knew
     of, where no park-keeper ever looks, a place where secret and ungardened daffodils grow in
     springtime, a place where all the mice and birds play unafraid, because no cat can find the way
     thither. You can see the Serpentine from that place, and the bronze shadows under its bridge,
     but no houses, and no railways, and no signs of London.</p>
    <p>Here the witch made a little fire, and leaned three sticks together over it; she lighted the
     fire with her finger-tip and hung over it the little patent folding cauldron, which she always
     carried on a chatelaine swinging from her belt. And she made a charm of daisy-heads, and
     spring-smelling grasses, and the roots of unappreciated weeds, and the mosses that cover the
     tiny faery cliffs of the Serpentine. Over the mixture she shook out the contents of one of her
     little paper packets of magic. All
     <pb n="152"/>this she boiled over her fire for many hours, sitting beside it in the silver
     darkness, with her knees drawn up and her hands clasped in front of them. The trees sprang up
     into the moonlight like dark fountains from the pools of their own shadows. Little shreds of
     cloud flowed wonderfully across the sky. There was no sound except the sound of the water, like
     an uncertain player upon a little instrument. The charm was still unfinished when the dawn
     passed over London, and the sun came up, the seed of another day, sown in a rich red soil. The
     trees of the Gardens remembered their daylight shadows again, and forgot their mystery. The
     water-birds, after examining their shoulder-blades with minute care for some moments, launched
     themselves upon a lake of diamonds. There seemed a veil of mist and bird-song over the world.
     The sudden song of the birds was like finding the hearing of one's heart restored, after long
     deafness.</p>
    <p>The witch anointed her shoulder with the charm, after having first made a drop of potion out
     of the bubbles in it. This potion she drank, and was healed of her wound
     <pb n="153"/>and her weariness, and of all desires except a desire to sleep with her face among
     the daffodils. She was the most beautifully alone person in the world that morning; nobody
     could have found her. A thin string of very blue smoke went up from her faint fire and was
     tangled among the boughs of a flowering tree, but the coarse eye of a park-keeper could never
     have seen it. She had escaped from the net of the cruel hours; for her the stained world was
     washed clean; for her all horror held its breath; for her there was absolute spring, and an
     innocent sun, and the shadows of daffodils upon closed eyes....
     <pb n="154"/>
     <pb n="155"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER VII</head>
    <head>THE FAERY FARM</head>
    <p>
     <pb n="156"/>
     <pb n="157"/>Sarah Brown, finding herself unfetched by the witch, went home alone as soon as
     the 'buses began putting out to sea after the storm. She expected to find the witch at home,
     but only the Dog David and Peony were in the House of Living Alone. David lay on Peony's bed,
     and Peony under it. Sarah Brown saw them as she passed their open door.</p>
    <p>"Ow Marmaduke!" said Peony, "is it all over? Are you sure? Them 'uns is so bloody deceitful
     you never know but what they might go an' blow a bugle or two to mike believe they'd done, an'
     then drops bombs on us just as we was comin' 'appily out from under our beds."</p>
    <p>Peony, with a touching faith in the combined protective powers of twelve inches of mattress
     and nine inches of dog, had been reading a little paper book called
     <pb n="158"/>
     <hi>Love in Society</hi> by the light of an electric torch.</p>
    <p>"It's all truly over," said Sarah Brown, who had come home through a roar of rumour. "They
     say we've brought down at least one Boche. In fact the ferryman says his aunt telephoned that
     the special on her corner says a female Boche was brought down. But that hardly sounds likely.
     Hasn't the witch come home yet?"</p>
    <p>"Lawd no," replied Peony. "The dear ol' Soup never comes 'ome of a moonlight night. It's my
     belief she goes to Maiden'ead among the Jews, to keep out of the wiy, and 'oo's to blime
     'er?"</p>
    <p>"Well, that's all right," said Sarah Brown. "For now I shall be able to buy — without pawning
     anything for the moment — a little land outfit from stock. I know she has some."</p>
    <p>The night was by then far from young, in fact it was well into its second childhood. But
     Sarah Brown and the Dog David sought and tried on land outfits for several hours.</p>
    <p>The shop was divided into three horizontal departments. Nearest the floor
     <pb n="159"/>were the foodstuffs; biscuit tins buttressed the counter on every side; regiments
     of Grape-nuts, officered by an occasional Quaker Oat, stood in review order all round the lower
     shelves. On the counter little castles of tinned fruit were built, while bins beneath it held
     the varied grain, cereal, and magic stock. About on a level with one's head the hardware
     department began: frying-pans lolled with tin coffee-pots over racks, dust-pans divorced from
     their brushes were platonically attached to flat-irons or pie-dishes, Stephen's Inks were
     allied with penny mugs or tins of boot polish in an invasion of the middle shelves, and a
     wreath of sponges crowned the champion of a row of kettles in shining armour. Against the
     ceiling the drapery section was found. Overalls, ready-made breeches, babies' socks, and pink
     flannelette mysteries hung doubled up as if in pain over strings nailed to the rafters. From
     this department Sarah Brown, balanced upon three large biscuit tins placed on the counter,
     chose her outfit with vanity and care. The general effect was not good, but she did not know
     this, for she studied
     <pb n="160"/>the parts separately in a six-inch mirror. She was filled with a simple pleasure.
     For she was always absurdly moved by little excitements, and by any prospect of a changed
     to-morrow. She was not really used to being alive at all, and that is what made her take to
     magic so kindly.</p>
    <p>"In six hours," she said, "I shall be on my way to something utterly new."</p>
    <p>And in six hours she was on her way, whistling, across the Parish of Faery. The Dog David ran
     in front of her among the daisies. The rabbits can never be caught in this land of happy
     animals, but they give good sport and always play fair.</p>
    <p>David Blessing Brown, a dog of independent yet loving habit, had spent about four-fifths of
     his life in the Brown family. He was three years old, and though ineligible for military
     service, made a point of wearing khaki about his face, and in a symmetrical heart-shaped spot
     near his tail. To Sarah Brown he was the Question and the Answer, his presence was a constant
     playtime for her mind; so well was he loved that he seemed to her to move in a little mist and
     <pb n="161"/>clamour of love. With every one else she held but lame intercourse, but her Dog
     David and she withheld no passing thought from each other. They could often be heard by
     unmattering landladies and passers-by exchanging views in the strong Suffolk accent that was a
     sort of standing joke between them. I believe that Sarah Brown had loved the Dog David so much
     that she had given him a soul. Certainly other dogs did not care for him. David said that they
     had found out that his second name was Blessing, and that they laughed at him for it. His face
     was seamed with the scars of their laughing. But I know that the enmity had a more fundamental
     reason than that. I know that when men speak with the tongues of angels they are shunned and
     hated by men, and so I think that when dogs approach humanity too nearly they are banished from
     the love of their own kind.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown was not altogether unfamiliar with the Parish of Faery, but she never failed to
     be surprised by the enchantment of the Enchanted Forest. The Green Ride
     <pb n="162"/>runs straight through it, so incredibly straight that as you walk along it the end
     of it is at the end of your sight, and is like a star in a green sky. There is a dream that
     binds your mind as you cross the forest; it is like an imitation of eternity, so that, as you
     pass into the forest's shade, time passes from before you, and, as you pass out of it, you seem
     to have lived a thousand quiet and utterly forgotten lives. Clocks and calendars have no
     meaning in the forest; the seasons and the hours haunt it at their will, and abide by no law.
     Just as the sun upon a stormy day makes golden a moving and elusive acre in our human woods, so
     the night in the Enchanted Forest comes and goes like a ghost upon the sight of lovers of the
     night. For there you may step, unastonished, from the end of a day into its beginning; there
     the summer and the winter may dodge each other round one tree; there you may see at one glance
     a spring hoar frost and an autumn trembling of airs, a wild cherry tree blossoming beside a
     tawny maple. The forest is so deep and so thick that it provides its own sky,
     <pb n="163"/>and can enjoy its own impulses, and its own quiet anarchy. There you forget that
     sky of ours across whose face some tyrant drives our few docile seasons in conventional
     order.</p>
    <p>I think the Dog David in his own way shared the dream that leads wayfarers through the
     Enchanted Forest. When he came out with Sarah Brown under the tasselled arch of Travellers' Joy
     that crosses the end of the Green Ride, he was all shining and dewy with adventure, and his
     tail was upright, as though he were pretending that it carried a flag.</p>
    <p>On an abrupt hill in the middle of an enormous green meadow a Castle stood, just as Richard
     had predicted. It was To Let, and was not looking its best. Some man of enterprise, taking
     advantage of its forlorn condition, had glued an advertisement upon its donjon keep. You could
     almost have measured that advertisement in acres; it recommended a face cream, and represented
     a lady with a face of horrible size, whose naturally immaculate complexion was marred by the
     rivets and loopholes of
     <pb n="164"/>the donjon keep itself, which protruded in rather a distressing way.</p>
    <p>Oak trees stood round the foot of that pale hill, and the general effect was rather that of
     parsley round a ham.</p>
    <p>Between two oaks Sarah Brown, following directions, found the beginning of the Daisified
     Path. There were not only daisies all over the path but real violets on either side of it. The
     daisies looked one in the face, but the violets did not, because they had morbidly bad manners.
     Still of course manners are very small change and count for very little; the violet, being an
     artist, is entitled to any manners it likes, while the daisy has no temperament whatever, and
     no excuse for eccentricity. Grasshoppers tatted industriously and impartially among the daisies
     and the violets.</p>
    <p>Here outside the forest there was weather again, and the weather was more promising than
     generous. It continued to promise all day without exactly explaining what its promise was, and
     without achieving any special fulfilment. Fine silver lines of sunlight were ruled at a steep
     angle across a grey slate view.
     <pb n="165"/></p>
    <p>At the gate of Higgins Farm, Sarah Brown was a little disconcerted to find a small dragon. It
     was coiled round a tree beside the clipped box archway. It was not a very fine specimen, being
     of a brownish-green colour, and having lost the tip of one wing. Its spine was serrated,
     especially deeply between its shoulder blades, where it could raise a sort of crest if angered
     or excited. But at present it was asleep, its saturnine and rather wistful face rested upon one
     scaly paw.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown was uncertain what to do, but the Dog David took the matter into his own paws by
     mistake. He had just met one of the castle dogs, one of those tremulous-tailed creatures who
     spend themselves in a rather pathetic effort to sustain an imaginary reputation for humour.
     David retorted to this dog's first facetious onslaught with a kindly quip, they trod on each
     other once or twice with extravagant gestures, and then parted hysterically, each supposing
     himself to be pursued by the other. It was then that David tripped over the dragon's barbed
     tail. David squeaked, and
     <pb n="166"/>the dragon awoke. It uncoiled itself suddenly like a broken spring.</p>
    <p>"Gosh," it said. "Asleep again! I was waiting for you, and the sun on my back always makes me
     sleepy. I am the foreman. Higgins telephoned that you were coming."</p>
    <p>It preceded her through the little green archway that led to the farm. The sight reminded
     Sarah Brown of watching from Golders Green Tube Station the train one has just missed dive into
     the tunnel. She followed.</p>
    <p>On the other side of the archway the whole view of the plain called Higgins Farm met the
     adventurer. The farm-buildings were heaped graciously together on a little wave in the sea of
     ploughed fields. Except for two pale ricks in their midst, they exactly matched their
     surroundings, they were plastered dark red, and thatched with very old green and brown thatch.
     Beyond the buildings was a little wood, its interior lighted up with bluebells, and this wood
     merged into an orchard, where a white pony and an auburn pig strove apparently to eat the same
     blade of grass. The various
     <pb n="167"/>sections of the farm land lay mapped out in different intensities of brown, very
     young green, and maturer green, and each section was dotted with people. They seemed small
     people even from a distance, and, as Sarah Brown advanced at the tail of the dragon, she saw
     that the workers were all indeed under ordinary human size. The tallest, a man guiding a
     miniature plough behind a tall horse, might have reached Sarah Brown's shoulder. None of them
     seemed hard at work, they stood talking in little groups. One group as they passed it was
     trafficking in cigarette cards. "I want to get my Gold Scale set of English Kings complete," a
     voice was saying tragically. "Has nobody got Edward the Confessor?" None of them took any
     notice of the foreman.</p>
    <p>"I'm afraid I haven't got the gift of discipline," sighed the dragon. "And fairies are of
     course abnormally undisciplined creatures. Still, we simply can't get any one else, and Higgins
     will not apply for a few German prisoners. Get on with your work, you people, do. There, you
     see, they defy
     <pb n="168"/>me to an extent. Ever since the cowmen dipped me in the horse-pond my authority's
     gone — gone where the good niggers go."</p>
    <p>I find that there are quite a lot of people who cannot say the word "gone" without adding the
     clause about the good niggers. These people have vague minds, sown like an allotment with
     phrases in grooves. Directly the dragon said "to an extent" without qualifying the extent, one
     saw why it had no gift of discipline.</p>
    <p>"I wouldn't attempt this job," it continued, winding breathlessly along the rutty road, "only
     I am under a great obligation to Richard Higgins. I am a <hi>protidgy</hi> of his, you know, he
     rescued me from a lot of mischievous knights who were persecuting me. One of them had tied his
     tin hat to my tail, I remember, and the rest were trying to stick their nasty spears between my
     scales. Really, you know, it was quite dangerous. I have known a fellow's eye put out that way.
     I am not very good at fighting, though I might have tackled one at a time. Richard Higgins rode
     right into the midst of them, knocking them right
     <pb n="169"/>and left. Gosh, he gave them a talking to, and they slank away. He took my case up
     after that, made enquiries, and gave me this job. We scrape along somehow, but I'm afraid I'm
     not really suited for it."</p>
    <p>They reached a part of a field in which broad beans were enjoying an innocent childhood among
     white butterflies.</p>
    <p>"If you wouldn't mind," said the dragon shyly, "I should like you to hoe between the rows of
     these beans. You will find a hoe against the big stack. This is your row, I reserved it for
     you."</p>
    <p>All the other rows were occupied by fairy women with their skirts tucked up — for only your
     amateur land-woman wears breeches. They all had hoes, but were not using them much. They were
     singing curious old round songs like summer dreams; you could hear strange fragments of phrases
     passing from voice to voice. They took no notice of Sarah Brown, and she began to work.</p>
    <p>"Oh, my One," she said to David. "How happy this is. No wonder they sing. Any one must sing
     working like this
     <pb n="170"/>in great fields. Why, I even remember that the Shropshire Lad whistled once by
     mistake, while ploughing, on his own admission, until a fatalistic blackbird recalled him to
     his usual tragic mind."</p>
    <p>David sat uncomfortably on a broad bean, protesting against this new mania. For a moment he
     had thought that she was seeking for a mouse with some patent mouse-finding implement. He had
     even tried to help her, and turned over a clod with a critical paw, but one sniff had showed
     him the empty futility of the thing.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown hoed rather happily for a couple of hours, and then she began to count the beans
     still waiting trustfully in the queue, waiting to be attended to and freed from their
     embarrassments. There were ninety-six, she decided, standing up ostensibly to greet an
     aeroplane. She became very glad of the occasional aeroplanes that crossed above her field, and
     gave her an excuse for standing with a straight back to watch them. Aeroplanes, crossing singly
     or in wild-bird formations, are so common in the sky of Faery that every one in those
     <pb n="171"/>parts, while turning his own eyes inevitably upwards, secretly thinks his
     neighbour lamentably rustic and unsophisticated for looking at them.</p>
    <p>Every aeroplane that crosses Faery feels, I suppose, the reflected magic from the land below,
     for there is never one with the barest minute to spare that does not pause and try to be clever
     over Higgins Farm. You may see one industriously climbing the clouds over the Enchanted Forest,
     evidently trying hard to be intent on its destination. You may see it falter, struggling with
     its sense of duty, and then break weakly into a mild figure eight. The ragged rooks of Faery at
     once hurry into the air to show their laborious imitator how this should be done. The spirit of
     frivolous competition enters into the aeroplane, its duty is flung to the winds. It flaunts
     itself up and down once or twice, as if to say: "Now look, everybody, I'm going to be clever."
     Then it goes mad. It leaps upon imaginary Boches, it stands upon its head and falls downward
     until the very butterflies begin to take cover, it stands upon its tail and falls upward, it
     <pb n="172"/>writes messages in a flowing hand across the sky and returns to cross the t's. It
     circles impertinently round your head, fixing its bold tricolour eye upon you until you begin
     to think there must be something wrong with your appearance. It bounds upon a field of onions
     and rebounds in the same breath from the topmost cloud of heaven. The rooks return
     disconsolately to their nests.</p>
    <p>Then you may see the erring machine suddenly remember itself, and check itself in the act of
     some new paroxysm. It remembers the European War that gave it birth; it thinks of its mates
     scanning the sky for its coming; its frivolity ebbs suddenly. The eastern sky becomes once more
     its highway instead of its trapeze. It collects its wits, emits a few contrite bubbles of
     smoke, and leaps beyond sight.</p>
    <p>Whenever this happened, the female fairies behaved in a very plebeian and forward manner,
     waving their hoes at each machine, encouraging it by brazen gestures to further extravagances,
     and striving to reach its hearing with loud shrill cries.
     <pb n="173"/> There was very little difference between these fairies and other lady
     war-workers. In fact they were only distinguishable by their stature and by the empty and
     innocent expression of their faces. Also perhaps by their tuneful singing, and by a habit of
     breaking out suddenly into country dances between the bean-rows.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown, who worked a great deal more industriously than any one else in sight, soon
     overtook them, and while conscious of that touch of interested scorn always felt by the One
     towards the Herd, found relief in watching their vagaries, and presently in speaking to
     them.</p>
    <p>For she needed relief, poor Sarah Brown, her disabilities were catching her up; a hoarse
     contralto cough was reminding her of many doctors' warnings against manual work. She could
     feel, so to speak, the distant approaching tramp of that pain in her side under whose threat
     she had lived all her life. But there were seventy-five beans yet.</p>
    <p>The note of her hoe, a high note not quite true pitched, clamoured monotonously
     <pb n="174"/>upon her brain. Three blisters and a half were persecuting her hands.</p>
    <p>"Let them blist," she said defiantly. "This row of beans was given me to hoe, and Death
     itself shall not take it from me."</p>
    <p>She could almost imagine she saw Death, waiting for her tactfully beyond the last bean. She
     had no sense of proportion. She was so very weary of having her life interrupted by her
     weakness that anything that she had begun to do always seemed to her worth finishing, even
     under torture. To finish every task, in spite of all hindrance, was her only ambition, but it
     was almost always frustrated.</p>
    <p>Seventy more beans. "Three score and ten," thought Sarah Brown. "What's that? Only a
     lifetime." She bent to her work.</p>
    <p>A great clump of buttercups bestrode her bean row, and as after a struggle she dragged its
     protesting roots from the earth, something fell from it.</p>
    <p>"Oh, a nest," she gasped. "Look, I have hoed up a nest."</p>
    <p>"Good gracious," exclaimed a fairy.
     <pb n="175"/> "Look what she's done. It's Clement's nest, poor chap, he only married in
     February. Say, girls, here's Clement's semi-detached gone up."</p>
    <p>Cries of consternation were heard from every bean-row.</p>
    <p>Clement's nest was really almost more than semi-detached. It had been but lightly wedged
     between two buttercup stalks. The two eggs in it were at once unseated, and one was broken.
     Sarah Brown was deeply distressed.</p>
    <p>"What a blind fool I am," she said, trying helplessly to replace the nest. "Won't Clement
     ever come back?"</p>
    <p>"Mrs. Clement won't," said the nearest fairy. "She is almost hysterical about the sanctity of
     the home, and all that. She'll probably get a divorce now."</p>
    <p>"Oh, poor Clement, poor Clement," said Sarah Brown. "Will he be terribly cut up?"</p>
    <p>"There he is," replied the fairy, pointing upward. "He's watching you. That's Clement's voice
     you hear."</p>
    <p>"Clement's voice," exclaimed Sarah
     <pb n="176"/> Brown. "Singing like that? Why, he sounds perfectly happy."</p>
    <p>"Perfectly happy," mocked the fairy. "His family only sings like that when it's upset.
     Perfectly happy indeed! Can't you understand tragedy when you hear it?"</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown with despairing care tucked the nest up under a bean, and replaced the unbroken
     egg.</p>
    <p>"Do you mean to tell me, then," she said, after a busy painful pause, "that Shelley probably
     misunderstood that lark he wrote a poem about? He called it a blithe spirit, you know, because
     it sang. Do you suppose it wasn't one?"</p>
    <p>"Certainly not," said the fairy. "I don't know the actual facts of the case, but without a
     doubt your friend Shelley was standing on the unfortunate bird's nest all the time he was
     writing his poem."</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown, with a deep sigh, began hoeing again.</p>
    <p>Fifty beans yet.</p>
    <p>She had altogether ceased to find pleasure in the day. Pain is an extinguisher that can put
     out the sun. She had ceased to
     <pb n="177"/>find pleasure in the singing of the birds, the voice of the pigeon sounded to her
     no more than an unbeautiful falsetto growl. She was irritated by the fact that the cuckoo had
     only one song to sing. She tried not to hoe in time to that song, but the monotony of it
     possessed her. Her row of beans stretched in front of her right across the world; every time
     she looked along it the end seemed farther away. Every time she raised her hoe the sword of
     pain slipped under her guard.</p>
    <p>The Dog David, impatient of her unnatural taste in occupations, had forsaken her. She could
     trace his course by a moving ripple across the potato patch, just as a shark's movement seams
     the sea.</p>
    <p>Forty beans.</p>
    <p>Time wears a strangely different guise out of doors. Under the sun time stands almost still.
     Only when every minute is a physical effort do you discover that there really are sixty minutes
     in an hour, and that one hour is very little nearer to the evening than another. People who
     work indoors under the government of clocks
     <pb n="178"/>never meet time face to face. Their quick seconds are dismissed by the clicking of
     typewriters, and when their typewriters fall silent, their day is over. We of Out of Doors have
     a daily eternity to contend with during which only our hands are busy; our minds may grow old
     and young again between sunrise and sunset; the future may be remade in an hour, hope killed
     and reborn before a blackbird's song is over. We know the length of days. And after many slow
     months of stress we come back again, old and bewildered with much silence and much wondering,
     to our friends in offices, and find them unchanged, floating innocently on the surface of
     time.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown dropped her hoe and fell upon her knees.</p>
    <p>"I can't hoe any more," she said. "There are twenty-five more beans, but I can't hoe
     them."</p>
    <p>"Why should you?" asked the nearest fairy indifferently. "The foreman never notices if we
     shirk. We always do."</p>
    <p>"I said I would hoe this row," said Sarah Brown. "But I am accursed. It is
     <pb n="179"/>a good thing at least to know one's limitations."</p>
    <p>Even in affliction she was prosy.</p>
    <p>"I would advise you to go and have your dinner," another fairy said. "Only that I ate your
     sandwiches as I passed just now. But I left a little lemonade in your bottle. Go under the
     trees and drink it."</p>
    <p>"I can't move," said Sarah Brown.</p>
    <p>"Sit there then," said the fairies, and passed on, tickling but not uprooting the weeds in
     their rows. Fairies are never ill. They have immortal bodies, but no souls. If they see you in
     pain, they simply think you are flaunting your superiority and your immortal soul in their
     faces.</p>
    <p>The dragon undulated up the field. "Very nicely hoed," he said, looking vaguely at Sarah
     Brown's row. "Much better than the other rows. Having your dinner? Quite right too."</p>
    <p>He never noticed the twenty-five unhoed beans.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown sat on the edge of a shore of green shadow, and a sea of sun speckled with
     buttercups was before her. David
     <pb n="180"/> Blessing came and leaned against her. His first intentions were good, he kissed
     her hurriedly on the chin, but after that he kissed the sandwich bag.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown wondered whether she could cut her throat with a hoe.</p>
    <p>"Suicide while of sound mind," she said. "The said mind being entirely sick of its unsound
     body."</p>
    <p>If she sat absolutely still and upright the pain was bearable. But even to think of movement
     brought tears of pain to her eyes. She detached her mind from her predicament, and sank into a
     warm tropical sea of thought. She was no real thinker, but she thought much about thinking, and
     was passionately interested in watching her own mind at work. Thought was like sleep to her,
     she sank deeply into it without reaching anything profound, nothing resulted but useless
     dreams, and a certain comforting and defiant intimacy with herself.</p>
    <p>She thought of Richard, and wished that she could have hoed a blessing into every bean of his
     that she had hoed. She noted half-consciously and without surprise that
     <pb n="181"/>the thought of him was beautiful to her. She could not conjure up his face before
     her mind, because she always forgot realities, and only remembered dreams. She could not
     imagine the sound of his voice, she could not recall anything that he had said. Yet she felt
     again the magic feeling of meeting him, and dreamt of all the things that might have happened,
     and that might yet happen, yet never would happen, between him and her. All the best things
     that she remembered had only happened in her dreams, her imagination no sooner sipped the first
     sip of an experience than it conjured up for her great absurd satisfying draughts of nectar,
     for which the waking Sarah Brown might thirst in vain. But there was no waking Sarah Brown. Her
     life was only a sleep-walking; only very rarely did she awake for a moment and feel ashamed to
     see how alert was the world about her.</p>
    <p>So she thought of Richard, not of Richard's Richard, but of some pale private Richard of her
     own.</p>
    <p>The approach of Richard upon a white
     <pb n="182"/>horse for some time seemed only an extension of her dream. It was only when she
     realised that he was riding up her bean-row, and partially undoing the work of her hoe, that
     she awoke suddenly with a start, and caught and tore her breath upon a pin of pain.</p>
    <p>It seemed that the afternoon had now long possessed the fields, it had wakened into a live
     and electric blue the Enchanted Forest which she had last noticed shimmering in its noon
     green.</p>
    <p>All the workers at the approach of Richard were working busily, bent ostentatiously in the
     form of hairpins up and down their rows. The dragon was rippling anxiously along at the heels
     of the white horse; a helpless hoping for the best expressed itself in every spike along his
     spine.</p>
    <p>"I don't really know why she's idling like that," Sarah Brown heard him say in his breathy
     pathetic voice. "I left her hard at work. They're all the same when my back's turned. A fellow
     needs to have eyes at the tip of his tail."</p>
    <p>"Are you suffering from that Leverhulme six-hour-working-day sort of feeling?" asked
     <pb n="183"/> Richard politely of Sarah Brown, in the manner of an advertisement of a cure for
     indigestion, as he approached. "I think it's just splendid how receptive and progressive
     working people are in these days."</p>
    <p>"I was meditating suicide," replied Sarah Brown candidly, if faintly. "I am a stricken and
     useless parasite on the face of your fine earth. But my hoe is too blunt."</p>
    <p>"I have a pocket-knife with three blades I could lend you," said Richard, slapping himself
     enquiringly over several pockets. "Or would you rather try a natty little spell I thought of
     this morning while I was shaving. I think any one stricken might find it rather useful."</p>
    <p>"Ah, give it to me. Give it to me," said Sarah Brown.</p>
    <p>The pain was like a wave breaking upon her, carrying her away from her safe shore of shadow,
     to be lost in seething and suffocating seas without rest. Her eyes felt dried up with fever,
     and whenever she shut them, the darkness was filled with a jumble of nauseating squares in blue
     upon
     <pb n="184"/>a mustard-coloured background. The smell of beans was terrible.</p>
    <p>Richard fumbled with something very badly folded up in newspaper. He also tried ineffectively
     to light a match by wiping it helplessly against his riding breeches. He seemed to have none of
     the small skill in details that comes to most people before they grow up. He did everything as
     if he were doing it for the first time.</p>
    <p>"I had nothing but the <hi>Morning Post</hi> to wrap it in," he murmured. "I'm afraid that
     may have spoilt the magic a little."</p>
    <p>It was the dragon finally who produced the necessary light. After watching Richard with the
     anxious sympathy of one ineffectual for another, it said: "Let me," and kindly breathed out a
     little flame, which set the packet aflare for a moment.</p>
    <p>The ashes fluttered down from Richard's hand among the beans, and a thin violet stalk of
     smoke went up.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown smelt the unmistakable sour smell of magic, and saw soundless words moving
     Richard's little khaki moustache. Then she found that she had disappeared.
     <pb n="185"/></p>
    <p>She had never done this before, she had always been present to disturb and interrupt herself.
     She had never seen the world before, except through the little glazed peepholes, called eyes,
     through which her everyday self rather wistfully believed that it could see. Now, of course,
     she knew what seeing was, and for the first time she was aware of the real sizes of things.
     Poor man measures all things by the size of his own foot. He looks complacently at the print of
     his boot in the mud, and notices that the ant which he crushed was not nearly as big as his
     foot, therefore the ant does not matter to him. He also notices that those same feet of his
     would not be able to walk to the moon within a reasonable time, therefore the moon does not
     matter to him.</p>
    <p>But Sarah Brown had disappeared, and therefore could not measure anything. The spider strode
     from hill to hill, with the wind rushing through the hair on his back. The blue sky was just a
     lampshade, clipped on to the earth to shield it from the glare of the gods, beyond it was a
     mere roof of
     <pb n="186"/>eternity, pricked with a few billion stars to keep it well ventilated.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown had for a while all the fun of being a god. She was nowhere and she was
     everywhere. She could have counted the hairs on David's head. The world waved like a flower
     upon a thin purple stalk of smoke....</p>
    <p>Her eyes began to see again. She was aware, of the hollowed tired eyes of Richard fixed upon
     her. The dragon dawned once more upon her sight, it was inquisitively watching developments,
     while pretending to claw a weed or two out of a neighbouring bean-row.</p>
    <p>The horizon was rusty with a rather heavy sunset. The fields were full of twilight and empty
     of fairies.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown came to herself with a start, she was shocked to find that she had opened her
     mouth to say something absolutely impossible to Richard. David's chin was resting on her hand.
     Her side felt frozen and dangerous but not painful.</p>
    <p>"It didn't altogether answer," said Richard. "I'm afraid the wrapping was
     <pb n="187"/>a mistake. A spell of that strength ought to have set you dancing in three
     minutes. I'll take you home on my horse. His name is Vivian."</p>
    <p>The Horse Vivian, who was so white as to be almost phosphorescent in the dusk, was now
     further illuminated by a little red light on his breast, and a little green light on his tail.
     Richard was fond of making elaborate and unnecessary arrangements like this, while neglecting
     to acquire skill in the more usual handicrafts.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown, a person of little weight, was placed astride on the back of the Horse Vivian.
     Richard walked beside. The dragon nodded good-bye, and disappeared into its home, a low
     tunnel-like barn, evidently built specially for it, with a door at each end, and a conveniently
     placed chimney which enabled it to breathe enough fire to cook its meals without suffocating
     itself.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown never saw the dragon again, but it stayed always in her memory as a puzzled soul
     born tragically out of its time, a shorn lamb, so to speak, to whom the wind had not been
     sufficiently tempered.
     <pb n="188"/></p>
    <p>Now this ride home, through the Enchanted Forest, on a tall horse, with Richard walking
     beside her, was the most perfect hour of Sarah Brown's life.</p>
    <p>The Enchanted Forest is only an accumulation of dreams, and from every traveller through it
     it exacts toll in the shape of a dream. By way of receipt, to every traveller it gives a
     darling memory that neither death nor hell nor paradise can efface.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown knew that her dream and Richard's could never meet. The fact that he was thinking
     of some one else all the way home was not hidden from her. But she was a person used to living
     alone, she could enjoy quite lonely romances, and never even envy real women, whose romances
     were always made for two. She was not a real woman, she was morbidly bodiless. Strange though
     it may seem, the kind, awkward, absent-minded touch of Richard as he had lifted her on to the
     Horse Vivian's back had been for her the one flaw in that enchanted ride. She could not bear
     touch. She had no pleasure in seeing or feeling the skin and homespun that encloses men
     <pb n="189"/>and women. She hated to watch people feeding themselves, or to see her own thin
     body in the mirror. She ought really to have been born a poplar tree; a human body was a gift
     wasted on her.</p>
    <p>As they passed along the Green Ride, the red light from the Horse Vivian's neck made a sort
     of heralding ghost before them on the grass. Bats darted above them for a few yards at a time,
     and were twitched aside as though by a string or a reminding conscience. The telegraph wires,
     bound for the post office of Faery, run through the Enchanted Forest, and the poles in the
     faint light were like tall crucifixes. A long way off, through the opening at the end of the
     Forest, were the little lights of Mitten Island.</p>
    <p>"Do you know," said Richard — and this is unfortunately the sort of thing that young men do
     say at silent and enchanted moments — "that if all the magic in this Forest were collected
     together and compressed into a liquid form, it would be enough to stop the War in one
     moment?"</p>
    <p>"My hat!" said Sarah Brown. "In one moment?"
     <pb n="190"/></p>
    <p>"In one moment."</p>
    <p>"My hat!" said Sarah Brown.</p>
    <p>"The powers of magic haven't been anything like thoroughly estimated even yet," said
     Richard.</p>
    <p>"I suppose the War was made by black magic," suggested Sarah Brown, trying to talk
     intelligently and to be faithful to her own thoughts at the same time.</p>
    <p>"Good Lord, no," replied Richard. "The worst of this war is that it has nothing whatever to
     do with magic of any sort. It was made and is supported by men who had forgotten magic, it is
     the result of the coming to an end of a spell. Haven't you noticed that a spell came to an end
     at the beginning of the last century? Why, doesn't almost every one see something lacking about
     the Victorian age?"</p>
    <p>"Something certainly died with Keats and Shelley," sighed Sarah Brown.</p>
    <p>"Oh well," said Richard, "I don't know about books. I can't read, you know. But obviously
     what was wrong with the last century was just that it didn't believe in fairies."
     <pb n="191"/></p>
    <p>"Does this century believe in fairies? If the spell came to an end, how is it that we are so
     magic now?"</p>
    <p>"This century knows that it doesn't know everything," said Richard. "And as for spells — we
     have started a new spell. That's the curious part of this War. So gross and so impossible and
     so unmagic was its cause, that magic, which had been virtually dead, rose again to meet it. The
     worse a world grows, the greater will magic grow to save it. Magic only dies in a tepid world.
     I think there is now more magic in the world than ever before. The soil of France is alive with
     it, and as for Belgium — when Belgium gets back home at last she will find her desecrated house
     enchanted.... And the same applies to all the thresholds in the world which fighting-men have
     crossed and will never cross again, except in the dreams of their friends. That sort of austere
     and secret magic, like a word known by all and spoken by none, is pretty nearly all that is
     left to keep the world alive now...."</p>
    <p>Richard seemed to be becoming less and
     <pb n="192"/>less of a man and more and more of a wizard the farther he penetrated into the
     Enchanted Forest. He was saying things that would have embarrassed him very much had they been
     said in the Piccadilly Restaurant, even after three glasses of champagne. For this reason,
     although the borders of the Enchanted Forest are said to be widening, it is to be hoped that
     they will not encroach beyond the confines of the Parish of Faery. What would happen if its
     trees began to seed themselves in the Strand? Imagine the Stock Exchange under the shadow of an
     enchanted oak, and the consequent disastrous wearing thin of the metal casing in which all good
     business men keep their souls.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown thought if rather a curious coincidence that so soon after they had spoken of the
     dead Keats they should see him alive. They saw him framed in a little pale aisle of the Forest,
     a faintly defined fragile ghost, crouched against the trunk of a tree, bent awkwardly into an
     attitude of pain forgotten and ecstatic attention. It was his dearest moment that they saw, a
     <pb n="193"/>moment without death. For he was a prisoner in a perfect spell; he was utterly
     entangled in the looped and ensnaring song of a nightingale. The song was like beaten gold
     wire. Never again in her life did Sarah Brown profane with her poor voice the words that a
     perfect singer begot in a marriage with a perfect song. But in unhappiness, and in the horrible
     nights, the song came to her, always....</p>
    <p>The travellers were approaching the end of the Green Ride, but that did not matter to Sarah
     Brown, for there had been nothing lacking all the way.</p>
    <p>"Love — — ," began Richard in a loud exalted voice, and then suddenly a searchlight glared
     diagonally across the end of the Ride, over Mitten Island, and quenched the magic of the
     moment.</p>
    <p>"Sorry," said Richard. "I thought I was talking to my True Love."</p>
    <p>"I'm sorry you weren't," said Sarah Brown, as they emerged from the Forest. "I mean, I'm
     sorry it was only me you were talking to."
     <pb n="194"/>
     <pb n="195"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER VIII</head>
    <head>THE REGRETTABLE WEDNESDAY</head>
    <p>"
     <pb n="196"/>
     <pb n="197"/>What a very singular thing," said the Mayor, meeting the witch towards three
     o'clock in the afternoon, as she came down the Broad Walk towards Kensington, having slept
     invisibly among the daffodils for nearly twelve hours. "A really very singular thing. 'Tisn't
     once in five years I visit these parts, and now I'm here I meet the very person I was thinkin'
     about." He winked.</p>
    <p>"It's almost like magic, isn't it," said the witch, winking busily in return.</p>
    <p>"Well, I've done what you told me to," said the Mayor.</p>
    <p>"What was that?"</p>
    <p>"You will 'ave your joke," he retorted indulgently. "Pretending not to know, indeed. I've
     done what you told me the other day when you came to that committee with your cat. I thought it
     over — I'm not a proud man, never above takin' a hint, —
     <pb n="198"/>and I admitted to meself that what you said was fair about makin' money. Some'ow I
     never thought but what money was the first thing to make in business. To tell you the truth, I
     always thought it rather a feather in my cap that I never took advantage of Brown Borough
     customers in selling adulterated goods, for — Lawdy — they'd swallow anythink. It's different
     with your business, bein' in an 'igher-class locality. 'Igh prices, I thought, was only
     natural. Make 'ay while the sun shines was my motter, and I says to meself there was no reason
     why this war should make <hi>everyone</hi> un'appy. As for lookin' at the grocery business as a
     trust from God, like you said, I never dremp of such a thing, although I've bin to Chapel
     regular for ten years. But I see now there was a lot in what you said, and when I come to think
     of it, there was no need to make such a terrible lot of extra hay, 'owever much the sun might
     be shinin'. When you put it like that, I couldn't say why I was so set on more money, 'aving
     quite enough. Well, I says to meself, after shutting meself up to think it out, like you
     <pb n="199"/>said, 'ere am I giving up all my life an' all my jolly days an' 'olidays, an' I'm
     damned if I know what for. For money, — just money stewin' in its own juice in a bank, — not
     money I can use. Well, everybody's trained so, I'm thinkin'. Anyway I took it friendly of you
     to put it so delicate, so fanciful as you did, so as them charity ladies didn't smell a rat. I
     appreciated that, an' thought the more of what you said. I'm not a proud man."</p>
    <p>"You're just proud enough," said the witch. "You're a darling. If ever I can help you in a
     business way, let me know. If you want to start a side line, for instance, in Happiness, I can
     give you a tip where to get it wholesale, within limits. It'd go like wildfire in the Brown
     Borough, if you put in an ounce or two, gratis of course, with every order."</p>
    <p>"You will 'ave your joke," murmured the Mayor. "But I like it in you. I'm a man that never
     takes a joke amiss. Let's go for a walk together."</p>
    <p>"No," said the witch. "I am so hungry that my ribs are beginning to bend inwards.
     <pb n="200"/> I must go and have sausages and mash and two apple dumplings."</p>
    <p>They found themselves presently seated at the marble-topped table of an A.B.C. After an
     interval that could hardly be accurately described as presently, sausages and mash dawned on
     the horizon, and the witch waved her fork rudely at it as it approached.</p>
    <p>"Mashed is splendid stuff to sculp with," she said, roughing in a ground plan upon her plate
     with the sure carelessness of the artist. "This is going to be an ivory castle built upon a
     rock in a glassy sea. The sausage is the dragon guarding it, and this little crumb of bread is
     the emprisoned princess, a dull but sterling creature — — "</p>
    <p>"Look 'ere, Miss Watkins," interrupted the Mayor. "I'm not as a rule an impulsive man, and I
     don't want to startle you — — "</p>
    <p>"How d'you mean startle me?" asked the witch. "You haven't startled me at all. But the fact
     is, I never have been much of a person for getting married, thank you very much. I'm an awful
     bad house-
     <pb n="201"/>keeper. And I <hi>do</hi> so much enjoy having no money."</p>
    <p>"Well, I'm blessed," exclaimed the Mayor. "You're a perfect witch, I declare." He laid a
     large meat-like hand upon hers. "But you know, you can't put the lid on me so easy as that.
     Ever since you came into that old committee room I saw there was something particular about
     you, something that you an' me 'ad in common. I'm not speakin' so much of us bein' in the same
     line of business. Some'ow — oh, 'ang it all, let's get out of this and take a taxi. I'm not a
     kissing man, but — — "</p>
    <p>He seemed very persistent in applying negatived adjectives to himself. It was not his fault
     if the world failed to grasp exactly what he was, or rather exactly what he was not.</p>
    <p>"I have often wondered," interrupted the witch, "talking of kissing — what would happen if
     two snipes wanted to kiss each other? It would have to be at such awfully long range, wouldn't
     it. Or — — "</p>
    <p>"Come off it," ordered the Mayor irritably. "What about gettin' out of this and — — "
     <pb n="202"/></p>
    <p>"Don't you think this is becoming rather a tiresome scene?" said the witch. "Somehow over
     luscious, don't you think? I wish those apple dumplings would hurry up."</p>
    <p>"'Ere, miss," said the Mayor ungraciously to a passing whirlwind. "'Urry them dumplings."</p>
    <p>"'Urry them dumplings," echoed the whirlwind to a little hole in the wall.</p>
    <p>The witch had a silly vision of two distressed dumplings, like dilatory chorus girls, mad
     with the nightmare feeling of not being dressed in time, hearing their cue called in a
     heartless voice from the inexorable sky, desperately applying the last dab of flour to their
     imperfect complexions. But the witch found no fault with them when they came. She gave them her
     whole attention for some minutes.</p>
    <p>"Well, well," she said, laying down her fork and spoon, "that's good. I feel awfully
     grown-up, having had a proposal. When real girls ask me now how many I've had, I shall be able
     to say One. But I met a girl the other day who had had six. She had six photographs, but she
     called them
     <pb n="203"/>scalps. If you would give me your photograph I could label it A Scalp, and hang it
     in the Shop. That would be very grown-up, wouldn't it?"</p>
    <p>"You will 'ave your joke," said the Mayor in a hollow voice. "I never met such a gurl as you
     for a bit of fun. I don't believe you've got any 'eart."</p>
    <p>There, of course, he was right. A heart is a sort of degree conferred by Providence on those
     who have passed a certain examination. Magic people are only freshmen in our college, and it is
     useless for us — secure in the possession of many learned letters after our names — to despise
     them. They will become sophisticated in due course.</p>
    <p>"How d'you mean — heart?" asked the witch therefore. "I've still got an awful hunger inside
     me, if that's anything to do with it. I'll tell you what. It's Wednesday. Let's go and call on
     Miss Ford. She might have grassy sandwiches."</p>
    <p>There was a most abrupt and disturbing draught in Miss Ford's sleek and decorous flat as the
     witch and the Mayor entered it. The serenity of the night and the morning
     <pb n="204"/>had been suddenly obliterated, and Kensington suffered a gust or two of gritty
     wind which blew the babies home from the Gardens, and kept all the window-gazers in the High
     Street on the alert with their fingers on the triggers of their umbrellas.</p>
    <p>But no rain fell. Rain cannot fall in this book of fine weather.</p>
    <p>The draught that intruded into the flat ruffled the neat hair of five persons, Miss Ford
     herself, Lady Arabel Higgins, Miss Ivy MacBee, Mr. Bernard Tovey, and Mr. Darnby Frere.</p>
    <p>Miss MacBee always seemed to be seated on tenterhooks, even in the most comfortable of
     chairs. Her Spartan spine never consented graciously to the curves of cushions. She had smooth
     padded hair and smooth padded manners, and her eyes were magnified by thick pince-nez to a
     cow-like size. Most people, especially most women, were instinctively sorry for her, because
     she always looked a little clever and very uncomfortable.</p>
    <p>Mr. Bernard Tovey was a blunt-nosed beaming person. He leaned forward
     <pb n="205"/>abruptly whenever he spoke, thereby swinging a lock of hair into his right eye. He
     agreed so heartily with everything that was said that people who addressed him were left with
     the happy impression that they had said something Rather Good. This habit, combined with the
     fact that he never launched an independent remark, had given him the reputation of being one of
     the best talkers in Kensington.</p>
    <p>Mr. Darnby Frere was the editor of an advanced religious paper called <hi>I Wonder</hi>, but
     he never wondered really. He knew almost everything, and therefore, while despising the public
     for knowing so little, he encouraged it to continue wondering, so that he might continue
     despising and instructing it.</p>
    <p>Now it was an almost unprecedented thing for two members of the small trades-man class to
     come into Miss Ford's drawing-room, especially on a Wednesday. The utmost social mingling of
     the classes that those walls had ever seen was the moment when Miss Ford asked the electric
     light man what he thought of the war. The
     <pb n="206"/>electric light man's reply had been quoted in the dialect on two or three of the
     following Wednesdays, as a proof of Miss Ford's daring intimacy with men in Another Station of
     Life. Really it would have been simpler, though of course not so picturesque, to have quoted it
     direct from its original source, <hi>John Bull</hi>, the electric light man's Bible.</p>
    <p>The entrance of the witch and the Mayor was to a certain extent a crisis, but Miss Ford kept
     her head, and her three friends, though grasping at once the extraordinary situation, did not
     give way to panic.</p>
    <p>"Well, well, well," said the Mayor, looking round and breathing very loudly. "This is a cosy
     little nook you've got 'ere."</p>
    <p>He was not at all at his ease, but being a business man, and being also blessed with a
     peculiarly inexpressive face, he was successfully dissembling his discomfort.</p>
    <p>For it had happened that the lift had been one of those lifts that can do no wrong, the kind
     that the public is indulgently allowed to work by itself. And the Mayor, looking upon this fact
     as specially planned by a propitious god of love, had tried to
     <pb n="207"/>kiss the witch as they shot up the darkened shaft. If I remind you that the witch
     was still accompanied by her broomstick, Harold, a creature of unreasoning fidelity, I need
     hardly describe the scene further. The Mayor stepped out of the lift with a tingling scraped
     face, and if he had possessed enough hair on his head, it would have been on end. As it was,
     when the lift stopped, he retrieved his hat from the floor with a frank oath, and, as the witch
     had at once rung the bell of Miss Ford's flat, he instinctively followed her across that
     threshold.</p>
    <p>She looked round in the hall, and said with a friendly smile: "I'm afraid Harold gets a bit
     irritable sometimes. I often tell him to count ten before he lets himself go, but he forgets.
     Did he hurt you?"</p>
    <p>I am afraid the angry Mayor did not give Harold credit for much initiative.</p>
    <p>"Kissing is such a funny habit, isn't it," said the witch briskly as she shook Miss Ford's
     hand. "I wonder who decided in the first place which forms of contact should express which
     forms of emotion. I wonder — — "
     <pb n="208"/></p>
    <p>She interrupted herself as her eyes fell on some green sandwiches which were occupying the
     third floor of a wicker Eiffel Tower beside Miss Ford. "Oh how gorgeous," she said. "Do you
     know, I've only had two meals in the last two days."</p>
    <p>Nobody present had ever been obliged to miss a meal, so this statement seemed to every one to
     be a message from another world.</p>
    <p>"You must tell us about all your experiences, my dear Miss Watkins," said Miss Ford, leading
     the witch towards a chair by the fire. The witch sat down suddenly cross-legged on the
     hearth-rug, leaving her rather embarrassed hostess in the air, so to speak, towering rigidly
     above her.</p>
    <p>"How d'you mean — experiences?" said the witch, after eating one sandwich in silent ecstasy.
     "I was up in the sky last night, talking to a German. Was that an experience?"</p>
    <p>"The sky last night was surely no place for a lady," said Mr. Frere with rather sour
     joviality.</p>
    <p>"Oh, I know what she means," said Miss
     <pb n="209"/> MacBee earnestly. "I was up in the sky last night too — — "</p>
    <p>"Great Scott," exclaimed the witch. "But — — "</p>
    <p>"Yes, I was," persisted Miss MacBee. "I lay on the hammock which I have had slung in my
     cellar, and shut my eyes, and loosed my spirit, and it shot upward like a lark released. It
     detached itself from the common trammels of the body, yes, my spirit, in shining armour, fought
     with the false, cruel spirits of murderers."</p>
    <p>"I hadn't got any shining armour," sighed the witch, who had been looking a little puzzled.
     "But I had the hell of a wrangle with a Boche witch who came over. We fought till we fell off
     our broomsticks, and then she quoted the <hi>Daily Mail</hi> at me, and then she fell through a
     hole and broke her back over the cross on St. Paul's."</p>
    <p>It was Miss MacBee's turn to look puzzled, but she said to Miss Ford: "My dear, you have
     brought us a real mystic."</p>
    <p>Mr. Frere, though emitting an applauding murmur, leaned back and fixed his face in the
     ambiguous expression of one who, while
     <pb n="210"/>listening with interest to the conversation of liars, is determined not to appear
     deceived.</p>
    <p>"How d'you mean — mystic?" asked the witch. "I don't think I can have made myself clear.
     Excuse me," she added to Miss Ford, "but this room smells awfully clever to any one coming in
     from outside. Do you mind if I dance a little, to move the air about?"</p>
    <p>"We shall be delighted," said Miss Ford indulgently. "Shall I play for you?"</p>
    <p>The witch did not answer; she rose, and as she rose she threw a little white paper packet
     into the fire. She danced round the sofa and the chairs. The floor shook a little, and all her
     watchers twisted their necks gravely, like lizards watching an active fly.</p>
    <p>The parlour-maid, by appearing in the doorway with an inaudible announcement, diverted their
     attention, though she did not interrupt the witch's exercises.</p>
    <p>A very respectable-looking man came in. Darnby Frere, who was a student of Henry James's
     works, and therefore constantly made elaborate guesses on matters that did not
     <pb n="211"/>concern him, and then forgot them because — unlike Mr. James's guesses — they were
     always wrong, gave the newcomer credit for being perhaps a shopwalker, or perhaps a
     South-Eastern and Chatham ticket-collector, but surely a chapel-goer.</p>
    <p>At any rate the stranger looked ill at ease, and especially disconcerted by the sight of the
     dancing witch.</p>
    <p>Miss Ford realised by now that her Wednesday had for some reason gone mad. She had lost her
     hold on the reins of that usually dignified equipage; there was nothing now for her to do but
     to grip tight and keep her head.</p>
    <p>She therefore concealed her ignorance of her newest guest's identity, she stiffened her lips
     and poured out another cup of tea with a nerveless hand. The stranger took the cup of tea with
     some relief, and said: "Thenk you, meddem."</p>
    <p>The witch stopped dancing, and stood in front of the newcomer's chair.</p>
    <p>"I think yours must be a discouraging job," she said to him. "Getting people punished for
     doing things you'd love to
     <pb n="212"/>do yourself. Oh, awfully discouraging. And do tell me, there's a little problem
     that's been on my mind ever since the war started. I hear that Hindenburg says the German Army
     intends to march through London the moment it can brush away the obstacles in front of it. Have
     you considered what will happen to the traffic, because you know Germans on principle march on
     the wrong side of the street — indeed everybody in the world does, except the conscientious
     British. Think of the knotted convulsions of traffic at the Bank, with a hundred thousand
     Boches goose-stepping on the wrong side of the road — think of poor thin Fleet Street, and the
     dam that would occur in Piccadilly Circus. What do you policemen intend to do about it?"</p>
    <p>"I don't know I'm sure, miss," said the newcomer coldly. "It's a long time since I was on
     point duty. I'm a plain clothes man, meddem," he added to Miss Ford. "I'm afraid I'm intruding
     on your tea-party, owing to your maid misunderstanding my business. But being 'ere, I 'ope
     you'll excuse me stating what I've come for."
     <pb n="213"/></p>
    <p>"Oh certainly, certainly," said Miss Ford, who was staring vaguely into the fireplace. A
     rather fascinating thread of lilac smoke was spinning itself out of the ashes of the little
     white paper packet.</p>
    <p>"The names of the Mayor of the Brown Borough, Miss Meter Mostyn Ford, and Lady A. 'Iggins —
     all of 'oom I understand from the maid are present — 'ave been mentioned as being presoomably
     willing to give information likely to be 'elpful in the search for a suspicious cherecter 'oo
     is believed to 'ave intruded on a cheritable meeting, at which you were present last Seturday,
     in order to escape arrest, 'aving just perpetrated a petty theft from a baker, 'Ermann Schwab.
     The cherecter is charged now with a more important offence, being in possession of an armed
     flying machine, in defiance of the Defence of the Realm Act, and interfering with the work of
     'Is Majesty's Forces during enemy attack. The cherecter is believed to be a man in female
     disguise, but enquiry up to date 'as failed to get any useful description. You ladies and
     gents, I understand, should be able to 'elp the Law in this metter."
     <pb n="214"/></p>
    <p>There was a stunned silence in the room, broken only by the pastoral sound of the witch
     eating grassy sandwiches. After a moment Miss Ford, the Mayor, and Lady Arabel all began
     speaking at once, and each stopped with a look of relief on hearing that some one else was
     ready to take the responsibility of speaking.</p>
    <p>Then the witch began with her mouth full: "You know — — ," but Lady Arabel interrupted
     her.</p>
    <p>"Angela dear, be silent. This does not concern you. Of course, inspector, we're all only too
     dretfully anxious to do anything to help the Law, but you must specify the occasion more
     exactly. Our committee sees so many applicants."</p>
    <p>"You are Lady A. 'Iggins, I believe," said the policeman impassively. "Well, my lady, may I
     ask you whether you are aware thet the cherecter in question was seen to leave your 'ouse last
     night, at nine forty-five P.M., after the warning of approaching enemy atteck was given, and to
     disappear in an easterly direction, on a miniature 'eavier than air machine, make and number
     unknown?"
     <pb n="215"/></p>
    <p>The threads of curious smoke in the fireplace were increasing. They shivered as though with
     laughter, and flowed like crimped hair up the chimney.</p>
    <p>"I had a dinner-party last night certainly," stammered Lady Arabel. A trembling seized the
     sock she was knitting. She had turned the heel some time ago, but in the present stress had
     forgotten all about the toe. The prolonged sock grew every minute more and more like a
     drain-pipe with a bend in it. "Why yes, of course I had a dinner-party; why shouldn't I? My son
     Rrchud, a private in the London Rifles, this young lady, Miss Angela — er — , and her friend —
     such a good quiet creature...."</p>
    <p>"And 'oo else was in the 'ouse?" asked the policeman, glancing haughtily at the witch.</p>
    <p>"Oh nobody, nobody. The servants all gave notice and left — too dretfully tahsome how they
     can't stand Rrchud and his ways. Of course there was the orchestra — twenty-five pieces — but
      <hi>so</hi> dependable."</p>
    <p>"Dependable," said the witch, "is a
     <pb n="216"/>mystery word to me. I can't think how it got into the English language without
     being right. Surely Depend-on-able — — "</p>
    <p>"Your son 'as peculiar ways, you say, my lady," interrupted the policeman.</p>
    <p>"Oh, nothing to speak of," answered Lady Arabel, wincing. "Merely lighthearted ... too
     dretfully Bohemian ... ingenious, you know, in making experiments ... magnetism...."</p>
    <p>"Experiments in Magnetism," spelt the policeman aloud into his notebook. "And 'oo left your
     'ouse at nine forty-five P.M. last night?"</p>
    <p>"I did," said the witch.</p>
    <p>The policeman withered her once more with a glance.</p>
    <p>"Lady 'Iggins, did you say your son left your 'ouse at nine forty-five P.M. last night?"</p>
    <p>"Yes, but — — "</p>
    <p>"Thenk you, my lady."</p>
    <p>"You seem to me dretfully impertinent," said Lady Arabel. "This is not a court of law. My son
     Rrchud left the house with me and our guest to seek shelter from the raid."
     <pb n="217"/></p>
    <p>"Thenk you, my lady," repeated the policeman coldly, and turned to Miss Ford.</p>
    <p>"Could you identify the cherecter 'oo came into your committee room last Seturday?" he asked
     of her.</p>
    <p>"No," she replied.</p>
    <p>"Couldn't you say whether it seemed like a male or a female in disguise? Couldn't you mention
     any physical pecooliarity that struck you?"</p>
    <p>"No," said Miss Ford.</p>
    <p>"'Ave you no memory of last Seturday night?"</p>
    <p>"No," said Miss Ford.</p>
    <p>"I have," said the witch.</p>
    <p>The policeman bridled. "I was addressing this 'ere lady, Miss M.M. Ford. Can you at least
     tell me, meddem, 'ow long you and the 'Iggins family 'ave been acquainted?"</p>
    <p>"No," said Miss Ford.</p>
    <p>"Eighteen years," said Lady Arabel.</p>
    <p>The fumes from the fireplace were very strong indeed, but nobody called attention to
     them.</p>
    <p>"I'm sorry, ..." said Miss Ford pres
     <pb n="218"/>ently, very slowly, "that ... I ... can't help you. I have ... been having ...
     nerve-storms ... since ... last ... Saturday...."</p>
    <p>The policeman fixed his ominous gaze upon her for quite a minute before he wrote something in
     his notebook.</p>
    <p>"Is Private Richard 'Iggins in town to-night?" he asked of Lady Arabel in a casual voice.</p>
    <p>"I suppose so," she replied. "But he has such a dretful habit of disappearing...."</p>
    <p>The policeman turned to the Mayor.</p>
    <p>"Now, sir," he said. "Could you help me at all in — — "</p>
    <p>"Look here," said the witch, rising. "If you would only come along to my house in Mitten
     Island I can truly give you all the information you need. In fact, won't you come to supper
     with me? If some one will kindly lend me half-a-crown I will go on ahead and cook
     something."</p>
    <p>Mr. Tovey mechanically produced a coin.</p>
    <p>"Here, Harold," called the witch, and holding Harold's collar she stepped out on to the
     balcony, mounted, and flew away.
     <pb n="219"/></p>
    <p>She left a room full of noise behind her.</p>
    <p>The policeman, who was intoxicated with the strange fumes, said: "Hell. Hell. Hell."</p>
    <p>Lady Arabel called in vain: "Angela, Angela, don't be so dretfully rash."</p>
    <p>Mr. Tovey, now afflicted with a lock of hair in each eye, seized the policeman by the
     shoulder thinking to prevent him from jumping out of the window. "You fool," he shouted.</p>
    <p>The Mayor slapped his thigh with a loud report. "Lawdy," he yelled. "She's a sport. She will
     'ave 'er joke."</p>
    <p>Miss MacBee laughed hysterically and very loudly.</p>
    <p>Mr. Darnby Frere said "My word" rather cautiously several times, and rubbed the bridge of his
     nose. He rather thought everybody was pulling his leg, but could not be sure.</p>
    <p>Only Miss Ford sat silent.
     <pb n="220"/>
     <pb n="221"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER IX</head>
    <head>THE HOUSE OF LIVING ALONE MOVES AWAY</head>
    <p>
     <pb n="222"/>
     <pb n="223"/>When Sarah Brown and Richard, followed by the Dog David, reached the Mitten Island
     Ferry, after travelling slowly by moonlight, they were surprised to see a great crowd of people
     banked up on the Island, and one man in the uniform of a policeman, standing alone on the
     mainland. About ten yards from land the ferryman sat in his boat, rowing gently to keep himself
     stationary in the current.</p>
    <p>"You'll 'ave to come to shore now," said the policeman, in the tone of one exhausted by long
     argument. "'Ere's some more parties wanting to cross." He turned to Richard. "Look 'ere, mate,"
     he said. "I'm 'ere in the discharge of my dooty, and this ferryman is obstructin' me."</p>
    <p>"Deah, deah," said Richard.</p>
    <p>The ferryman said: "If the King of England — why, if the two ghosts of Queen
     <pb n="224"/> Victoria and Albert the Good — was waiting to cross now, I wouldn't come in for
     them, not if it was going to give you a chance to set foot on Mitten Island."</p>
    <p>The crowd across the river, divining that a climax of defiance was being reached, shouted:
     "Yah, yah," in unison.</p>
    <p>"Is either of you parties an 'ouse'older on Mitten Island?" asked the policeman of Sarah
     Brown and Richard.</p>
    <p>"I am," said Richard, to his companion's surprise.</p>
    <p>"Can you give me any information regarding the whereabouts of a cherecter known under any of
     these names: Iris 'Yde, T.B. Watkins, Hangela the Witch, possibly a male in female disguise,
     believed to conduct a general shop and boardin' 'ouse on Mitten Island?"</p>
    <p>"There is only one shop on Mitten Island," said Richard. "And one boarding house. All in one.
     I own it. I can recite you the prospectus if you like. I have a superintendent there. I have
     known her all my life. I did not know she was believed to be a male in female disguise. I did
     not
     <pb n="225"/>know she had any name at all, let alone half-a-dozen."</p>
    <p>The policeman seemed to be troubled all the time by mosquitoes. He slapped his face and his
     ears and the back of his neck. He succeeded in killing one insect upon the bridge of his nose,
     and left it there by mistake, a strangely ignoble corpse. Sarah Brown suspected Richard of some
     responsibility for this untimely persecution.</p>
    <p>"That party is charged with an offence against the Defence of the Realm Act," said the
     policeman, — "with being, although a civilian, in possession of a flying machine, and — er —
     obstructin' 'Is Majesty's enemies in the performance of their dooty."</p>
    <p>"Oh deah, deah," said Richard. "Deah, deah, deah...."</p>
    <p>"Do either of you know the present whereabouts of the party?" persisted the policeman.
     Attacked on every side by insects, he was becoming rather pathetic in his discomfort and
     indignity. His small eyes, set in red fat, stared with uncomprehending protest; his fat busy
     hands were not agile enough to defend him. He felt
     <pb n="226"/>unsuccessful and foolish, and very near the ground. He wished quite
     disproportionately to be at home with his admiring wife in Acton.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown shook her head in reply, and Richard could say nothing but "Oh deah,
     deah...."</p>
    <p>"May I take your name and 'ome address, and regimental number, please, young man," said the
     policeman, after a baffled pause.</p>
    <p>"Now my address," said Richard, with genuine shame, "is a thing I honestly can never
     remember. I know I've heard it; I've tried and tried to learn it at my mother's knee. It begins
     with an H, I think. That's the worst of not being able to read or write. I can describe the
     place to you exactly, a house with a lot of windows, that sees a long way. If you turn your
     back on the Marble Arch, and go on till you get to a big poster saying Eat Less Meat, and then
     turn to your right — (pointing to the left) — or again, if you go by air as the crow flies — or
     rather as the witch flies — — "
     <pb n="227"/></p>
    <p>"You shall 'ear of this foolery, my fine feller," said the distressed policeman, almost with
     a break in his voice. "Seein' as 'ow you refuse information, an' this ferryman thinks fit to
     defy the law, I 'ave no course open but to whistle for my mate, and leave 'im 'ere while I
     telephone for a police-boat."</p>
    <p>He raised his whistle to his lips, but before he could blow it, the climax of this the least
     successful evening of his life, overwhelmed him. A shadow swept over the party, a large flying
     substance caught him full on the back of the neck and knocked him off the landing-stage into
     the river.</p>
    <p>The witch on Harold her Broomstick landed on the spot vacated by the policeman.</p>
    <p>"Oh, look what I've done, look what I've done ..." she exclaimed in an ecstasy of vexation.
     There was no need to tell anybody to look. Five hundred odd people were already doing so with
     enthusiasm. "Oh, what a dreadfully bad landing! Oh, Harold, how could you be so careless?"</p>
    <p>She took the cringing Harold by the mane and slapped him violently once or twice. Richard
     stretched out his riding-
     <pb n="228"/>crop to the splashing policeman, murmuring: "Oh deah, deah...."</p>
    <p>"Don't be frightened," said the witch to the policeman. "We'll soon get you out, and the
     water's so shallow you can't sink. Talking of sinking, Richard, there's a question that puzzles
     me rather. If a rat got on to a submarine, how would it behave? A submarine, you see, is a
     sinking ship, and rats pride themselves so on knowing when to — — "</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown seized the witch by the shoulder. "Go away, witch," she said.</p>
    <p>"How d'you mean — go away?" asked the witch. "I've only just this minute come."</p>
    <p>"Go away, go away," was all that Sarah Brown could manage to repeat.</p>
    <p>"Oh, very well," said the witch in her offended grown-up voice. "I can take a hint, I
     suppose, as well as anybody. I'm going."</p>
    <p>She seated herself with an irritable flouncing movement on Harold's saddle, and flew
     away.</p>
    <p>The policeman climbed out of the water,
     <pb n="229"/>looking like an enraged seal. Peals of laughter from the other side of the moonlit
     river robbed him of adequate words.</p>
    <p>"Not ser fast, my fine feller," he roared, seeing Richard kissing the Horse Vivian on the
     nose, preparatory to riding away. "Don't you think for a minute I don't know 'oo's at the
     bottom of this."</p>
    <p>"You don't know how tired I am of loud noises," said Richard, lifting one foot with dignity
     to the stirrup. "You don't know how bitterly I long to be still and hear things very far off
     ... but always there is an angry voice or the angry noise of guns in the way...."</p>
    <p>He twined one finger negligently into the mane on the Horse Vivian's neck, and pulled himself
     slowly into the saddle. The policeman stood mysteriously impotent. Water dripped loudly from
     his clothes and punctuated Richard's quiet speech.</p>
    <p>"Dear policeman," continued Richard. "I believe you have talked so much to-night that you
     haven't heard what a quiet night it is. You are smaller than a star, and yet you make more
     noise than all the stars
     <pb n="230"/>together. You are not so cold as the moon, and yet your teeth chatter more loudly
     than hers. The heat of your wrath is less than the heat of the sun, and yet, while he is silent
     and departed, you fill the air with clamour, and — if I may say so — seem to be outstaying your
     welcome. Oh, dear policeman, listen.... Do you know, if there were no London on this side and
     no War on that, the silence would be deep enough to fill all the seas of all the
     worlds...."</p>
    <p>He shook the reins, and the Horse Vivian moved, treading quietly on the strip of grass that
     borders the path to the ferry.</p>
    <p>"I am going to talk to my True Love now," said Richard, his voice fading away as he rode. "My
     True Love's voice is the only voice that is a little more beautiful to me than silence...."</p>
    <p>For a moment he looked every inch a wizard. Every button on his uniform and every buckle on
     the Horse Vivian's harness caught the moonlight, and changed into faery spangles as he turned
     and waved his hand before disappearing.
     <pb n="231"/></p>
    <p>The policeman seemed quieted, as he looked at Sarah Brown sitting, white and haggard with
     pain, on the river bank, with her arm round the shivering David.</p>
    <p>"In a minute, in a minute, my One," she was saying to David. "We are nearly home now. We
     shall soon be quiet now."</p>
    <p>There was always something startlingly inoffensive about Sarah Brown's appearance.</p>
    <p>"I'd like to know 'oo was responsible for this houtrage, all the same," said the
     policeman.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown did not hear him, but she said: "Oh, I am so very sorry it happened. It was a
     pure accident, of course, but it is so terrible to see any one have an accident to his dignity.
     You must forget it quickly, you must run and find someone who knows you at your best, you must
     tell her a fine revised version of the incident, and then you will feel better."</p>
    <p>The ferryman shouted: "I don't mind coming in now to fetch this young woman. You can come too
     now if you like, Mr. Pompous-in-the-Pond, for the party you're looking for is not at home, and
     I've no
     <pb n="232"/>doubt but what that crowd over there will give you a gay welcome."</p>
    <p>"I'll look into the metter to-morrer," said the policeman. "You 'aven't 'eard the last of
     this, none of you 'aven't, not by a long chalk. I've a good mind to get the Mayor to read the
     Riot Act at you."</p>
    <p>As Sarah Brown landed on Mitten Island she could not distinguish the faces of the waiting
     crowd, but she heard sharp anxious voices.</p>
    <p>"They ain't goin' to get 'er, not if I knows it."</p>
    <p>"She never speaks but kindness, the dear lamb."</p>
    <p>"She's more of a saint than any in the Calendar."</p>
    <p>"She gave my Danny a room in 'er house, and put 'eart into 'im after 'e lost 'is sight in the
     War."</p>
    <p>"She's the good fairy of the Island."</p>
    <p>"She grew all them Sweet Williams in my garden in one night, when I first come 'ere and was
     'omesick for Devon."</p>
    <p>"The law's always after saints and fairies, always 'as bin."
     <pb n="233"/></p>
    <p>"But the law can't catch 'er."</p>
    <p>"The law has driven her away," said Sarah Brown. "There is no magic now on Mitten
     Island."</p>
    <p>She staggered through the open door of the Shop. "This is Richard's house," she said to
     herself as she entered, and felt doubly alone because Richard was far away, riding to his True
     Love. She struck her last match, lit the lantern, and looked round. There was no sound in the
     house of Living Alone, she thought there would never again be any magic sound there to
     penetrate to her imprisoned hearing. The aprons hanging from the ceiling near the door flapped
     in the cold wind, and she thought they were like grey bats in a cave. The breeze blew out the
     open lantern. Ah, how desolate, how desolate....</p>
    <p>A piece of paper was impaled upon the counter by means of a headless hatpin. There was
     something very largely and badly written on it. Sarah Brown read: "Well Soup it looks like my
     Night's come and what dyou think Sherry's come too. Im an me as gone off to a place e knows
     that's a fine
     <pb n="234"/>place for such a boy as Elbert to be born in so no more at present from your true
     Peony."</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown climbed up the short stairway, painful step by painful step, to her cell. She sat
     on her bed holding her throbbing side, and breathing with fearful caution. She looked at the
     empty grate. She put a cigarette in her mouth, the unconscious and futile answer of the Dweller
     Alone to that blind hunger for comfort. But she had no matches, and presently, dimly conscious
     that her groping for comfort had lacked result, she absently put another cigarette into her
     mouth, and then felt a fool.</p>
    <p>She stared at the cold window. The sky seemed to be nailed carelessly to it by means of a
     crooked star or two.</p>
    <p>These are the terrible nights of Living Alone, when you have fever and sometimes think that
     your beloved stands in the doorway to bring you comfort, and sometimes think that you have no
     beloved, and that there is no one left in all the world, no word, no warmth, nor ever a kindly
     candle to be lighted in that spotted darkness that walls
     <pb n="235"/>up your hot sight. Again on those nights you dream that you have already done
     those genial things your body cries for, or perhaps That Other has done them. The fire is built
     and alight at last, a cup of something cool and beautifully sour stands ready to your hand, you
     can hear the delicious rattle of china on a tray in the passage — someone coming with food you
     would love to look at, and presently perhaps to eat ... when you feel better. But again and
     again your eyes open on the cold dumb darkness, and there is nothing but the wind and strange
     sinister emptiness creaking on the stair.</p>
    <p>These are the terrible nights of Living Alone, yet no real lover of that house and of that
     state would ever exchange one of those haunted and desert nights for a night spent watched, in
     soft warm places.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown was not long left alone that night to look at the strip of moonlight on the cold
     ashes of her fireplace. The Shop below shook suddenly with many footfalls, and the metallic
     officious barking of the Dog David rent the still air of her cell.</p>
    <p>A man's voice at the foot of the stairs
     <pb n="236"/>said: "I can hear a dog barking." And a woman's voice followed it: "Angela, dear,
     is that you?"</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown was only aware of a vague and irksome disturbance. She groped to her door, opened
     it, and shouted miserably: "Go away, policeman, go away. She is not here."</p>
    <p>Lady Arabel came up, flashing an electric torch.</p>
    <p>"My dear, you look dretfully ill. Why look, you are trembling. Why look, your little dog is
     making your counterpane muddy. Don't be afraid for Angela, we are all here to try and help
     her."</p>
    <p>"All here?"</p>
    <p>"Yes, Meta and the Mayor and Mr. Tovey and Mr. Frere. Let me help you into bed, and then you
     shall tell me what you know of her. You have had a dretfully trying time."</p>
    <p>"I am well," said Sarah Brown ungraciously. "You are none of you going to help the witch
     without me."</p>
    <p>"Ah, this is all very dretful," sighed Lady Arabel. "Most foolish of us to come
     <pb n="237"/>here all together like this, after the policeman took our names and addresses, and
     was dretfully impertinent and suspicious. But Meta insisted. I quite expect to spend the next
     twenty-four hours in gaol, or else to be shot for Offence of the Realm. In fact, speaking as a
     ratepayer, I think the police ought to have done it before. Still, Meta thought we might
     perhaps be able to help Angela.... Meta has many friends who seem influential ... but
      <hi>so</hi> talkative, my dear."</p>
    <p>She led the way downstairs. Mr. Tovey and the Mayor were talking at the foot of the stairs,
     Mr. Frere was listening sardonically. As Sarah Brown went past them into the Shop, she smelt
     the unflower-like scent that always denoted the presence of Miss Ford. Sarah Brown herself was
     accompanied by nothing more seductive than a faint smell of gasoline, showing that her clothes
     had lately been home-cleaned. In the darkness of the Shop she saw Miss Ford stooping, trying to
     shut the big difficult drawer in which the witch kept her magic.</p>
    <p>"It is frightfully explosive," said Sarah Brown.
     <pb n="238"/></p>
    <p>Miss Ford started and straightened her back. "Ah, Miss Brown.... I was just looking
     about...."</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown sat gasping on the counter, and the rest of the party re-entered the Shop,
     bringing the lantern.</p>
    <p>"How very absurd all this is," said Miss Ford nervously, — "taking such a great deal of
     trouble about a necessitous case."</p>
    <p>"America is in my mind," said Lady Arabel. "If we could get her there. Anybody who has done
     anything silly goes to America. Indeed, if I remember rightly, America is entirely populated
     with fugitives from somewhere else. So dretfully confusing for the Red Indians. They say the
     story of the Tower of Babel was only a prophecy about the Woolworth Building — "</p>
    <p>"You couldn't get a passport," said Mr. Darnby Frere, who was the only person present really
     conscious of sanity. "Only a miracle could produce a passport in these days, especially for a
     fugitive from justice."</p>
    <p>"Only a miracle — or magic," said Sarah Brown.
     <pb n="239"/></p>
    <p>Miss Ford moved instinctively behind the counter towards the open drawer full of ingredients
     for happiness.</p>
    <p>"We must remember," added Mr. Frere, "that, after all, she did break the law. In fact I
     cannot for the life of me imagine why on earth we are all — "</p>
    <p>"Oh, Darnby, do be sensible," said Miss Ford. "Of course we know it is wrong to break the
     law, but in this case — well, I myself should be the last to blame her."</p>
    <p>"No, not the last," said Sarah Brown.</p>
    <p>"What do you mean?"</p>
    <p>"Certainly not the last. Probably not even the penultimate one. You flatter yourself."</p>
    <p>"Why, surely some of you ladies, movin' in the 'ighest circles, knows of gentlemen in the
     Foreign Office that would do a little shut-eye job, for old times' sake," suggested the
     Mayor.</p>
    <p>This was a challenge to Miss Ford. She ceased to gaze haughtily on Sarah Brown. "Men from
     three departments of the Foreign Office are fairly regular Wednesday friends of mine," she
     said. "But I could
     <pb n="240"/>hardly trouble any of them on — er — so trivial a matter."</p>
    <p>There was silence, while Miss Ford toyed gingerly with one of the paper packets out of the
     witch's drawer. Presently she said: "What about Richard?"</p>
    <p>Lady Arabel showed sudden irritation. "There you go again, Meta; I have spoken to you of it
     again and again. It's Rrchud this and Rrchud that whenever anything in the least tahsome or out
     of the way happens. One would think you considered the poor boy a wizard."</p>
    <p>"You needn't lose your temper, Arabel," said Miss Ford coldly. "I only meant that Richard
     might be useful, having so many friends, and such skill in ... chemistry...." As if
     unconsciously she tore off one corner of the packet of magic she held before adding: "And
     besides, as I have often told you, I believe Richard to have real Occult Power, which would
     give him a special interest in this case."</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown, who was burying her face in her hands and missing much of the conversation,
     caught the name of Richard,
     <pb n="241"/>and said: "Richard has gone to his True Love."</p>
    <p>A tempest of restrained embarrassment arose.</p>
    <p>"She's feverish," murmured Miss Ford, turning scarlet.</p>
    <p>"My dear Sarah," said Lady Arabel tartly. "You are quite mistaken, and I must beg of you to
     be careful how you repeat idle gossip about my son. Rrchud is at his office. You know it is
     only open at night — one of Rrchud's quaint fancies."</p>
    <p>"I will ring up his office," said Miss Ford, deciding to ignore Sarah Brown both now and in
     future. "Where is the telephone?"</p>
    <p>"There is none," replied Sarah Brown. "This is the House of Living Alone."</p>
    <p>Miss Ford was pouring a grain or two of the magic into her palm. "How very credulous people
     are," she said with a self-conscious smile. "If Thelma Bennett Watkins were here she would
     credit this powder with — "</p>
    <p>She stopped, for an astonishing sharp smell filled the Shop. Almost immediately
     <pb n="242"/>a curious wheezy sound, punctuated by taps, proceeded from the corner. It was Mr.
     Bernard Tovey trying to sing, "Mon coeur s'ouvr' à ta voix," and beating time by swinging his
     heels against the counter on which he sat.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown felt suddenly well. She trembled but was well. She jumped off the counter. "I
     will run across, if you like," she said, "and ring up Richard from the ferryman's house. He may
     have left his True Love now. I am not deaf on the telephone, and the ferryman won't admit
     strangers."</p>
    <p>As she left, the smell of magic was getting stronger and stronger. Mr. Tovey, still
     impersonating Delilah in the corner, was approaching the more excitable passages of the song.
     Miss Ford was saying, "Really, Bernard...." Sarah Brown felt a slight misgiving.</p>
    <p>A warm and rather dramatic-looking light was shining behind the red curtain of the ferryman's
     lattice window, as Sarah Brown crossed the moonlit road. She delighted, after her recent black
     hours, to
     <pb n="243"/>think of all those people in the world who were sitting stuffily and pleasantly in
     little ugly rooms that they loved, doing quiet careful things that pleased them. And she told
     herself that the thought of Richard's little office, alone and alight in the deserted City
     every night, would comfort her often in the darkness.</p>
    <p>The ferryman opened his door, and invited her genially to his telephone. He had been sitting
     at his table, surrounded by the snakes that for him took the place of a family. On the table
     was a bowl of milk from which a large bull-snake, in a gay Turkey-carpet design, was drinking.
     A yellow and black python lay coiled in several figures of eight in the armchair, and an
     intelligent-looking small dust-coloured snake with a broad nose and an active tongue leaned out
     of the ferryman's breast pocket.</p>
    <p>"Aren't they beautiful?" he said, with shy and paternal pride, as Sarah Brown tried to find a
     place on which the python would like to be tickled or scratched. Somehow the python has a
     barren figure, from a caresser's point of view. The ferryman
     <pb n="244"/>went on: "There is something about the grip and spring in a snake's body that
     makes me feel giddy with pleasure. Snakes to me, you know, are just a drug, sold by the yard
     instead of in bottles. My brain is getting every day colder and quieter, and all through loving
     snakes so."</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown rang up Richard's office, and the over-refined voice of a young gentleman clerk
     answered her.</p>
    <p>Mr. Higgins was not in the office.</p>
    <p>Mr. Higgins had left particular word that if any one wanted him they were to be told that he
     had — er — gone to his True Love.</p>
    <p>But any minor business matter connected with magic could be attended to in his absence. Mr.
     Higgins spending so much of his time on the battlefield at present, a good deal of the routine
     work had to be done in any case by the speaker, his confidential clerk.</p>
    <p>Passports to America? Perfectly simple. The office had simply to issue blank sheets treated
     in a certain way, and every official to whom the sheet should be presented would read upon it
     what he would want.
     <pb n="245"/> But Mr. Higgins would have to affix his mark and seal. Mr. Higgins would be in
     the office sometime to-night, probably within the hour.</p>
    <p>How many passports?</p>
    <p>"Two," said Sarah Brown. "One for my friend and one for me. A dog doesn't need one, does he —
     a British dog? I will book the berths to-morrow. I can pawn my — or rather, I can sell my War
     Loan."</p>
    <p>As she hung up the receiver, the ferryman asked: "Are you having a party up at the Shop, in
     the superintendent's absence?"</p>
    <p>"Not intentionally," replied Sarah Brown. "Why?"</p>
    <p>"Well, I just wondered. There's a noise like a thousand mad gramophones playing backwards,
     coming from there."</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown's misgivings returned like a clap of thunder. She rushed back to the Shop.</p>
    <p>The lantern was standing in the middle of the floor, its glass was shattered, and out of each
     of its eight panels streamed a great flame six or seven feet high, like the petal
     <pb n="246"/>of an enormous flower. Facing these flames stood Miss Ford and Mr. Tovey, hand in
     hand, each singing a different song very earnestly. Lady Arabel had found somewhere a patent
     fire extinguisher, and was putting on her glasses in order to read the directions. Mr. Frere
     was hesitating in the background with a leaking biscuit tin full of water. The Mayor was
     gone.</p>
    <p>"Great Scott!" said Sarah Brown. You'll burn the place down. Look at that row of petticoats
     up there, catching fire already. What have you done with the Mayor?"</p>
    <p>"We made him invisible by mistake," whispered Mr. Tovey. "But sh — sh, he doesn't know it
     yet."</p>
    <p>"Nothing matters," said Miss Ford. "We are all going to America." And she continued her song,
     which was an extempore one about the sea.</p>
    <p>"But that's no reason why you should burn the house down," said Sarah Brown.</p>
    <p>"That's what I thought," agreed Mr. Frere. "But water won't put out that flame."
     <pb n="247"/></p>
    <p>The singers fell silent. Only the voice of the invisible Mayor could be heard, singing, "If
     those lips could only speak," in a loud tremulous voice, to the accompaniment of his own unseen
     stamping feet.</p>
    <p>"You've been putting magic into that flame," said Sarah Brown distractedly. "I told you it
     was dangerous. Nothing will put magic out, except more magic. What will the witch say?"</p>
    <p>"It doesn't matter what anybody says," said Miss Ford. "We are all going to America. No place
     and no person matters when I am not there. There are no places and no people existing where I
     am not. I have suspected it before, and now I am sure that everything is all a pretence, except
     me. Look how easy it was to dismiss that gross grocer from sight. He was just a bit of
     background. I have painted him out."</p>
    <p>The drapery department on the ceiling was ablaze now, and flakes of ashy petticoat, and the
     metal frames of buttons, showered to the floor.</p>
    <p>"I will go and get help," said Sarah Brown, and hurried out of doors, followed
     <pb n="248"/>feverishly by David, who was not a very brave dog in moments of crisis, and yet
     liked to appear busy and helpful. It was to the ferryman's telephone that they returned. Sarah
     Brown knew that the fire was a magic fire, and that an appeal to the L.C.C. Fire Brigade would
     only bring defeat and unnecessary bewilderment upon a deserving organisation.</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown rang up Richard's office, and Richard, who had a heroic and almost cinematic gift
     for being on hand at the right moments, answered her himself.</p>
    <p>"Come at once," said Sarah Brown. "The House of Living Alone is on fire. Someone has been
     tampering with the magic drawer."</p>
    <p>"Oh deah, deah," said Richard. "And this is such a busy night at the office too. Do you think
     it is really important? It is my house, you know."</p>
    <p>"Well, I don't see what is to prevent Mitten Island from being burnt to the water's edge. In
     fact I don't see why, being a magic fire, it should stop at the water's edge. Not to mention
     that the Mayor — — "
     <pb n="249"/></p>
    <p>"Very well, I'll come," said Richard.</p>
    <p>As she stepped out of the door he arrived.</p>
    <p>"I came by flash of lightning," he explained, smoothing his hair and readjusting his Bill
     Sykes service cap, in the manner of one who has moved swiftly. "The lightning service is
     getting very bad. I was held up for quite three-quarters of a second over Whitehall. There was
     some wireless war-news coming in, and the lightning had to let it pass. Now, what's all this
     fuss about, Sarah Brown?"</p>
    <p>There was a crowd of delirious Mitten Islanders round the House of Living Alone. While Sarah
     Brown and Richard were about fifty yards away, a many-forked and enormous white flame suddenly
     wrapped the house about, like a hand clutching and crushing it.</p>
    <p>"The faggots round the stake are lighted," said Richard. "But the witch has fled."</p>
    <p>It seemed that the stars were devoured by the flame, so far did it outshine them. The flame
     shrank in upon itself and
     <pb n="250"/>collapsed. There was no more House of Living Alone.</p>
    <p>"Oh, Richard," said Sarah Brown. "Your mother and Miss Ford and — — "</p>
    <p>"Was mother in there?" asked Richard placidly. "Wonders will never cease. Well, well, it is
     fortunate that no magic of any sort could ever touch mother."</p>
    <p>And indeed, as they pushed through the crowd, they saw all the recent occupants of the Shop
     arguing at the front gate.</p>
    <p>"I didn't blow it," Mr. Tovey was saying in an aggrieved voice. "I was singing, not
     blowing."</p>
    <p>"Well, all I know is that while you were on that high note something seemed to scatter the
     flames, and the drawer full of explosives caught fire," said Mr. Darnby Frere aggressively,
     flourishing his empty biscuit tin.</p>
    <p>"It doesn't matter," said Miss Ford calmly. "We are all going across the sea to-morrow." She
     roused herself a little, and said to Mr. Frere with a smile: "You know, I inherit the sea
     tradition. My father commanded H.M.S. <hi>Indigestible</hi> in '84."</p>
    <p>"I wonder what put out the flame so
     <pb n="251"/>suddenly?" asked Mr. Tovey, who was still dreamily beating time to imaginary music
     with one hand.</p>
    <p>"I put it out," said Richard.</p>
    <p>"I wonder whose house it is?" added Mr. Tovey, turning vaguely to face Richard.</p>
    <p>"It is my house," said Richard.</p>
    <p>They all discovered his presence.</p>
    <p>"Your house, dear Rrchud?" exclaimed Lady Arabel. "Are you sure? I didn't know the Higginses
     had any house property on Mitten Island."</p>
    <p>"They haven't now," replied Richard. "But never mind. It has always seemed to me that there
     were too many houses in the world. Most houses are traps into which everything enters, and out
     of which nothing comes. It always grieves me to see tradesmen pouring sustenance in at the back
     door, and no result or justification coming out of the front door. I often think that only the
     houses that men's bodies have deserted are really inhabited."</p>
    <p>"It was I who burnt your house down, Richard," said Miss Ford. "But it doesn't matter. It
     wasn't a real house."
     <pb n="252"/></p>
    <p>"You are right," said Richard. "To such as you, dear Meta, it was not a real house. It was
     the House of Living Alone, and only to people who live alone was it real. It is dark and
     deserted now, and levelled with the cold ground; it is as though it were a tent, being moved
     from its position to follow the fortunes of those dwellers alone who wander continually in
     silence up and down the world...."</p>
    <p>He looked at Sarah Brown.</p>
    <p>"Talking of wandering," said Miss Ford. "We are all going to America, Richard. Can you get us
     passports?"</p>
    <p>"Certainly," agreed Richard. "To America, eh? A nice little trip for you all. America, you
     know, would be entirely magic, if it weren't for the Americans...."</p>
    <p>"I have quite a circle of friends in New York," said Miss Ford, who seemed to be recovering
     from her nerve-storm.</p>
    <p>"Beware," said Richard, "lest you all forget the magic of to-night, and change from
     adventurers to tourists."</p>
    <p>"I am not going to America," said Lady Arabel. "I am going home. I never heard
     <pb n="253"/>such dretful nonsense. I was only in fun when I agreed to the plan."</p>
    <p>"I never agreed to the plan at all," said Mr. Frere. "I shall be truly thankful to get to
     bed, and wake up to-morrow sober. I will never go out to tea in Kensington again if this is the
     result."</p>
    <p>"I am going to America," said Mr. Tovey, fixing his innocent eyes, obscured by hair, upon
     Miss Ford.</p>
    <p>"I am going to America," echoed the unseen Mayor from an unexpected direction. Nobody had yet
     dared to tell him of the misfortune that had overtaken him. "I'll give up this Mayor job
     to-morrer. Catch me stayin' be'ind if — oh, by the way, that reminds me — — "</p>
    <p>"I didn't need reminding," interrupted Sarah Brown. "It seems to me that everybody has
     forgotten why they came here. Please, Richard, do you know of a spell to find a missing
     person?"</p>
    <p>"Yes, several," answered Richard, who was always as eager as a travelling salesman to
     recommend his wares. "There is an awfully ingenious little spell I can show you,
     <pb n="254"/>if you happen to have a telephone book and a compass and a toad's heart and a hair
     from a black goat's beard about you. Or again, if you stand on a sea-beach at low tide on
     Christmas night with the moon at your back and a wax candle in your left hand, and write upon
     the sand the name — by the way, who is it you want to find?"</p>
    <p>"The witch," answered Sarah Brown.</p>
    <p>Richard's face fell. "Oh, only the witch?" he said. "I can tell you where she is without any
     spell at all. She's with my True Love at Higgins Farm, helping — oh, by the way, mother, I
     forgot to tell you. You are a grandmother."</p>
    <p>"RRCHUD!" said Lady Arabel. She sat down suddenly on the smooth grass slope between the road
     and the garden hedge. "Ah, it is too cruel," she cried, burying her face in her hands. "It is
     too cruel. Is this my son? I meant so well, and all my life I did the things that other people
     did, the natural things. Except just once. And for that once, I am so cruelly punished.... I am
     given a son who is no son to me, who says only things I mustn't understand ...
     <pb n="255"/> who does only things I mustn't see...." She paused, and, taking her hands from
     her face, looked round aghast at Richard, who was sitting beside her on the bank, stroking her
     arm. "<hi>A faery son</hi> ..." she added in a terrified whisper, and then broke out again
     crying: "Ah, it is too cruel...."</p>
    <p>Richard continued to stroke her arm without comprehension. "Yes, mother, and Peony, my True
     Love, insists on calling him Elbert," he said. "Mother, listen, Elbert your faery
     grandson...."</p>
    <p>But Lady Arabel still sobbed.
     <pb n="256"/>
     <pb n="257"/></p>
   </div>
   <div type="chapter">
    <head>CHAPTER X</head>
    <head>THE DWELLER ALONE</head>
    <p>"
     <pb n="258"/>
     <pb n="259"/>Well, Sarah Brown, here we are," said the witch, her Byronic hair flying as she
     sat perilously on the rail of the deck. The distant flying buttresses of New York were
     supporting a shining sky, and north and east lay the harbour and sea, and many ships moving
     with the glad gait of home-comers after perilous voyaging.</p>
    <p>Every minute upon the sea is a magic minute, but the voyage of the witch and Sarah Brown had
     been unmarked by any supernatural activities on the part of the witch. She had been more or
     less extinguished by the presence of five hundred Americans, not one of whom had ever heard the
     word "magic" used, except by advertisers in connection with their wares.</p>
    <p>Miss Ford had been left behind, cured for ever of nerve-storms. She had become unexpectedly
     engaged to Mr. Bernard Tovey while looking for a porter on Lime Street Station, Liverpool, and
     had returned with him to London to celebrate the event by means of a Super-Wednesday. The Mayor
     <pb n="260"/>also had failed to embark. Indeed the unfortunate man had not been heard of since
     his seizure on the night of the fire, and I believe that the London police are still trying to
     arrest him as a German spy.</p>
    <p>"Here we are," said the witch to Sarah Brown. "At least, I suppose this City on its Tiptoes
     is New York. Do you think I ought to call the attention of the Captain to that largish lady on
     our left, who seems to be marooned upon a rock, and signalling to us for help?"</p>
    <p>"That is the Statue of Liberty," said three neighbouring Americans in chorus.</p>
    <p>"How d'you mean — Liberty?" asked the witch.</p>
    <p>The three Americans froze her with three glances.</p>
    <p>"America is the home of Liberty," they said all together.</p>
    <p>"Oh yes, of course, how stupid of me," said the witch. "I ought to have remembered that every
     country is the Home of Liberty. Such a pity that Liberty never seems to begin at home. Every
     big shop in London, you know, is labelled Patronised by Royalty,
     <pb n="261"/>yet I have bought haberdashery by the hour without running across a single queen.
     I suppose if you didn't have this big label sticking up in your harbour, you Americans might
     forget that America is the Home of Liberty. I know quite a lot about America from a grey
     squirrel who rents my may-tree on Mitten Island. It is a long time since he came over, but he
     still chitters with a strong New England accent. He came away because he was a socialist. I
     gather America is too full of Liberty to leave room for socialism, isn't that so? My squirrel
     says there are only two parties in America, Republicans and Sinners — at least I think that was
     what he said — and anybody who belongs to neither of these parties is given penal servitude for
     life. So I understood, but I may be wrong. I am not very good at politics. Anyway, my squirrel
     had to leave the Home of Liberty and come to England, so as to be able to say what he thought.
     I wish I were there too. Sarah Brown, I don't yet know why you brought me here."</p>
    <p>"I brought you here to escape the Law," said Sarah Brown.
     <pb n="262"/></p>
    <p>"How d'you mean — escape the Law? Didn't you know that all magic lives and thrives on the
     wrath of the Law? Have you forgotten our heroic tradition of martyrdom and the stake? Isn't the
     world tame enough already? What do you want Magic to become? A branch of the Civil
     Service?"</p>
    <p>"I spent all I had in bringing you here," said Sarah Brown. "I left all I loved to bring you
     here. I am as if dead in England now. Nobody there will ever think of me again, except as a
     thing that has been heard the last of."</p>
    <p>The witch looked kindly at her. "You know," she said, "when you first told me to go away,
     after Harold made that bad landing on a policeman, I thought perhaps you were a sort of cinema
     villainess, driving me away from my house and heritage. At first I thought of arguing the
     matter, but then I remembered that villains always have a rotten time, without being bullied
     and persecuted by the rest of us. Besides solid things are never worth fighting over. So I have
     been patient with you all this time, and have fallen in courteously with all your fiendish
     plans — as I thought — and now I am
     <pb n="263"/>glad I was patient, for I see you meant well. Dear Sarah Brown, you did mean well.
     How sad it is that people who have once lived in the House of Living Alone can never make a
     success of friendship. You say you left all you loved — what business have you with love? Thank
     you, my dear, for meaning so well, and for these fair days at sea. But I mustn't stay with you.
     I mustn't set foot on this land — I can smell cleverness and un-magic even from here. I must go
     back to my little Spring island, and my parish of Faery...."</p>
    <p>"Ah, witch, don't leave me, don't leave me like this, ill and bewildered and so far from
     home...."</p>
    <p>"How can you ever be far from home, you, a dweller in the greatest home of all. Did you think
     you had destroyed the House of Living Alone? Did you think you could escape from it?"</p>
    <p>Sarah Brown said nothing. She watched the witch call Harold her Broomstick to her, and adjust
     the saddle and tighten the strap round his middle. She watched her mount and embark upon the
     sunny air. The three Americans were talking politics, and did
     <pb n="264"/>not notice anything but each other. The witch alighted for a moment on one spike
     of the crown of Liberty, and climbing carefully down on to the lady's parting, was seen by
     Sarah Brown to bend down till her head hung apoplectically upside down, and gaze long and
     curiously into that impassive bronze eye. Presently she remounted Harold, and, with a flippant
     and ambiguous gesture of her foot, launched herself eastward. She disappeared without looking
     back.</p>
    <p>The dock was reached. Sarah Brown collected David her Dog, and Humphrey her Suit-case. Hers
     was a very wieldy family. An official asked her something, using one side of his mouth only to
     do so, in the alarming manner of American officials.</p>
    <p>"I cannot hear you," said Sarah Brown. "I am stone deaf."</p>
    <p>And she stepped over the threshold of the greater House of Living Alone.</p>
    <trailer>THE END</trailer>
    <trailer><hi>Printed by</hi> R. &amp; R. CLARK, LIMITED, <hi>Edinburgh.</hi></trailer>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>