<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
    <?xml-model href="../../Schemas/eltec-1.rng" type="application/xml" 
            schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
    <?xml-model href="../../Schemas/eltec-1.rng" type="application/xml" 
            schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en" xml:id="ENG18910">
 <teiHeader>
  <fileDesc>
   <titleStmt>
    <title>John Sherman and Dhoya : ELTeC edition</title>
    <author ref="https://viaf.org/viaf/46768718/">Yeats, William Butler (1865–1939)</author>
    <respStmt>
     <resp>ELTeC conversion</resp>
     <name>Lou Burnard</name>
    </respStmt>
   </titleStmt>
   <extent>
    <measure unit="words">24676</measure>
    <measure unit="pages">151</measure>
   </extent>
   <publicationStmt>
<publisher ref="https://distant-reading.net">COST Action "Distant Reading for European Literary History" (CA16204)</publisher>
<distributor ref="https://zenodo.org/communities/eltec/">Zenodo.org</distributor><date when="2021-04-09"/>
<availability><licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"/></availability>
<ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3462435">ELTeC</ref>
<ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4662444">ELTeC release 1.1.0</ref>
<ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3533868">ELTeC-eng</ref>
<ref type="doi" target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4662490">ELTeC-eng release 1.0.1</ref>
</publicationStmt>
   <sourceDesc><bibl type="digitalSource"><title>The Project Gutenberg eBook of John Sherman and Dhoya, by
      Ganconagh (William Butler Yeats)</title>
     <ref target="http://www.gutenberg.org/files/49109/49109-h/49109-h.htm">Gutenberg</ref></bibl><bibl type="firstEdition" n="B8426"><title>John Sherman and Dhoya</title>
     <author>Ganconagh [pseud.]</author>
     <publisher>London: T. Fisher Unwin,</publisher>
     <date>1891</date></bibl><bibl type="printSource">
     <title>John Sherman and Dhoya: second edition</title>
     <date>1891</date>
     <ref target="http://archive.org/details/johnshermandhoya00yeatrich"/>
    </bibl></sourceDesc>
  </fileDesc>
  <encodingDesc n="eltec-1">
   <p/>
  </encodingDesc>
  <profileDesc>
   <langUsage>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
   </langUsage>
   <textClass>
    <keywords>
     <term>Pseudonym Library</term>
    </keywords>
   </textClass>
   <textDesc>
    <authorGender xmlns="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns" key="M"/>
    <size xmlns="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns" key="short"/>
    <reprintCount xmlns="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns" key="low"/>
    <timeSlot xmlns="http://distantreading.net/eltec/ns" key="T3"/>
   </textDesc>
  </profileDesc>
  <revisionDesc>
<change when="2021-04-09">Converted by checkUp script for new release</change>
<change when="2020-11-14">Converted by checkUp script for new release</change>
   <change when="2020-05-19">Add text classifications from Bassett</change>
   <change when="2019-11-09">Checked by releaseChecker script</change>
   <change when="2019-01-15">LB convert to ELTeC-1</change>
  </revisionDesc>
 </teiHeader>


 <text type="T3MSU">
  <front>
   <div type="titlepage">

    <p>JOHN SHERMAN AND DHOYA</p>

    <p>GANCONAGH </p>
    <p> JOHN SHERMAN</p>
    <p>AND</p>
    <p>DHOYA</p>
    <p><hi>SECOND EDITION</hi></p>
    <p>LONDON T. FISHER UNWIN</p>
    <p>PATERNOSTER SQUARE</p>

    <p>M DCCC XCI</p>
   </div>


   <div type="liminal">
    <head> GANCONAGH’S APOLOGY.</head>
    <p>The maker of these stories has been told that he must not bring them to you himself. He has
     asked me to pretend that I am the author. I am an old little Irish spirit, and I sit in the
     hedges and watch the world go by. I see the boys going to market driving donkeys with creels of
     turf, and the girls carrying baskets of apples. Sometimes I call to some pretty face, and we
     chat a little in the shadow, the apple basket before us, for, as my faithful historian
     O’Kearney has put it in his now yellow manuscript, I care for nothing in the world but love and
     idleness. Will not
     <pb n="2"/> you, too, sit down under the shade of the bushes while I read you the stories? The
     first I do not care for because it deals with dull persons and the world’s affairs, but the
     second has to do with my own people. If my voice at whiles grows distant and dreamy when I talk
     of the world’s affairs, remember that I have seen all from my hole in the hedge. I hear
     continually the songs of my own people who dance upon the hill-side, and am content. I have
     never carried apples or driven turf myself, or if I did it was only in a dream. Nor do my kind
     use any of man’s belongings except the little black pipes which the farmers find now and then
     when they are turning the sods over with a plough.</p>
    <p>GANCONAGH.</p>
   </div>
  </front>
  <body>
   <div type="group">
    <head> PART I. JOHN SHERMAN LEAVES BALLAH.</head>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head> I.</head>
     <p>In the west of Ireland, on the 9th of December, in the town of Ballah, in the Imperial Hotel
      there was a single guest, clerical and youthful. With the exception of a stray commercial
      traveller, who stopped once for a night, there had been nobody for a whole month but this
      guest, and now he was thinking of going away. The town, full enough in summer of trout and
      salmon fishers, slept all winter like the bears.</p>
     <p>On the evening of the 9th of December, in the coffee-room of the Imperial Hotel, there was
      nobody but this guest. The guest was irritated. It had rained all day, and now that it
      <pb n="6"/> was clearing up night had almost fallen. He had packed his portmanteau: his
      stockings, his clothes-brush, his razor, his dress shoes were each in their corner, and now he
      had nothing to do. He had tried the paper that was lying on the table. He did not agree with
      its politics.</p>
     <p>The waiter was playing an accordion in a little room over the stairs. The guest’s irritation
      increased, for the more he thought about it the more he perceived that the accordion was badly
      played. There was a piano in the coffee-room; he sat down at it and played the tune correctly,
      as loudly as possible. The waiter took no notice. He did not know that he was being played
      for. He was wholly absorbed in his own playing, and besides he was old, obstinate, and deaf.
      The guest could stand it no longer. He rang for the waiter, and then, remembering that he did
      not need anything, went out before he came.</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="7"/> He went through Martin’s Street, and Peter’s Lane, and turned down by the burnt
      house at the corner of the fish-market, picking his way towards the bridge. The town was
      dripping, but the rain was almost over. The large drops fell seldomer and seldomer into the
      puddles. It was the hour of ducks. Three or four had squeezed themselves under a gate, and
      were now splashing about in the gutter of the main street. There was scarcely any one abroad.
      Once or twice a countryman went by in yellow gaiters covered with mud and looked at the guest.
      Once an old woman with a basket of clothes, recognizing the Protestant curate’s <hi>locum
       tenens</hi>, made a low curtsey.</p>
     <p>The clouds gradually drifted away, the twilight deepened and the stars came out. The guest,
      having bought some cigarettes, had spread his waterproof on the parapet of the bridge and was
      now leaning his elbows upon it,
      <pb n="8"/> looking at the river and feeling at last quite tranquil. His meditations, he
      repeated, to himself, were plated with silver by the stars. The water slid noiselessly, and
      one or two of the larger stars made little roadways of fire into the darkness. The light from
      a distant casement made also its roadway. Once or twice a fish leaped. Along the banks were
      the vague shadows of houses, seeming like phantoms gathering to drink.</p>
     <p>Yes; he felt now quite contented with the world. Amidst his enjoyment of the shadows and the
      river—a veritable festival of silence—was mixed pleasantly the knowledge that, as he leant
      there with the light of a neighbouring gas-jet, flickering faintly on his refined form and
      nervous face and glancing from the little medal of some Anglican order that hung upon his
      watch-guard, he must have seemed—if there had been any to witness—a being
      <pb n="9"/> of a different kind to the inhabitants—at once rough and conventional—of this
      half-deserted town. Between these two feelings the unworldly and the worldly tossed a leaping
      wave of perfect enjoyment. How pleasantly conscious of his own identity it made him when he
      thought how he and not those whose birthright it was, felt most the beauty of these shadows
      and this river? To him who had read much, seen operas and plays, known religious experiences,
      and written verse to a waterfall in Switzerland, and not to those who dwelt upon its borders
      for their whole lives, did this river raise a tumult of images and wonders. What meaning it
      had for them he could not imagine. Some meaning surely it must have!</p>
     <p>As he gazed out into the darkness, spinning a web of thoughts from himself to the river,
      from the river to himself, he saw, with a corner of his eye, a spot of red light moving in the
      <pb n="10"/> air at the other end of the bridge. He turned towards it. It came closer and
      closer, there appearing behind it the while a man and a cigar. The man carried in one hand a
      mass of fishing-line covered with hooks, and in the other a tin porringer full of bait.</p>
     <p>“Good evening, Howard.”</p>
     <p>“Good evening,” answered the guest, taking his elbows off the parapet and looking in a
      preoccupied way at the man with the hooks. It was only gradually he remembered that he was in
      Ballah among the barbarians, for his mind had strayed from the last evening gnats, making
      circles on the water beneath, to the devil’s song against “the little spirits” in
      “Mefistofele.” Looking down at the stone parapet he considered a moment and then burst
      out—</p>
     <p>“Sherman, how do you stand this place—you who have thoughts above mere eating and sleeping
      and are not always grinding
      <pb n="11"/> at the stubble mill? Here everybody lives in the eighteenth century—the squalid
      century. Well, I am going to-morrow, you know. Thank Heaven, I am done with your grey streets
      and grey minds! The curate must come home, sick or well. I have a religious essay to write,
      and besides I should die. Think of that old fellow at the corner there, our most important
      parishioner. There are no more hairs on his head than thoughts in his skull. To merely look at
      him is to rob life of its dignity. Then there is nothing in the shops but school-books and
      Sunday-school prizes. Excellent, no doubt, for any one who has not had to read as many as I
      have. Such a choir! such rain!”</p>
     <p>“You need some occupation peculiar to the place,” said the other, baiting his hooks with
      worms out of the little porringer. “I catch eels. You should set some night-lines too. You
      bait
      <pb n="12"/> them with worms in this way, and put them among the weeds at the edge of the
      river. In the morning you find an eel or two, if you have good fortune, turning round and
      round and making the weeds sway. I shall catch a great many after this rain.”</p>
     <p>“What a suggestion! Do you mean to stay here,” said Howard, “till your mind rots like our
      most important parishioner’s?”</p>
     <p>“No, no! To be quite frank with you,” replied the other, “I have some good looks and shall
      try to turn them to account by going away from here pretty soon and trying to persuade some
      girl with money to fall in love with me. I shall not be altogether a bad match, you see,
      because after she has made me a little prosperous my uncle will die and make me much more so.
      I wish to be able always to remain a lounger. Yes, I shall marry money. My mother has set her
      heart on it, and I am not, you see, the kind of person who falls
      <pb n="13"/> in love inconveniently. For the present——”</p>
     <p>“You are vegetating,” interrupted the other.</p>
     <p>“No, I am seeing the world. In your big towns a man finds his minority and knows nothing
      outside its border. He knows only the people like himself. But here one chats with the whole
      world in a day’s walk, for every man one meets is a class. The knowledge I am picking up may
      be useful to me when I enter the great cities and their ignorance. But I have lines to set.
      Come with me. I would ask you home, but you and my mother, you know, do not get on well.”</p>
     <p>“I could not live with any one I did not believe in,” said Howard; “you are so different
      from me. You can live with mere facts, and that is why, I suppose, your schemes are so
      mercenary. Before this beautiful river, these stars, these great purple shadows, do you not
      feel
      <pb n="14"/> like an insect in a flower? As for me, I also have planned my future. Not too
      near or too far from a great city I see myself in a cottage with diamond panes, sitting by the
      fire. There are books everywhere and etchings on the wall; on the table is a manuscript essay
      on some religious matter. Perhaps I shall marry some day. Probably not, for I shall ask so
      much. Certainly I shall not marry for money, for I hold the directness and sincerity of the
      nature to be its compass. If we once break it the world grows trackless.”</p>
     <p>“Good-bye,” said Sherman, briskly; “I have baited the last hook. Your schemes suit you, but
      a sluggish fellow like me, poor devil, who wishes to lounge through the world, would find them
      expensive.”</p>
     <p>They parted; Sherman to set his lines and Howard to his hotel in high spirits, for it seemed
      to him he had been eloquent. The billiard-room, which opened
      <pb n="15"/> on the street, was lighted up. A few young men came round to play sometimes. He
      went in, for among these provincial youths he felt <hi>recherché</hi>; besides, he was a
      really good player. As he came in one of the players missed and swore. Howard reproved him
      with a look. He joined the play for a time, and then catching sight through a distant door of
      the hotel-keeper’s wife putting a kettle on the hob he hurried off, and, drawing a chair to
      the fire, began one of those long gossips about everybody’s affairs peculiar to the cloth.</p>
     <p>As Sherman, having set his lines, returned home, he passed a tobacconist’s—a sweet-shop and
      tobacconist’s in one—the only shop in town, except public-houses, that remained open. The
      tobacconist was standing in his door, and, recognizing one who dealt consistently with a rival
      at the other end of the town, muttered: “There goes that <hi>gluggerabunthaun</hi> and Jack o’
      <pb n="16"/> Dreams; been fishing most likely. Ugh!” Sherman paused for a moment as he
      repassed the bridge and looked at the water, on which now a new-risen and crescent moon was
      shining dimly. How full of memories it was to him! what playmates and boyish adventures did it
      not bring to mind! To him it seemed to say, “Stay near to me,” as to Howard it had said, “Go
      yonder, to those other joys and other sceneries I have told you of.” It bade him who loved
      stay still and dream, and gave flying feet to him who imagined.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head> II.</head>
     <p>The house where Sherman and his mother lived was one of those bare houses so common in
      country towns. Their dashed fronts mounting above empty pavements have a kind of dignity in
      their utilitarianism. They seem to say, “Fashion has not made us, nor ever do its caprices
      pass our sand-cleaned doorsteps.” On every basement window is the same dingy wire blind; on
      every door the same brass knocker. Custom everywhere! “So much the longer,” the blinds seem to
      say, “have eyes glanced through us”; and the knockers to murmur, “And fingers lifted us.”</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="18"/> No. 15, Stephens’ Row, was in no manner peculiar among its twenty fellows. The
      chairs in the drawing-room facing the street were of heavy mahogany with horsehair cushions
      worn at the corners. On the round table was somebody’s commentary on the New Testament laid
      like the spokes of a wheel on a table-cover of American oilcloth with stamped Japanese figures
      half worn away. The room was seldom used, for Mrs. Sherman was solitary because silent. In
      this room the dressmaker sat twice a year, and here the rector’s wife used every month or so
      to drink a cup of tea. It was quite clean. There was not a fly-mark on the mirror, and all
      summer the fern in the grate was constantly changed. Behind this room and overlooking the
      garden was the parlour, where cane-bottomed chairs took the place of mahogany. Sherman had
      lived here with his mother all his life, and their old servant hardly remembered
      <pb n="19"/> having lived anywhere else; and soon she would absolutely cease to remember the
      world she knew before she saw the four walls of this house, for every day she forgot something
      fresh. The son was almost thirty, the mother fifty, and the servant near seventy. Every year
      they had two hundred pounds among them, and once a year the son got a new suit of clothes and
      went into the drawing-room to look at himself in the mirror.</p>
     <p>On the morning of the 20th of December Mrs. Sherman was down before her son. A spare,
      delicate-featured woman, with somewhat thin lips tightly closed as with silent people, and
      eyes at once gentle and distrustful, tempering the hardness of the lips. She helped the
      servant to set the table, and then, for her old-fashioned ideas would not allow her to rest,
      began to knit, often interrupting her knitting to go into the kitchen or to listen at the foot
      of the stairs. At last,
      <pb n="20"/> hearing a sound upstairs, she put the eggs down to boil, muttering the while, and
      began again to knit. When her son appeared she received him with a smile.</p>
     <p>“Late again, mother,” he said.</p>
     <p>“The young should sleep,” she answered, for to her he seemed still a boy.</p>
     <p>She had finished her breakfast some time before the young man, and because it would have
      appeared very wrong to her to leave the table, she sat on knitting behind the tea-urn: an
      industry the benefit of which was felt by many poor children—almost the only neighbours she
      had a good word for.</p>
     <p>“Mother,” said the young man, presently, “your friend the <hi>locum tenens</hi> is off
      to-morrow.”</p>
     <p>“A good riddance.”</p>
     <p>“Why are you so hard on him? He talked intelligently when here, I thought,” answered her
      son.</p>
     <p>“I do not like his theology,”
      <pb n="21"/> she replied, “nor his way of running about and flirting with this body and that
      body, nor his way of chattering while he buttons and unbuttons his gloves.”</p>
     <p>“You forget he is a man of the great world, and has about him a manner that must seem
      strange to us.”</p>
     <p>“Oh, he might do very well,” she answered, “for one of those Carton girls at the
      rectory.”</p>
     <p>“That eldest girl is a good girl,” replied her son.</p>
     <p>“She looks down on us all, and thinks herself intellectual,” she went on. “I remember when
      girls were content with their Catechism and their Bibles and a little practice at the piano,
      maybe, for an accomplishment. What does any one want more? It is all pride.”</p>
     <p>“You used to like her as a child,” said the young man.</p>
     <p>“I like all children.”</p>
     <p>Sherman having finished his breakfast, took a book of travels in one hand and a trowel in
      the
      <pb n="22"/> other and went out into the garden. Having looked under the parlour window for
      the first tulip shoots, he went down to the further end and began covering some sea-kale for
      forcing. He had not been long at work when the servant brought him a letter. There was a stone
      roller at one side of the grass plot. He sat down upon it, and taking the letter between his
      finger and thumb began looking at it with an air that said: “Well! I know what you mean.” He
      remained long thus without opening it, the book lying beside him on the roller.</p>
     <p>The garden—the letter—the book! You have there the three symbols of his life. Every morning
      he worked in that garden among the sights and sounds of nature. Month by month he planted and
      hoed and dug there. In the middle he had set a hedge that divided the garden in two. Above the
      hedge were flowers; below it, vegetables. At the furthest end from
      <pb n="23"/> the house, lapping broken masonry full of wallflowers, the river said, month
      after month to all upon its banks, “Hush!” He dined at two with perfect regularity, and in the
      afternoon went out to shoot or walk. At twilight he set night-lines. Later on he read. He had
      not many books—a Shakespeare, Mungo Park’s travels, a few two-shilling novels, “Percy’s
      Reliques,” and a volume on etiquette. He seldom varied his occupations. He had no profession.
      The town talked of it. They said: “He lives upon his mother,” and were very angry. They never
      let him see this, however, for it was generally understood he would be a dangerous fellow to
      rouse; but there was an uncle from whom Sherman had expectations who sometimes wrote
      remonstrating. Mrs. Sherman resented these letters, for she was afraid of her son going away
      to seek his fortune—perhaps even in America.
      <pb n="24"/> Now this matter preyed somewhat on Sherman. For three years or so he had been
      trying to make his mind up and come to some decision. Sometimes when reading he would start
      and press his lips together and knit his brows for a moment.</p>
     <p>It will now be seen why the garden, the book, and the letter were the three symbols of his
      life, summing up as they did his love of out-of-door doings, his meditations, his anxieties.
      His life in the garden had granted serenity to his forehead, the reading of his few books had
      filled his eyes with reverie, and the feeling that he was not quite a good citizen had given a
      slight and occasional trembling to his lips.</p>
     <p>He opened the letter. Its contents were what he had long expected. His uncle offered to take
      him into his office. He laid it spread out before him—a foot on each margin, right and
      left—and looked at it, turning the
      <pb n="25"/> matter over and over in his mind. Would he go? would he stay? He did not like the
      idea much. The lounger in him did not enjoy the thought of London. Gradually his mind wandered
      away into scheming—infinite scheming—what he would do if he went, what he would do if he did
      not go.</p>
     <p>A beetle, attracted by the faint sunlight, had crawled out of his hole. It saw the paper and
      crept on to it, the better to catch the sunlight. Sherman saw the beetle but his mind was not
      occupied with it. “Shall I tell Mary Carton?” he was thinking. Mary had long been his adviser
      and friend. She was, indeed, everybody’s adviser. Yes, he would ask her what to do. Then again
      he thought—no, he would decide for himself. The beetle began to move. “If it goes off the
      paper by the top I will ask her—if by the bottom I will not.”</p>
     <p>The beetle went off by the
      <pb n="26"/> top. He got up with an air of decision and went into the tool-house and began
      sorting seeds and picking out the light ones, sometimes stopping to watch a spider; for he
      knew he must wait till the afternoon to see Mary Carton. The tool-house was a favourite place
      with him. He often read there and watched the spiders in the corners.</p>
     <p>At dinner he was preoccupied.</p>
     <p>“Mother,” he said, “would you much mind if we went away from this?”</p>
     <p>“I have often told you,” she answered, “I do not like one place better than another. I like
      them all equally little.”</p>
     <p>After dinner he went again into the tool-house. This time he did not sort seeds—only watched
      the spiders.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head> III.</head>
     <p>Towards evening he went out. The pale sunshine of winter flickered on his path. The wind
      blew the straws about. He grew more and more melancholy. A dog of his acquaintance was chasing
      rabbits in a field. He had never been known to catch one, and since his youth had never seen
      one for he was almost wholly blind. They were his form of the eternal chimera. The dog left
      the field and followed with a friendly sniff.</p>
     <p>They came together to the rectory. Mary Carton was not in. There was a children’s practice
      in the school-house. They went thither.</p>
     <p>A child of four or five with a
      <pb n="28"/> swelling on its face was sitting under a wall opposite the school door, waiting
      to make faces at the Protestant children as they came out. Catching sight of the dog she
      seemed to debate in her mind whether to throw a stone at it or call it to her. She threw the
      stone and made it run. In after times he remembered all these things as though they were of
      importance.</p>
     <p>He opened the latched green door and went in. About twenty children were singing in shrill
      voices standing in a row at the further end. At the harmonium he recognized Mary Carton, who
      nodded to him and went on with her playing. The white-washed walls were covered with glazed
      prints of animals; at the further end was a large map of Europe; by a fire at the near end was
      a table with the remains of tea. This tea was an idea of Mary’s. They had tea and cake first,
      afterwards the singing. The floor was covered with crumbs.
      <pb n="29"/> The fire was burning brightly. Sherman sat down beside it. A child with a great
      deal of oil in her hair was sitting on the end of a form at the other side.</p>
     <p>“Look,” she whispered, “I have been sent away. At any rate they are further from the fire.
      They have to be near the harmonium. I would not sing. Do you like hymns? I don’t. Will you
      have a cup of tea? I can make it quite well. See, I did not spill a drop. Have you enough
      milk?” It was a cup full of milk—children’s tea. “Look, there is a mouse carrying away a
      crumb. Hush!”</p>
     <p>They sat there, the child watching the mouse, Sherman pondering on his letter, until the
      music ceased and the children came tramping down the room. The mouse having fled, Sherman’s
      self-appointed hostess got up with a sigh and went out with the others.</p>
     <p>Mary Carton closed the harmonium and came towards
      <pb n="30"/> Sherman. Her face and all her movements showed a gentle decision of character.
      Her glance was serene, her features regular, her figure at the same time ample and beautifully
      moulded; her dress plain yet not without a certain air of distinction. In a different society
      she would have had many suitors. But she was of a type that in country towns does not get
      married at all. Its beauty is too lacking in pink and white, its nature in that small
      assertiveness admired for character by the uninstructed. Elsewhere she would have known her
      own beauty—as it is right that all the beautiful should—and have learnt how to display it, to
      add gesture to her calm and more of mirth and smiles to her grave cheerfulness. As it was, her
      manner was much older than herself.</p>
     <p>She sat down by Sherman with the air of an old friend. They had long been accustomed
      <pb n="31"/> to consult together on every matter. They were such good friends they had never
      fallen in love with each other. Perfect love and perfect friendship are indeed incompatible;
      for the one is a battlefield where shadows war beside the combatants, and the other a placid
      country where Consultation has her dwelling.</p>
     <p>These two were such good friends that the most gossiping townspeople had given them up with
      a sigh. The doctor’s wife, a faded beauty and devoted romance reader, said one day, as they
      passed, “They are such cold creatures.” The old maid who kept the Berlin-wool shop remarked,
      “They are not of the marrying sort,” and now their comings and goings were no longer noticed.
      Nothing had ever come to break in on their quiet companionship and give obscurity as a
      dwelling-place for the needed illusions. Had one been weak and the other strong, one plain and
      the other handsome,
      <pb n="32"/> one guide and the other guided, one wise and the other foolish, love might have
      found them out in a moment, for love is based on inequality as friendship is on equality.</p>
     <p>“John,” said Mary Carton, warming her hands at the fire, “I have had a troublesome day. Did
      you come to help me teach the children to sing? It was good of you: you were just too
      late.”</p>
     <p>“No,” he answered, “I have come to be your pupil. I am always your pupil.”</p>
     <p>“Yes, and a most disobedient one.”</p>
     <p>“Well, advise me this time at any rate. My uncle has written, offering me £100 a year to
      begin with in his London office. Am I to go?”</p>
     <p>“You know quite well my answer,” she said.</p>
     <p>“Indeed I do not. Why should I go? I am contented here. I am now making my garden ready for
      spring. Later on there will be trout fishing
      <pb n="33"/> and saunters by the edge of the river in the evening when the bats are flickering
      about. In July there will be races. I enjoy the bustle. I enjoy life here. When anything
      annoys me I keep away from it, that is all. You know I am always busy. I have occupation and
      friends and am quite contented.”</p>
     <p>“It is a great loss to many of us, but you must go, John,” she said. “For you know you will
      be old some day, and perhaps when the vitality of youth is gone you will feel that your life
      is empty and find that you are too old to change it; and you will give up, perhaps, trying to
      be happy and likeable and become as the rest are. I think I can see you,” she said, with a
      laugh, “a hypochondriac, like Gorman, the retired excise officer, or with a red nose like Dr.
      Stephens, or growing like Peters, the elderly cattle merchant, who starves his horse.”</p>
     <p>“They were bad material to
      <pb n="34"/> begin with,” he answered, “and besides, I cannot take my mother away with me at
      her age, and I cannot leave her alone.”</p>
     <p>“What annoyance it may be,” she answered, “will soon be forgotten. You will be able to give
      her many more comforts. We women—we all like to be dressed well and have pleasant rooms to sit
      in, and a young man at your age should not be idle. You must go away from this little backward
      place. We shall miss you, but you are clever and must go and work with other men and have your
      talents admitted.”</p>
     <p>“How emulous you would have me. Perhaps I shall be well-to-do some day; meanwhile I only
      wish to stay here with my friends.”</p>
     <p>She went over to the window and looked out with her face turned from him. The evening light
      cast a long shadow behind her on the floor. After some moments, she said, “I see
      <pb n="35"/> people ploughing on the slope of the hill. There are people working on a house to
      the right. Everywhere there are people busy,” and, with a slight tremble in her voice, she
      added, “and, John, nowhere are there any doing what they wish. One has to think of so many
      things—of duty and God.”</p>
     <p>“Mary, I didn’t know you were so religious.”</p>
     <p>Coming towards him with a smile, she said, “No more did I, perhaps. But sometimes the self
      in one is very strong. One has to think a great deal and reason with it. Yet I try hard to
      lose myself in things about me. These children now—I often lie awake thinking about them. That
      child who was talking to you is often on my mind. I do not know what will happen to her. She
      makes me unhappy. I am afraid she is not a good child at all. I am afraid she is not taught
      well at home. I try hard to be gentle
      <pb n="36"/> and patient with her. I am a little displeased with myself to-day; so I have
      lectured you. There! I have made my confession. But,” she added, taking one of his hands in
      both hers and reddening, “you must go away. You must not be idle. You will gain
      everything.”</p>
     <p>As she stood there with bright eyes, the light of evening about her, Sherman for perhaps the
      first time saw how beautiful she was, and was flattered by her interest. For the first time
      also her presence did not make him at peace with the world.</p>
     <p>“Will you be an obedient pupil?”</p>
     <p>“You know so much more than I do,” he answered, “and are so much wiser. I will write to my
      uncle and agree to his offer.”</p>
     <p>“Now you must go home,” she said. “You must not keep your mother waiting for her tea. There!
      I have raked the fire out. We must not forget to lock the door behind us.”</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="37"/> As they stood on the doorstep the wind blew a whirl of dead leaves about
      them.</p>
     <p>“They are my old thoughts,” he said; “see, they are all withered.”</p>
     <p>They walked together silently. At the vicarage he left her and went homeward.</p>
     <p>The deserted flour store at the corner of two roads, the house that had been burnt hollow
      ten years before and still lifted its blackened beams, the straggling and leafless fruit-trees
      rising above garden walls, the church where he was christened—these foster-mothers of his
      infancy seemed to nod and shake their heads over him.</p>
     <p>“Mother,” he said, hurriedly entering the room, “we are going to London.”</p>
     <p>“As you wish. I always knew you would be a rolling stone,” she answered, and went out to
      tell the servant that as soon as she had finished the week’s washing they must pack up
      <pb n="38"/> everything, for they were going to London.</p>
     <p>“Yes, we must pack up,” said the old peasant; she did not stop peeling the onion in her
      hand—she had not comprehended. In the middle of the night she suddenly started up in bed with
      a pale face and a prayer to the Virgin whose image hung over her head—she had now
      comprehended.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>IV.</head>
     <p>On January the 5th about two in the afternoon, Sherman sat on the deck of the steamer
       <hi>Lavinia</hi> enjoying a period of sunshine between two showers. The steamer
       <hi>Lavinia</hi> was a cattle boat. It had been his wish to travel by some more expensive
      route, but his mother, with her old-fashioned ideas of duty, would not hear of it, and now, as
      he foresaw, was extremely uncomfortable below, while he, who was a good sailor, was pretty
      happy on deck, and would have been quite so if the pigs would only tire of their continual
      squealing. With the exception
      <pb n="40"/> of a very dirty old woman sitting by a crate of geese, all the passengers but
      himself were below. This old woman made the journey monthly with geese for the Liverpool
      market.</p>
     <p>Sherman was dreaming. He began to feel very desolate, and commenced a letter to Mary Carton
      in his notebook to state this fact. He was a laborious and unpractised writer, and found it
      helped him to make a pencil copy. Sometimes he stopped and watched the puffin sleeping on the
      waves. Each one of them had its head tucked in in a somewhat different way.</p>
     <p>“That is because their characters are different,” he thought.</p>
     <p>Gradually he began to notice a great many corks floating by, one after the other. The old
      woman saw them too, and said, waking out of a half sleep—</p>
     <p>“Misther John Sherman, we will be in the Mersey before evening. Why are ye goin’ among them
      savages in London,
      <pb n="41"/> Misther John? Why don’t ye stay among your own people—for what have we in this
      life but a mouthful of air?”</p>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div type="group">
    <head> PART II. MARGARET LELAND.</head>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head> I.</head>
     <p>Sherman and his mother rented a small house on the north side of St. Peter’s Square,
      Hammersmith. The front windows looked out on to the old rank and green square, the windows
      behind on to a little patch of garden round which the houses gathered and pressed as though
      they already longed to trample it out. In this garden was a single tall pear-tree that never
      bore fruit.</p>
     <p>Three years passed by without any notable event. Sherman went every day to his office in
      Tower Hill Street, abused his work a great deal, and was not unhappy perhaps. He was probably
      <pb n="46"/> a bad clerk, but then nobody was very exacting with the nephew of the head of the
      firm.</p>
     <p>The firm of Sherman and Saunders, ship brokers, was a long-established, old-fashioned house.
      Saunders had been dead some years and old Michael Sherman ruled alone—an old bachelor full of
      family pride and pride in his wealth. He lived, for all that, in a very simple fashion. His
      mahogany furniture was a little solider than other people’s perhaps. He did not understand
      display. Display finds its excuse in some taste good or bad, and in a long industrious life
      Michael Sherman had never found leisure to form one. He seemed to live only from habit. Year
      by year he grew more silent, gradually ceasing to regard anything but his family and his
      ships. His family were represented by his nephew and his nephew’s mother. He did not feel much
      affection for them. He believed in his family—that
      <pb n="47"/> was all. To remind him of the other goal of his thoughts hung round his private
      office pictures with such inscriptions as “S.S. <hi>Indus</hi> at the Cape of Good Hope,” “The
      barque <hi>Mary</hi> in the Mozambique Channel,” “The barque <hi>Livingstone</hi> at Port
      Said,” and many more. Every rope was drawn accurately with a ruler, and here and there were
      added distant vessels sailing proudly by with all that indifference to perspective peculiar to
      the drawings of sailors. On every ship was the flag of the firm spread out to show the
      letters.</p>
     <p>No man cared for old Michael Sherman. Every one liked John. Both were silent, but the young
      man had sometimes a talkative fit. The old man lived for his ledger, the young man for his
      dreams.</p>
     <p>In spite of all these differences, the uncle was on the whole pleased with the nephew. He
      noticed a certain stolidity that was of the family. It sometimes
      <pb n="48"/> irritated others. It pleased him. He saw a hundred indications besides that made
      him say, “He is a true Sherman. We Shermans begin that way and give up frivolity as we grow
      old. We are all the same in the end.”</p>
     <p>Mrs. Sherman and her son had but a small round of acquaintances—a few rich people, clients
      of the house of Sherman and Saunders for the most part. Among these was a Miss Margaret Leland
      who lived with her mother, the widow of the late Henry Leland, ship-broker, on the eastern
      side of St. Peter’s Square. Their house was larger than the Shermans, and noticeable among its
      fellows by the newly-painted hall door. Within on every side were bronzes and china vases and
      heavy curtains. In all were displayed the curious and vagrant taste of Margaret Leland. The
      rich Italian and mediæval draperies of the pre-Raphaelites
      <pb n="49"/> jostling the brightest and vulgarest products of more native and Saxon schools.
      Vases of the most artistic shape and colour side by side with artificial flowers and stuffed
      birds. This house belonged to the Lelands. They had bought it in less prosperous days, and
      having altered it according to their taste and the need of their growing welfare could not
      decide to leave it.</p>
     <p>Sherman was an occasional caller at the Lelands, and had certainly a liking, though not a
      very deep one, for Margaret. As yet he knew little more about her than that she wore the most
      fascinating hats, that the late Lord Lytton was her favourite author, and that she hated
      frogs. It is clear that she did not know that a French writer on magic says the luxurious and
      extravagant hate frogs because they are cold, solitary, and dreary. Had she done so, she would
      have been more circumspect about revealing her tastes.</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="50"/> For the rest John Sherman was forgetting the town of Ballah. He corresponded
      indeed with Mary Carton, but his laborious letter writing made his letters fewer and fewer.
      Sometimes, too, he heard from Howard, who had a curacy in Glasgow and was on indifferent terms
      with his parishioners. They objected to his way of conducting the services. His letters were
      full of it. He would not give in, he said, whatever happened. His conscience was involved.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>II.</head>
     <p>One afternoon Mrs. Leland called on Mrs. Sherman. She very often called—this fat,
      sentimental woman, moving in the midst of a cloud of scent. The day was warm, and she carried
      her too elaborate and heavy dress as a large caddis-fly drags its case with much labour and
      patience. She sat down on the sofa with obvious relief, leaning so heavily among the cushions
      that a clothes-moth in an antimacassar thought the end of the world had come and fluttered out
      only to be knocked down and crushed by Mrs. Sherman, who was very quick in her movements.</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="52"/> As soon as she found her breath, Mrs. Leland began a long history of her sorrows.
      Her daughter Margaret, had been jilted and was in despair, had taken to her bed with every
      resolution to die, and was growing paler and paler. The hard-hearted man, though she knew he
      had heard, did not relent. She knew he had heard because her daughter had told his sister all
      about it, and his sister had no heart, because she said it was temper that ailed Margaret, and
      she was a little vixen, and that if she had not flirted with everybody the engagement would
      never have been broken off. But Mr. Sims had no heart clearly, as Miss Marriot and Mrs. Eliza
      Taylor, her daughter’s friends, said, when they heard, and Lock, the butler, said the same
      too, and Mary Young, the housemaid, said so too—and she knew all about it, for Margaret used
      to read his letters to her often when having her hair brushed.</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="53"/> “She must have been very fond of him,” said Mrs. Sherman.</p>
     <p>“She is so romantic, my dear,” answered Mrs. Leland, with a sigh. “I am afraid she takes
      after an uncle on her father’s side, who wrote poetry and wore a velvet jacket and ran away
      with an Italian countess who used to get drunk. When I married Mr. Leland people said he was
      not worthy of me, and that I was throwing myself away—and he in business, too! But Margaret is
      so romantic. There was Mr. Walters, the gentleman farmer, and Simpson who had a jeweller’s
      shop—I never approved of him!—and Mr. Samuelson, and the Hon. William Scott. She tired of them
      all except the Hon. William Scott, who tired of her because some one told him she put
      belladonna in her eyes—and it is not true; and now there is Mr. Sims!” She then cried a
      little, and allowed herself to be consoled by Mrs. Sherman.</p>
     <p>“You talk so intelligently and
      <pb n="54"/> are so well informed,” she said at parting. “I have made a very pleasant call,”
      and the caddis-worm toiled upon its way, arriving in due course at other cups of tea.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>III.</head>
     <p>The day after Mrs. Leland’s call upon his mother, John Sherman, returning home after his not
      very lengthy day in the office, saw Margaret coming towards him. She had a lawn tennis racket
      under her arm, and was walking slowly on the shady side of the road. She was a pretty girl
      with quite irregular features, who though really not more than pretty, had so much manner, so
      much of an air, that every one called her a beauty: a trefoil with the fragrance of a
      rose.</p>
     <p>“Mr. Sherman,” she cried, coming smiling to meet him, “I
      <pb n="56"/> have been ill, but could not stand the house any longer. I am going to the Square
      to play tennis. Will you come with me?”</p>
     <p>“I am a bad player,” he said.</p>
     <p>“Of course you are,” she answered; “but you are the only person under a hundred to be found
      this afternoon. How dull life is!” she continued, with a sigh. “You heard how ill I have been?
      What do you do all day?”</p>
     <p>“I sit at a desk, sometimes writing, and sometimes, when I get lazy, looking up at the
      flies. There are fourteen on the plaster of the ceiling over my head. They died two winters
      ago. I sometimes think to have them brushed off, but they have been there so long now I hardly
      like to.”</p>
     <p>“Ah! you like them,” she said, “because you are accustomed to them. In most cases there is
      not much more to be said for our family affections, I think.”</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="57"/> “In a room close at hand,” he went on, “there is, you know, Uncle Michael, who
      never speaks.”</p>
     <p>“Precisely. You have an uncle who never speaks; I have a mother who never is silent. She
      went to see Mrs. Sherman the other day. What did she say to her?”</p>
     <p>“Nothing.”</p>
     <p>“Really. What a dull thing existence is!”—this with a great sigh. “When the Fates are
      weaving our web of life some mischievous goblin always runs off with the dye-pot. Everything
      is dull and grey. Am I looking a little pale? I have been so very ill.”</p>
     <p>“A little bit pale, perhaps,” he said, doubtfully.</p>
     <p>The Square gate brought them to a stop. It was locked, but she had the key. The lock was
      stiff, but turned easily for John Sherman.</p>
     <p>“How strong you are,” she said.</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="58"/> It was an iridescent evening of spring. The leaves of the bushes had still their
      faint green. As Margaret darted about at the tennis, a red feather in her cap seemed to
      rejoice with its wearer. Everything was at once gay and tranquil. The whole world had that
      unreal air it assumes at beautiful moments, as though it might vanish at a touch like an
      iridescent soap-bubble.</p>
     <p>After a little Margaret said she was tired, and, sitting on a garden seat among the bushes,
      began telling him the plots of novels lately read by her. Suddenly she cried—</p>
     <p>“The novel-writers were all serious people like you. They are so hard on people like me.
      They always make us come to a bad end. They <hi>say</hi> we are always acting, acting, acting;
      and what else do you serious people do? You act before the world. I think, do you know,
       <hi>we</hi> act before ourselves. All the old
      <pb n="59"/> foolish kings and queens in history were like us. They laughed and beckoned and
      went to the block for no very good purpose. I dare say the headsmen were like you.”</p>
     <p>“We would never cut off so pretty a head.”</p>
     <p>“Oh, yes, you would—you would cut off mine to-morrow.” All this she said vehemently,
      piercing him with her bright eyes. “You would cut off my head to-morrow,” she repeated, almost
      fiercely; “I tell you you would.”</p>
     <p>Her departure was always unexpected, her moods changed with so much rapidity. “Look!” she
      said, pointing where the clock on St. Peter’s church showed above the bushes. “Five minutes to
      five. In five minutes my mother’s tea-hour. It is like growing old. I go to gossip.
      Good-bye.”</p>
     <p>The red feather shone for a moment among the bushes and was gone.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>IV.</head>
     <p>The next day and the day after, Sherman was followed by those bright eyes. When he opened a
      letter at his desk they seemed to gaze at him from the open paper, and to watch him from the
      flies upon the ceiling. He was even a worse clerk than usual.</p>
     <p>One evening he said to his mother, “Miss Leland has beautiful eyes.”</p>
     <p>“My dear, she puts belladonna in them.”</p>
     <p>“What a thing to say!”</p>
     <p>“I know she does, though her mother denies it.”</p>
     <p>“Well, she is certainly beautiful,” he answered.</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="61"/> “My dear, if she has an attraction for you, I don’t want to discourage it. She is
      rich as girls go nowadays; and one woman has one fault, another another: one’s untidy, one
      fights with her servants, one fights with her friends, another has a crabbed tongue when she
      talks of them.”</p>
     <p>Sherman became again silent, finding no fragment of romance in such discourse.</p>
     <p>In the next week or two he saw much of Miss Leland. He met her almost every evening on his
      return from the office, walking slowly, her racket under her arm. They played tennis much and
      talked more. Sherman began to play tennis in his dreams. Miss Leland told him all about
      herself, her friends, her inmost feelings; and yet every day he knew less about her. It was
      not merely that saying everything she said nothing, but that continually there came through
      her wild words the sound of the mysterious
      <pb n="62"/> flutes and viols of that unconscious nature which dwells so much nearer to woman
      than to man. How often do we not endow the beautiful and candid with depth and mystery not
      their own? We do not know that we but hear in their voices those flutes and viols playing to
      us of the alluring secret of the world.</p>
     <p>Sherman had never known in early life what is called first love, and now, when he had passed
      thirty, it came to him that love more of the imagination than of either the senses or
      affections: it was mainly the eyes that followed him.</p>
     <p>It is not to be denied that as this love grew serious it grew mercenary. Now active, now
      latent, the notion had long been in Sherman’s mind, as we know, that he should marry money. A
      born lounger, riches tempted him greatly. When those eyes haunted him from the fourteen flies
      on the ceiling, he would say, “I should be rich; I should have a
      <pb n="63"/> house in the country; I should hunt and shoot, and have a garden and three
      gardeners; I should leave this abominable office.” Then the eyes became even more beautiful.
      It was a new kind of belladonna.</p>
     <p>He shrank a little, however, from choosing even this pleasant pathway. He had planned many
      futures for himself and learnt to love them all. It was this that had made him linger on at
      Ballah for so long, and it was this that now kept him undecided. He would have to give up the
      universe for a garden and three gardeners. How sad it was to make substantial even the best of
      his dreams. How hard it was to submit to that decree which compels every step we take in life
      to be a death in the imagination. How difficult it was to be so enwrapped in this one new hope
      as not to hear the lamentations that were going on in dim corners of his mind.</p>
     <p>One day he resolved to propose.
      <pb n="64"/> He examined himself in the glass in the morning; and for the first time in his
      life smiled to see how good-looking he was. In the evening before leaving the office he peered
      at himself in the mirror over the mantlepiece in the room where customers were received. The
      sun was blazing through the window full on his face. He did not look so well. Immediately all
      courage left him.</p>
     <p>That evening he went out after his mother had gone to bed and walked far along the
      towing-path of the Thames. A faint mist half covered away the houses and factory chimneys on
      the further side; beside him a band of osiers swayed softly, the deserted and full river
      lapping their stems. He looked on all these things with foreign eyes. He had no sense of
      possession. Indeed it seemed to him that everything in London was owned by too many to be
      owned by any one. Another river that he did seem to possess flowed
      <pb n="65"/> through his memory with all its familiar sights—boys riding in the stream to the
      saddle-girths, fish leaping, water-flies raising their small ripples, a swan asleep, the
      wallflowers growing on the red brick of the margin. He grew very sad. Suddenly a shooting
      star, fiery and vagabond, leaped from the darkness. It brought his mind again in a moment to
      Margaret Leland. To marry her, he thought, was to separate himself from the old life he loved
      so well.</p>
     <p>Crossing the river at Putney, he hurried homewards among the market gardens. Nearing home,
      the streets were deserted, the shops closed. Where King Street joins the Broadway, entirely
      alone with itself, in the very centre of the road a little black cat was leaping after its
      shadow.</p>
     <p>“Ah!” he thought, “it would be a good thing to be a little black cat. To leap about in the
      moonlight and sleep in the sunlight,
      <pb n="66"/> and catch flies, to have no hard tasks to do or hard decisions to come to, to be
      simple and full of animal spirits.”</p>
     <p>At the corner of Bridge Road was a coffee-stall, the only sign of human life. He bought some
      cold meat and flung it to the little black cat.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head> V.</head>
     <p>Some more days went by. At last, one day, arriving at the Square somewhat earlier than
      usual, and sitting down to wait for Margaret on the seat among the bushes, he noticed the
      pieces of a torn-up letter lying about. Beside him on the seat was a pencil, as though some
      one had been writing there and left it behind them. The pencil-lead was worn very short. The
      letter had been torn up, perhaps, in a fit of impatience.</p>
     <p>In a half-mechanical way he glanced over the scraps. On one of them he read: “<hi>My dear
       Eliza</hi>,—What an incurable gossip
      <pb n="68"/> my mother is. You heard of my misfortune. I nearly died——” Here he had to search
      among the scraps; at last he found one that seemed to follow. “Perhaps you will hear news from
      me soon. There is a handsome young man who pays me attention, and——” Here another piece had to
      be found. “I would take him though he had a face like the man in the moon, and limped like the
      devil at the theatre. Perhaps I am a little in love. Oh! friend of my heart——” Here it broke
      off again. He was interested, and searched the grass and the bushes for fragments. Some had
      been blown to quite a distance. He got together several sentences now. “I will not spend
      another winter with my mother for anything. All this is, of course, a secret. I had to tell
      somebody; secrets are bad for my health. Perhaps it will all come to nothing.” Then the letter
      went off into dress, the last novel the
      <pb n="69"/> writer had read, and so forth. A Miss Sims, too, was mentioned, who had said some
      unkind thing of the writer.</p>
     <p>Sherman was greatly amused. It did not seem to him wrong to read—we do not mind spying on
      one of the crowd, any more than on the personages of literature. It never occurred to him that
      he, or any friend of his, was concerned in these pencil scribblings.</p>
     <p>Suddenly he saw this sentence: “Heigho! your poor Margaret is falling in love again; condole
      with her, my dear.”</p>
     <p>He started. The name “Margaret,” the mention of Miss Sims, the style of the whole letter,
      all made plain the authorship. Very desperately ashamed of himself, he got up and tore each
      scrap of paper into still smaller fragments and scattered them far apart.</p>
     <p>That evening he proposed, and was accepted.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>VI.</head>
     <p>For several days there was a new heaven and a new earth. Miss Leland seemed suddenly
      impressed with the seriousness of life. She was gentleness itself; and as Sherman sat on
      Sunday mornings in his pocket-handkerchief of a garden under the one tree, with its smoky
      stem, watching the little circles of sunlight falling from the leaves like a shower of new
      sovereigns, he gazed at them with a longer and keener joy than heretofore—a new heaven and a
      new earth, surely!</p>
     <p>Sherman planted and dug and raked this pocket-handkerchief of a garden most diligently,
      rooting
      <pb n="71"/> out the docks and dandelions and mouse-ear and the patches of untimely grass. It
      was the point of contact between his new life and the old. It was far too small and unfertile
      and shaded in to satisfy his love of gardener’s experiments and early vegetables.</p>
     <p>Perforce this husbandry was too little complex for his affections to gather much round plant
      and bed. His garden in Ballah used to touch him like the growth of a young family.</p>
     <p>Now he was content to satisfy his barbaric sense of colour; right round were planted
      alternate holyhock and sunflower, and behind them scarlet-runners showed their inch-high
      cloven shoots.</p>
     <p>One Sunday it occurred to him to write to his friends on the matter of his engagement. He
      numbered them over. Howard, one or two less intimate, and Mary Carton. At that name he paused;
      he would not write just yet.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>VII.</head>
     <p>One Saturday there was a tennis party. Miss Leland devoted herself all day to a young
      Foreign Office clerk. She played tennis with him, talked with him, drank lemonade with him,
      had neither thoughts nor words for any one else. John Sherman was quite happy. Tennis was
      always a bore, and now he was not called upon to play. It had not struck him there was
      occasion for jealousy.</p>
     <p>As the guests were dispersing, his betrothed came to him. Her manner seemed strange.</p>
     <p>“Does anything ail you, Margaret?” he asked, as they left the Square.</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="73"/> “Everything,” she answered, looking about her with ostentatious secrecy. “You are
      a most annoying person. You have no feeling; you have no temperament; you are quite the most
      stupid creature I was ever engaged to.”</p>
     <p>“What is wrong with you?” he asked, in bewilderment.</p>
     <p>“Don’t you see,” she replied, with a broken voice, “I flirted all day with that young clerk?
      You should have nearly killed me with jealousy. You do not love me a bit! There is no knowing
      what I might do!”</p>
     <p>“Well, you know,” he said, “it was not right of you. People might say, ‘Look at John
      Sherman; how furious he must be!’ To be sure I wouldn’t be furious a bit; but then they’d go
      about saying I was. It would not matter, of course; but you know it is not right of you.”</p>
     <p>“It is no use pretending you have feeling. It is all that miserable little town you come
      <pb n="74"/> from, with its sleepy old shops and its sleepy old society. I would give up
      loving you this minute,” she added, with a caressing look, “if you had not that beautiful
      bronzed face. I will improve you. To-morrow evening you must come to the opera.” Suddenly she
      changed the subject. “Do you see that little fat man coming out of the Square and staring at
      me? I was engaged to him once. Look at the four old ladies behind him, shaking their bonnets
      at me. Each has some story about me, and it will be all the same in a hundred years.”</p>
     <p>After this he had hardly a moment’s peace. She kept him continually going to theatres,
      operas, parties. These last were an especial trouble; for it was her wont to gather about her
      an admiring circle to listen to her extravagancies, and he was no longer at the age when we
      enjoy audacity for its own sake.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>VIII.</head>
     <p>Gradually those bright eyes of his imagination, watching him from letters and from among the
      fourteen flies on the ceiling, had ceased to be centres of peace. They seemed like two
      whirlpools, wherein the order and quiet of his life were absorbed hourly and daily.</p>
     <p>He still thought sometimes of the country house of his dreams and of the garden and the
      three gardeners, but somehow they had lost half their charm.</p>
     <p>He had written to Howard and some others, and commenced, at last, a letter to Mary Carton.
      It lay unfinished on his desk; a thin coating of dust was gathering upon it.</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="76"/> Mrs. Leland called continually on Mrs. Sherman. She sentimentalized over the
      lovers, and even wept over them; each visit supplied the household with conversation for a
      week.</p>
     <p>Every Sunday morning—his letter-writing time—Sherman looked at his uncompleted letter.
      Gradually it became plain to him he could not finish it. It had never seemed to him he had
      more than friendship for Mary Carton, yet somehow it was not possible to tell her of this
      love-affair.</p>
     <p>The more his betrothed troubled him the more he thought about the unfinished letter. He was
      a man standing at the cross-roads.</p>
     <p>Whenever the wind blew from the south he remembered his friend, for that is the wind that
      fills the heart with memory.</p>
     <p>One Sunday he removed the dust from the face of the letter almost reverently, as though it
      were the dust from the wheels of destiny. But the letter remained unfinished.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>IX.</head>
     <p>One Wednesday in June Sherman arrived home an hour earlier than usual from his office, as
      his wont was the first Wednesday in every month, on which day his mother was at home to her
      friends. They had not many callers. To-day there was no one as yet but a badly-dressed old
      lady his mother had picked up he knew not where. She had been looking at his photograph album,
      and recalling names and dates from her own prosperous times. As she went out Miss Leland came
      in. She gave the old lady in passing a critical look that made the poor creature very
      conscious of a
      <pb n="78"/> threadbare mantle, and went over to Mrs. Sherman, holding out both hands.
      Sherman, who knew all his mother’s peculiarities, noticed on her side a slight coldness;
      perhaps she did not altogether like this beautiful dragon-fly.</p>
     <p>“I have come,” said Miss Leland, “to tell John that he must learn to paint. Music and
      society are not enough. There is nothing like art to give refinement.” Then turning to John
      Sherman—“My dear, I will make you quite different. You are a dreadful barbarian, you
      know.”</p>
     <p>“What ails me, Margaret?”</p>
     <p>“Just look at that necktie! Nothing shows a man’s cultivation like his necktie. Then your
      reading! You never read anything but old books nobody wants to talk about. I will lend you
      three every one has read this month. You really must acquire small talk and change your
      necktie.”</p>
     <p>Presently she noticed the
      <pb n="79"/> photograph-book lying open on a chair.</p>
     <p>“Oh!” she cried, “I must have another look at John’s beauties.”</p>
     <p>It was a habit of his to gather all manner of pretty faces. It came from incipient old
      bachelorhood, perhaps.</p>
     <p>Margaret criticized each photo in turn with, “Ah! she looks as if she had some life in her!”
      or, “I do not like your sleepy eyelids,” or some such phrase. The mere relations were passed
      by without a word. One face occurred several times—a quiet face. As Margaret came on this one
      for the third time, Mrs. Sherman, who seemed a little resentful about something, said—</p>
     <p>“That is his friend, Mary Carton.”</p>
     <p>“He told me about her. He has a book she gave him. So that is she? How interesting! I pity
      these poor country people. It must be hard to keep from getting stupid.”</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="80"/> “My friend is not at all stupid,” said Sherman.</p>
     <p>“Does she speak with a brogue? I remember you told me she was very good. It must be
      difficult to keep from talking platitudes when one is very good.”</p>
     <p>“You are quite wrong about her. You would like her very much,” he replied.</p>
     <p>“She is one of those people, I suppose, who can only talk about their relatives, or their
      families, or about their friends’ children: how this one has got the hooping-cough, and this
      one is getting well of the measles!” She kept swaying one of the leaves between her finger and
      thumb impatiently. “What a strange way she does her hair; and what an ugly dress!”</p>
     <p>“You must not talk that way about her—she is my great friend.”</p>
     <p>“Friend! friend!” she burst out. “He thinks I will believe in friendship between a man and a
      woman.”</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="81"/> She got up, and said, turning round with an air of changing the subject, “Have
      you written to your friends about our engagement? You had not done so when I asked you
      lately.”</p>
     <p>“I have.”</p>
     <p>“All?”</p>
     <p>“Well, not all.”</p>
     <p>“Your great friend, Miss——what do you call her?”</p>
     <p>“Miss Carton. I have not written to her.”</p>
     <p>She tapped impatiently with her foot.</p>
     <p>“They were really old companions—that is all,” said Mrs. Sherman, wishing to mend matters.
      “They were both readers; that brought them together. I never much fancied her. Yet she was
      well enough as a friend, and helped, maybe, with reading, and the gardening, and his good
      bringing-up, to keep him from the idle young men of the neighbourhood.”</p>
     <p>“You must make him write and tell her at once—you must,
      <pb n="82"/> you must!” almost sobbed out Miss Leland.</p>
     <p>“I promise,” he answered.</p>
     <p>Immediately returning to herself, she cried, “If I were in her place I know what I would
      like to do when I got the letter. I know who I would like to kill!”—this with a laugh as she
      went over, and looked at herself in the mirror over the mantlepiece.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div type="group">
    <head> PART III. JOHN SHERMAN REVISITS BALLAH.</head>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head> I.</head>
     <p>The others had gone, and Sherman was alone in the drawing-room by himself, looking through
      the window. Never had London seemed to him so like a reef whereon he was cast away. In the
      Square the bushes were covered with dust; some sparrows were ruffling their feathers on the
      side-walk; people passed, continually disturbing them. The sky was full of smoke. A terrible
      feeling of solitude in the midst of a multitude oppressed him. A portion of his life was
      ending. He thought that soon he would be no longer a young man, and now, at the period when
      the
      <pb n="86"/> desire of novelty grows less, was coming the great change of his life. He felt he
      was of those whose granaries are in the past. And now this past would never renew itself. He
      was going out into the distance as though with strange sailors in a strange ship.</p>
     <p>He longed to see again the town where he had spent his childhood: to see the narrow roads
      and mean little shops. And perhaps it would be easier to tell her who had been the friend of
      so many years of this engagement in his own person than by letter. He wondered why it was so
      hard to write so simple a thing.</p>
     <p>It was his custom to act suddenly on his decisions. He had not made many in his life. The
      next day he announced at the office that he would be absent for three or four days. He told
      his mother he had business in the country.</p>
     <p>His betrothed met him on the
      <pb n="87"/> way to the terminus, as he was walking, bag in hand, and asked where he was
      going. “I am going on business to the country,” he said, and blushed. He was creeping away
      like a thief.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>II.</head>
     <p>He arrived in the town of Ballah by rail, for he had avoided the slow cattle steamer and
      gone by Dublin.</p>
     <p>It was the forenoon, and he made for the Imperial Hotel to wait till four in the evening,
      when he would find Mary Carton in the schoolhouse, for he had timed his journey so as to
      arrive on Thursday, the day of the children’s practice.</p>
     <p>As he went through the streets his heart went out to every familiar place and sight: the
      rows of tumble-down thatched cottages; the slated roofs of the shops; the women selling
      gooseberries;
      <pb n="89"/> the river bridge; the high walls of the garden where it was said the gardener
      used to see the ghost of a former owner in the shape of a rabbit; the street corner no child
      would pass at nightfall for fear of the headless soldier; the deserted flour store; the
      wharves covered with grass. All these he watched with Celtic devotion, that devotion carried
      to the ends of the world by the Celtic exiles, and since old time surrounding their
      journeyings with rumour of plaintive songs.</p>
     <p>He sat in the window of the Imperial Hotel, now full of guests. He did not notice any of
      them. He sat there meditating, meditating. Grey clouds covering the town with flying shadows
      rushed by like the old and dishevelled eagles that Maeldune saw hurrying towards the waters of
      life. Below in the street passed by country people, townspeople, travellers, women with
      baskets, boys driving donkeys, old men
      <pb n="90"/> with sticks; sometimes he recognized a face or was recognized himself, and
      welcomed by some familiar voice.</p>
     <p>“You have come home a handsomer gentleman than your father, Misther John, and he was a neat
      figure of a man, God bless him!” said the waiter, bringing him his lunch; and in truth Sherman
      had grown handsomer for these years away. His face and gesture had more of dignity, for on the
      centre of his nature life had dropped a pinch of experience.</p>
     <p>At four he left the hotel and waited near the schoolhouse till the children came running
      out. One or two of the elder ones he recognized but turned away.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>III.</head>
     <p>Mary Carton was locking the harmonium as he went in. She came to meet him with a surprised
      and joyful air.</p>
     <p>“How often I have wished to see you. When did you come? How well you remembered my habits to
      know where to find me. My dear John, how glad I am to see you.”</p>
     <p>“You are the same as when I left, and this room is the same, too.”</p>
     <p>“Yes,” she answered, “the same, only I have had some new prints hung up—prints of fruits and
      leaves and bird-nests. It was only done last week.
      <pb n="92"/> When people choose pictures and poems for children they choose out such domestic
      ones. I would not have any of the kind; children are such undomestic animals. But, John, I am
      so glad to see you in this old schoolhouse again. So little has changed with us here. Some
      have died and some have been married, and we are all a little older and the trees a little
      taller.”</p>
     <p>“I have come to tell you I am going to be married.”</p>
     <p>She became in a moment perfectly white, and sat down as though attacked with faintness. Her
      hand on the edge of the chair trembled.</p>
     <p>Sherman looked at her, and went on in a bewildered, mechanical way—“My betrothed is a Miss
      Leland. She has a good deal of money. You know my mother always wished me to marry some one
      with money. Her father, when alive, was an old client of Sherman and
      <pb n="93"/> Saunders. She is much admired in society.” Gradually his voice became a mere
      murmur. He did not seem to know that he was speaking. He stopped entirely. He was looking at
      Mary Carton.</p>
     <p>Everything around him was as it had been some three years before. The table was covered with
      cups and the floor with crumbs. Perhaps the mouse pulling at a crumb under the table was the
      same mouse as on that other evening. The only difference was the brooding daylight of summer
      and the ceaseless chirruping of the sparrows in the ivy outside. He had a confused sense of
      having lost his way. It was just the same feeling he had known as a child, when one dark night
      he had taken a wrong turning, and instead of arriving at his own house, found himself at a
      landmark he knew was miles from home.</p>
     <p>A moment earlier, however
      <pb n="94"/> difficult his life, the issues were always definite; now suddenly had entered the
      obscurity of another’s interest.</p>
     <p>Before this it had not occurred to him that Mary Carton had any stronger feeling for him
      than warm friendship.</p>
     <p>He began again, speaking in the same mechanical way—“Miss Leland lives with her mother near
      us. She is very well educated and very well connected, though she has lived always among
      business people.”</p>
     <p>Miss Carton, with a great effort, had recovered her composure.</p>
     <p>“I congratulate you,” she said. “I hope you will be always happy. You came here on some
      business for your firm, I suppose? I believe they have some connection with the town
      still.”</p>
     <p>“I only came here to tell you I was going to be married.”</p>
     <p>“Do you not think it would have been better to have
      <pb n="95"/> written?” she said, beginning to put away the children’s tea-things in a cupboard
      by the fireplace.</p>
     <p>“It would have been better,” he answered, drooping his head.</p>
     <p>Without a word, locking the door behind them, they went out. Without a word they walked the
      grey streets. Now and then a woman or a child curtseyed as they passed. Some wondered,
      perhaps, to see these old friends so silent. At the rectory they bade each other good-bye.</p>
     <p>“I hope you will be always happy,” she said. “I will pray for you and your wife. I am very
      busy with the children and old people, but I shall always find a moment to wish you well in.
      Good-bye now.”</p>
     <p>They parted; the gate in the wall closed behind her. He stayed for a few moments looking up
      at the tops of the trees and bushes showing over the wall, and at the house a little
      <pb n="96"/> way beyond. He stood considering his problem—her life, his life. His, at any
      rate, would have incident and change; hers would be the narrow existence of a woman who,
      failing to fulfil the only abiding wish she has ever formed, seeks to lose herself in
      routine—mournfulest of things on this old planet.</p>
     <p>This had been revealed: he loved Mary Carton, she loved him. He remembered Margaret Leland,
      and murmured she did well to be jealous. Then all her contemptuous words about the town and
      its inhabitants came into his mind. Once they made no impression on him, but now the sense of
      personal identity having been disturbed by this sudden revelation, alien as they were to his
      way of thinking, they began to press in on him. Mary, too, would have agreed with them, he
      thought; and might it be that at some distant time weary monotony in abandonment would have so
      weighed
      <pb n="97"/> down the spirit of Mary Carton, that she would be merely one of the old and
      sleepy whose dulness filled the place like a cloud?</p>
     <p>He went sadly towards the hotel; everything about him, the road, the sky, the feet wherewith
      he walked seeming phantasmal and without meaning.</p>
     <p>He told the waiter he would leave by the first train in the morning. “What! and you only
      just come home?” the man answered. He ordered coffee and could not drink it. He went out and
      came in again immediately. He went down into the kitchen and talked to the servants. They told
      him of everything that had happened since he had gone. He was not interested, and went up to
      his room. “I must go home and do what people expect of me; one must be careful to do
      that.”</p>
     <p>Through all the journey home his problem troubled him. He saw the figure of Mary
      <pb n="98"/> Carton perpetually passing through a round of monotonous duties. He saw his own
      life among aliens going on endlessly, wearily.</p>
     <p>From Holyhead to London his fellow-travellers were a lady and her three young daughters, the
      eldest about twelve. The smooth faces shining with well-being became to him ominous symbols.
      He hated them. They were symbolic of the indifferent world about to absorb him, and of the
      vague something that was dragging him inch by inch from the nook he had made for himself in
      the chimney corner. He was at one of those dangerous moments when the sense of personal
      identity is shaken, when one’s past and present seem about to dissolve partnership. He sought
      refuge in memory, and counted over every word of Mary’s he could remember. He forgot the
      present and the future. “Without love,” he said to himself, “we would be either gods or
      vegetables.”</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="99"/> The rain beat on the window of the carriage. He began to listen; thought and
      memory became a blank; his mind was full of the sound of rain-drops.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div type="group">
    <head> PART IV. THE REV. WILLIAM HOWARD.</head>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head> I.</head>
     <p>After his return to London Sherman for a time kept to himself, going straight home from his
      office, moody and self-absorbed, trying not to consider his problem—her life, his life. He
      often repeated to himself, “I must do what people expect of me. It does not rest with me
      now—my choosing time is over.” He felt that whatever way he turned he would do a great evil to
      himself and others. To his nature all sudden decisions were difficult, and so he kept to the
      groove he had entered upon. It did not even occur to him to do otherwise. He never thought of
      <pb n="104"/> breaking this engagement off and letting people say what they would. He was
      bound in hopelessly by a chain of congratulations.</p>
     <p>A week passed slowly as a month. The wheels of the cabs and carriages seemed to be rolling
      through his mind. He often remembered the quiet river at the end of his garden in the town of
      Ballah. How the weeds swayed there, and the salmon leaped! At the week’s end came a note from
      Miss Leland, complaining of his neglecting her so many days. He sent a rather formal answer,
      promising to call soon. To add to his other troubles a cold east wind arose and made him
      shiver continually.</p>
     <p>One evening he and his mother were sitting silent, the one knitting, the other half-asleep.
      He had been writing letters and was now in a reverie. Round the walls were one or two
      drawings, done by him at school. His
      <pb n="105"/> mother had got them framed. His eyes were fixed on a drawing of a stream and
      some astonishing cows.</p>
     <p>A few days ago he had found an old sketch-book for children among some forgotten papers,
      which taught how to draw a horse by making three ovals for the basis of his body, one lying
      down in the middle, two standing up at each end for flank and chest, and how to draw a cow by
      basing its body on a square. He kept trying to fit squares into the cows. He was half inclined
      to take them out of their frames and retouch on this new principle. Then he began somehow to
      remember the child with the swollen face who threw a stone at the dog the day he resolved to
      leave home first. Then some other image came. His problem moved before him in a disjointed
      way. He was dropping asleep. Through his reverie came the click, click of his mother’s
      needles. She had
      <pb n="106"/> found some London children to knit for. He was at that marchland between waking
      and dreaming where our thoughts begin to have a life of their own—the region where art is
      nurtured and inspiration born.</p>
     <p>He started, hearing something sliding and rustling, and looked up to see a piece of
      cardboard fall from one end of the mantlepiece, and, driven by a slight gust of air, circle
      into the ashes under the grate.</p>
     <p>“Oh,” said his mother, “that is the portrait of the <hi>locum tenens</hi>.” She still spoke
      of the Rev. William Howard by the name she had first known him by. “He is always being
      photographed. They are all over the house, and I, an old woman, have not had one taken all my
      life. Take it out with the tongs.” Her son after some poking in the ashes, for it had fallen
      far back, brought out a somewhat dusty photograph. “That,” she continued, “is one he sent us
      <pb n="107"/> two or three months ago. It has been lying in the letter-rack since.”</p>
     <p>“He is not so spick and span looking as usual,” said Sherman, rubbing the ashes off the
      photograph with his sleeve.</p>
     <p>“By the by,” his mother replied, “he has lost his parish, I hear. He is very mediæval, you
      know, and he lately preached a sermon to prove that children who die unbaptized are lost. He
      had been reading up the subject and was full of it. The mothers turned against him, not being
      so familiar with St. Augustine as he was. There were other reasons in plenty too. I wonder
      that any one can stand that monkeyish fantastic family.”</p>
     <p>As the way is with so many country-bred people, the world for her was divided up into
      families rather than individuals.</p>
     <p>While she was talking, Sherman, who had returned to his chair, leant over the table and
      began to write hurriedly. She
      <pb n="108"/> was continuing her denunciation when he interrupted with—“Mother, I have just
      written this letter to him:—</p>
     <quote>
      <p>“‘<hi>My dear Howard</hi>:</p>
      <p>“‘Will you come and spend the autumn with us? I hear you are unoccupied just now. I am
       engaged to be married, as you know; it will be a long engagement. You will like my betrothed.
       I hope you will be great friends.</p>
      <p>“‘Yours expectantly,</p>
      <p>“‘<hi>John Sherman</hi>.’”</p>
     </quote>
     <p>“You rather take me aback,” she said.</p>
     <p>“I really like him,” he answered. “You were always prejudiced against the Howards. Forgive
      me, but I really want very much to have him here.”</p>
     <p>“Well, if you like him, I suppose I have no objection.”</p>
     <p>“I do like him. He is very clever,” said her son, “and knows a great deal. I wonder
      <pb n="109"/> he does not marry. Do you not think he would make a good husband?—for you must
      admit he is sympathetic.”</p>
     <p>“It is not difficult to sympathize with every one if you have no true principles and
      convictions.”</p>
     <p>Principles and convictions were her names for that strenuous consistency attained without
      trouble by men and women of few ideas.</p>
     <p>“I am sure you will like him better,” said the other, “when you see more of him.”</p>
     <p>“Is that photograph quite spoilt?” she answered.</p>
     <p>“No; there was nothing on it but ashes.”</p>
     <p>“That is a pity, for one less would be something.”</p>
     <p>After this they both became silent, she knitting, he gazing at the cows browsing at the edge
      of their stream, and trying to fit squares into their bodies; but now a smile played about his
      lips.</p>
     <p>Mrs. Sherman looked a little
      <pb n="110"/> troubled. She would not object to any visitor of her son’s, but quite made up
      her mind in no manner to put herself out to entertain the Rev. William Howard. She was puzzled
      as well. She did not understand the suddenness of this invitation. They usually talked over
      things for weeks.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>II.</head>
     <p>Next day his fellow-clerks noticed a decided improvement in Sherman’s spirits. He had a
      lark-like cheerfulness and alacrity breaking out at odd moments. When evening came he called,
      for the first time since his return, on Miss Leland. She scolded him roundly for having
      answered her note in such a formal way, but was sincerely glad to see him return to his
      allegiance. We have said he had sometimes, though rarely, a talkative fit. He had one this
      evening. The last play they had been to, the last party, the picture of the year, all in turn
      he glanced at.
      <pb n="112"/> She was delighted. Her training had not been in vain. Her barbarian was learning
      to chatter. This flattered her a deal.</p>
     <p>“I was never engaged,” she thought, “to a more interesting creature.”</p>
     <p>When he had risen to go Sherman said—“I have a friend coming to visit me in a few days; you
      will suit each other delightfully. He is very mediæval.”</p>
     <p>“Do tell me about him; I like everything mediæval.”</p>
     <p>“Oh,” he cried, with a laugh, “his mediævalism is not in your line. He is neither a gay
      troubadour nor a wicked knight. He is a High Church curate.”</p>
     <p>“Do not tell me anything more about him,” she answered; “I will try to be civil to him, but
      you know I never liked curates. I have been an agnostic for many years. You, I believe, are
      orthodox.”</p>
     <p>As Sherman was on his way home he met a fellow-clerk, and stopped him with—</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="113"/> “Are you an agnostic?”</p>
     <p>“No. Why, what is that?”</p>
     <p>“Oh, nothing! Good-bye,” he made answer, and hurried on his way.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>III.</head>
     <p>The letter reached the Rev. William Howard at the right moment, arriving as it did in the
      midst of a crisis in his fortunes. In the course of a short life he had lost many parishes. He
      considered himself a martyr, but was considered by his enemies a clerical coxcomb. He had a
      habit of getting his mind possessed with some strange opinion, or what seemed so to his
      parishioners, and of preaching it while the notion lasted in the most startling way. The
      sermon on unbaptized children was an instance. It was not so much that he thought it true as
      that it possessed
      <pb n="115"/> him for a day. It was not so much the thought as his own relation to it that
      allured him. Then, too, he loved what appeared to his parishioners to be the most unusual and
      dangerous practices. He put candles on the altar and crosses in unexpected places. He
      delighted in the intricacies of High Church costume, and was known to recommend confession and
      prayers for the dead.</p>
     <p>Gradually the anger of his parishioners would increase. The rector, the washerwoman, the
      labourers, the squire, the doctor, the school teachers, the shoemakers, the butchers, the
      seamstresses, the local journalist, the master of the hounds, the innkeeper, the veterinary
      surgeon, the magistrate, the children making mud pies, all would be filled with one
      dread—popery. Then he would fly for consolation to his little circle of the faithful, the
      younger ladies, who still repeated his fine sentiments and
      <pb n="116"/> saw him in their imaginations standing perpetually before a wall covered with
      tapestry and holding a crucifix in some constrained and ancient attitude. At last he would
      have to go, feeling for his parishioners a gay and lofty disdain, and for himself that
      reverend approbation one gives to the captains who lead the crusade of ideas against those who
      merely sleep and eat. An efficient crusader he certainly was—too efficient, indeed, for his
      efficiency gave to all his thoughts a certain over-completeness and isolation, and a kind of
      hardness to his mind. His intellect was like a musician’s instrument with no sounding-board.
      He could think carefully and cleverly, and even with originality, but never in such a way as
      to make his thoughts an allusion to something deeper than themselves. In this he was the
      reverse of poetical, for poetry is essentially a touch from behind a curtain.</p>
     <p>This conformation of his mind
      <pb n="117"/> helped to lead him into all manner of needless contests and to the loss of this
      last parish among much else. Did not the world exist for the sake of these hard, crystalline
      thoughts, with which he played as with so many bone <hi>spilikins</hi>, delighting in his own
      skill? and were not all who disliked them merely—the many?</p>
     <p>In this way it came about that Sherman’s letter reached Howard at the right moment. Now,
      next to a new parish, he loved a new friend. A visit to London meant many. He had found he
      was, on the whole, a success at the beginning of friendships.</p>
     <p>He at once wrote an acceptance in his small and beautiful handwriting, and arrived shortly
      after his letter. Sherman, on receiving him, glanced at his neat and shining boots, the little
      medal at the watch-chain and the well-brushed hat, and nodded as though in answer to an inner
      query. He smiled approval at the slight, elegant figure in its black clothes,
      <pb n="118"/> at the satiny hair, and at the face, mobile as moving waters.</p>
     <p>For several days the Shermans saw little of their guest. He had friends everywhere to turn
      into enemies and acquaintances to turn into friends. His days passed in visiting, visiting,
      visiting. Then there were theatres and churches to see, and new clothes to be bought, over
      which he was as anxious as a woman. Finally he settled down.</p>
     <p>He passed his mornings in the smoking-room. He asked Sherman’s leave to hang on the walls
      one or two religious pictures, without which he was not happy, and to place over the
      mantlepiece, under the pipe-rack, an ebony crucifix. In one corner of the room he laid a rug
      neatly folded for covering his knees on chilly days, and on the table a small collection of
      favourite books—a curious and carefully-chosen collection, in which Cardinal Newman and
      Bourget, St. Chrysostom and Flaubert,
      <pb n="119"/> lived together in perfect friendship.</p>
     <p>Early in his visit Sherman brought him to the Lelands. He was a success. The three—Margaret,
      Sherman, and Howard—played tennis in the Square. Howard was a good player, and seemed to
      admire Margaret. On the way home Sherman once or twice laughed to himself. It was like the
      clucking of a hen with a brood of chickens. He told Howard, too, how wealthy Margaret was said
      to be.</p>
     <p>After this Howard always joined Sherman and Margaret at the tennis. Sometimes, too, after a
      little, on days when the study seemed dull and lonely, and the unfinished essay on St.
      Chrysostom more than usually laborious, he would saunter towards the Square before his
      friend’s arrival, to find Margaret now alone, now with an acquaintance or two. About this time
      also press of work, an unusual thing with him, began to delay Sherman in town
      <pb n="120"/> half an hour after his usual time. In the evenings they often talked of
      Margaret—Sherman frankly and carefully, as though in all anxiety to describe her as she was;
      and Howard with some enthusiasm: “She has a religious vocation,” he said once, with a slight
      sigh.</p>
     <p>Sometimes they played chess—a game that Sherman had recently become devoted to, for he found
      it drew him out of himself more than anything else.</p>
     <p>Howard now began to notice a curious thing. Sherman grew shabbier and shabbier, and at the
      same time more and more cheerful. This puzzled him, for he had noticed that he himself was not
      cheerful when shabby, and did not even feel upright and clever when his hat was getting old.
      He also noticed that when Sherman was talking to him he seemed to be keeping some thought to
      himself. When he first came to know him long ago in Ballah he had noticed occasionally
      <pb n="121"/> the same thing, and set it down to a kind of suspiciousness and over-caution,
      natural to one who lived in such an out-of-the-way place. It seemed more persistent now,
      however. “He is not well trained,” he thought; “he is half a peasant. He has not the brilliant
      candour of the man of the world.”</p>
     <p>All this while the mind of Sherman was clucking continually over its brood of thoughts.
      Ballah was being constantly suggested to him. The grey corner of a cloud slanting its rain
      upon Cheapside called to mind by some remote suggestion the clouds rushing and falling in
      cloven surf on the seaward steep of a mountain north of Ballah. A certain street corner made
      him remember an angle of the Ballah fish-market. At night a lantern, marking where the road
      was fenced off for mending, made him think of a tinker’s cart, with its swing can of burning
      coals, that used to stop on market days at
      <pb n="122"/> the corner of Peter’s Lane at Ballah. Delayed by a crush in the Strand, he heard
      a faint trickling of water near by; it came from a shop window where a little water-jet
      balanced a wooden ball upon its point. The sound suggested a cataract with a long Gaelic name,
      that leaped crying into the Gate of the Winds at Ballah. Wandering among these memories a
      footstep went to and fro continually and the figure of Mary Carton moved among them like a
      phantom. He was set dreaming a whole day by walking down one Sunday morning to the border of
      the Thames—a few hundred yards from his house—and looking at the osier-covered Chiswick eyot.
      It made him remember an old day-dream of his. The source of the river that passed his garden
      at home was a certain wood-bordered and islanded lake, whither in childhood he had often gone
      blackberry-gathering. At the further end was a little islet
      <pb n="123"/> called Inniscrewin. Its rocky centre, covered with many bushes, rose some forty
      feet above the lake. Often when life and its difficulties had seemed to him like the lessons
      of some elder boy given to a younger by mistake, it had seemed good to dream of going away to
      that islet and building a wooden hut there and burning a few years out, rowing to and fro,
      fishing, or lying on the island slopes by day, and listening at night to the ripple of the
      water and the quivering of the bushes—full always of unknown creatures—and going out at
      morning to see the island’s edge marked by the feet of birds.</p>
     <p>These pictures became so vivid to him that the world about him—that Howard, Margaret, his
      mother even—began to seem far off. He hardly seemed aware of anything they were thinking and
      feeling. The light that dazzled him flowed from the vague and refracting regions of
      <pb n="124"/> hope and memory; the light that made Howard’s feet unsteady was ever the too
      glaring lustre of life itself.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>IV.</head>
     <p>On the evening of the 20th of June, after the blinds had been pulled down and the gas
      lighted, Sherman was playing chess in the smoking-room, right hand against left. Howard had
      gone out with a message to the Lelands. He would often say, “Is there any message I can
      deliver for you? I know how lazy you are, and will save you the trouble.” A message was always
      found for him. A pile of books lent for Sherman’s improvement went home one by one.</p>
     <p>“Look here,” said Howard’s voice in the doorway, “I have been watching you for some time.
      <pb n="126"/> You are cheating the red men most villainously. You are forcing them to make
      mistakes that the white men may win. Why, a few such games would ruin any man’s moral
      nature.”</p>
     <p>He was leaning against the doorway, looking, to Sherman’s not too critical eyes, an
      embodiment of all that was self-possessed and brilliant. The great care with which he was
      dressed and his whole manner seemed to say, “Look at me; do I not combine perfectly the zealot
      with the man of the world?” He seemed excited to-night. He had been talking at the Lelands,
      and talking well, and felt that elation which brings us many thoughts.</p>
     <p>“My dear Sherman,” he went on, “do cease that game. It is very bad for you. There is nobody
      alive who is honest enough to play a game of chess fairly out—right hand against left. We are
      so radically dishonest that we even cheat ourselves. We can no more play chess
      <pb n="127"/> than we can think altogether by ourselves with security. You had much better
      play with me.”</p>
     <p>“Very well, but you will beat me; I have not much practice,” replied the other.</p>
     <p>They reset the men and began to play. Sherman relied most upon his bishops and queen. Howard
      was fondest of the knights. At first Sherman was the attacking party, but in his
      characteristic desire to scheme out his game many moves ahead, kept making slips, and at last
      had to give up, with his men nearly all gone and his king hopelessly cornered. Howard seemed
      to let nothing escape him. When the game was finished he leant back in his chair and said, as
      he rolled a cigarette—</p>
     <p>“You do not play well.” It gave him satisfaction to feel his proficiency in many small arts.
      “You do not do any of these things at all well,” he went on, with an insolence peculiar to him
      <pb n="128"/> when excited. “You have been really very badly brought up and stupidly educated
      in that intolerable Ballah. They do not understand there any, even the least, of the arts of
      life; they only believe in information. Men who are compelled to move in the great world, and
      who are also cultivated, only value the personal acquirements—self-possession, adaptability,
      how to dress well, how even to play tennis decently—you would be not so bad at that, by the
      by, if you practised—or how to paint or write effectively. They know that it is better to
      smoke one’s cigarette with a certain charm of gesture than to have by heart all the
      encyclopedias. I say this not merely as a man of the world, but as a teacher of religion. A
      man when he rises from the grave will take with him only the things that he is in himself. He
      will leave behind the things that he merely possesses, learning and information
      <pb n="129"/> not less than money and high estate. They will stay behind with his house and
      his clothes and his body. A collection of facts will no more help him than a collection of
      stamps. The learned will not get into heaven as readily as the flute-player, or even as the
      man who smokes a cigarette gracefully. Now you are not learned, but you have been brought up
      almost as badly as if you were. In that wretched town they told you that education was to know
      that Russia is bounded on the north by the Arctic Sea, and on the west by the Baltic Ocean,
      and that Vienna is situated on the Danube, and that William the Third came to the throne in
      the year 1688. They have never taught you any personal art. Even chess-playing might have
      helped you at the day of judgment.”</p>
     <p>“I am really not a worse chess-player than you. I am only more careless.”</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="130"/> There was a slight resentment in Sherman’s voice. The other noticed it, and
      said, changing his manner from the insolent air of a young beauty to a self-depreciatory one,
      which was wont to give him at times a very genuine charm—</p>
     <p>“It is really a great pity, for you Shermans are a deep people, much deeper than we Howards.
      We are like moths or butterflies on rather rapid rivulets, while you and yours are deep pools
      in the forest where the beasts go to drink. No! I have a better metaphor. Your mind and mine
      are two arrows. Yours has got no feathers, and mine has no metal on the point. I don’t know
      which is most needed for right conduct. I wonder where we are going to strike earth. I suppose
      it will be all right some day when the world has gone by and they have collected all the
      arrows into one quiver.”</p>
     <p>He went over to the mantlepiece to hunt for a match, as
      <pb n="131"/> his cigarette had gone out. Sherman had lifted a corner of the blind and was
      gazing over the roofs shining from a recent shower, and thinking how on such a night as this
      he had sat with Mary Carton by the rectory fire listening to the rain without and talking of
      the future and of the training of village children.</p>
     <p>“Have you seen Miss Leland in her last new dress from Paris?” said Howard, making one of his
      rapid transitions. “It is very rich in colour, and makes her look a little pale, like St.
      Cecilia. She is wonderful as she stands by the piano, a silver cross round her neck. We have
      been talking about you. She complains to me. She says you are a little barbarous; you seem to
      look down on style, and sometimes—you must forgive me—even on manners, and you are quite
      without small talk. You must really try and be worthy of that beautiful girl, with her great
      soul and religious genius. She
      <pb n="132"/> told me quite sadly, too, that you are not improving.”</p>
     <p>“No,” said Sherman, “I am not going forward; I am at present trying to go sideways like the
      crabs.”</p>
     <p>“Be serious,” answered the other. “She told me these things with the most sad and touching
      voice. She makes me her confidant, you know, in many matters, because of my wide religious
      experience. You must really improve yourself. You must paint or something.”</p>
     <p>“Well, I will paint or something.”</p>
     <p>“I am quite serious, Sherman. Try and be worthy of her, a soul as gentle as St.
      Cecilia’s.”</p>
     <p>“She is very wealthy,” said Sherman. “If she were engaged to you and not to me you might
      hope to die a bishop.”</p>
     <p>Howard looked at him in a mystified way and the conversation dropped. Presently Howard got
      up and went to his room, and Sherman, resetting
      <pb n="133"/> the chess-board, began to play again, and, letting longer and longer pauses of
      reverie come between his moves, played far into the morning, cheating now in favour of the red
      men now in favour of the white.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>V.</head>
     <p>The next afternoon Howard found Miss Leland sitting, reading in an alcove in her
      drawing-room, between a stuffed paroquet and a blue De Morgan jar. As he was shown in he
      noticed, with a momentary shock, that her features were quite commonplace. Then she saw him,
      and at once seemed to vanish wrapped in an exulting flame of life. She stood up, flinging the
      book on to the seat with some violence.</p>
     <p>“I have been reading that sweet ‘Imitation of Christ,’ and was just feeling that I should
      have to become a theosophist or a socialist, or go and join the
      <pb n="135"/> Catholic Church, or do something. How delightful it is to see you again! How is
      my savage getting on? It is so good of you to try and help me to reform him.”</p>
     <p>They talked on about Sherman, and Howard did his best to console her for his shortcomings.
      Time would certainly improve her savage. Several times she gazed at him with those large dark
      eyes of hers, of which the pupils to-day seemed larger than usual. They made him feel dizzy
      and clutch tightly the arm of his chair. Then she began to talk about her life since
      childhood—how they got to the subject he never knew—and made a number of those confidences
      which are so dangerous because so flattering. To love—there is nothing else worth living for;
      but then men are so shallow. She had never found a nature deep as her own. She would not
      pretend that she had not often been in love, but never had any heart rung back to her the true
      note. As she
      <pb n="136"/> spoke her face quivered with excitement. The exulting flame of life seemed
      spreading from her to the other things in the room. To Howard’s eyes it seemed as though the
      bright pots and stuffed birds and plush curtains began to glow with a light not of this
      world—to glimmer like the strange and chaotic colours the mystic Blake imagined upon the
      scaled serpent of Eden. The light seemed gradually to dim his past and future, and to make
      pale his good resolves. Was it not in itself that which all men are seeking, and for which all
      else exists?</p>
     <p>He leant forward and took her hand, timidly and doubtingly. She did not draw it away. He
      leant nearer and kissed her on the forehead. She gave a joyful cry, and, casting her arms
      round his neck, burst out, “Ah! you—and I. We were made for each other. I hate Sherman. He is
      an egotist. He is a beast. He is selfish and foolish.” Releasing
      <pb n="137"/> one of her arms she struck the seat with her hand, excitedly, and went on, “How
      angry he will be! But it serves him right! How badly he is dressing. He does not know anything
      about anything. But you—you—I knew you were meant for me the moment I saw you.”</p>
     <p>That evening Howard flung himself into a chair in the empty smoking-room. He lighted a
      cigarette; it went out. Again he lighted it; again it went out. “I am a traitor—and that good,
      stupid fellow, Sherman, never to be jealous!” he thought. “But then, how could I help it? And,
      besides, it cannot be a bad action to save her from a man she is so much above in refinement
      and feeling.” He was getting into good-humour with himself. He got up and went over and looked
      at the photograph of Raphael’s Madonna, which he had hung over the mantlepiece. “How like
      Margaret’s are her big eyes!”</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>VI.</head>
     <p>The next day when Sherman came home from his office he saw an envelope lying on the
      smoking-room table. It contained a letter from Howard, saying that he had gone away, and that
      he hoped Sherman would forgive his treachery, but that he was hopelessly in love with Miss
      Leland, and that she returned his love.</p>
     <p>Sherman went downstairs. His mother was helping the servant to set the table.</p>
     <p>“You will never guess what has happened,” he said. “My affair with Margaret is over.”</p>
     <p>“I cannot pretend to be sorry, John,” she replied. She had
      <pb n="139"/> long considered Miss Leland among accepted things, like the chimney-pots on the
      roof, and submitted, as we do, to any unalterable fact, but had never praised her or expressed
      liking in any way. “She puts belladonna in her eyes, and is a vixen and a flirt, and I dare
      say her wealth is all talk. But how did it happen?”</p>
     <p>Her son was, however, too excited to listen.</p>
     <p>He went upstairs and wrote the following note—</p>
     <quote>
      <p>“<hi>My dear Margaret</hi>:</p>
      <p>“I congratulate you on a new conquest. There is no end to your victories. As for me, I bow
       myself out with many sincere wishes for your happiness, and remain,</p>
      <p>“Your friend,</p>
      <p>“<hi>John Sherman</hi>.”</p>
     </quote>
     <p>Having posted this letter he sat down with Howard’s note spread out before him, and wondered
      <pb n="140"/> whether there was anything mean and small-minded in neatness—he himself was
      somewhat untidy. He had often thought so before, for their strong friendship was founded in a
      great measure on mutual contempt, but now immediately added, being in good-humour with the
      world, “He is much cleverer than I am. He must have been very industrious at school.”</p>
     <p>A week went by. He made up his mind to put an end to his London life. He broke to his mother
      his resolve to return to Ballah. She was delighted, and at once began to pack. Her old home
      had long seemed to her a kind of lost Eden, wherewith she was accustomed to contrast the
      present. When, in time, this present had grown into the past it became an Eden in turn. She
      was always ready for a change, if the change came to her in the form of a return to something
      old. Others place their ideals in the future; she laid hers in the past.</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="141"/> The only one this momentous resolution seemed to surprise was the old and deaf
      servant. She waited with ever-growing impatience. She would sit by the hour wool-gathering on
      the corner of a chair with a look of bewildered delight. As the hour of departure came near
      she sang continually in a cracked voice.</p>
     <p>Sherman, a few days before leaving, was returning for the last time from his office when he
      saw, to his surprise, Howard and Miss Leland carrying each a brown paper bundle. He nodded
      good-humouredly, meaning to pass on.</p>
     <p>“John,” she said, “look at this brooch William gave me—a ladder leaning against the moon and
      a butterfly climbing up it. Is it not sweet? We are going to visit the poor.”</p>
     <p>“And I,” he said, “am going to catch eels. I am leaving town.”</p>
     <p>He made his excuses, saying he had no time to wait, and
      <pb n="142"/> hurried off. She looked after him with a mournful glance, strange in anybody who
      had exchanged one lover for another more favoured.</p>
     <p>“Poor fellow,” murmured Howard, “he is broken-hearted.”</p>
     <p>“Nonsense,” answered Miss Leland, somewhat snappishly.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div type="group">
    <head> PART V. JOHN SHERMAN RETURNS TO BALLAH.</head>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head> I.</head>
     <p>This being the homeward trip, SS. <hi>Lavinia</hi> carried no cattle, but many passengers.
      As the sea was smooth and the voyage near its end, they lounged about the deck in groups. Two
      cattle merchants were leaning over the taffrail smoking. In appearance they were something
      between betting men and commercial travellers. For years they had done all their sleeping in
      steamers and trains. A short distance from them a clerk from Liverpool, with a consumptive
      cough, walked to and fro, a little child holding his hand. Shortly he would be landed in a
      boat putting off from
      <pb n="146"/> the shore for the purpose. He had come hoping that his native air of Teeling
      Head would restore him. The little child was a strange contrast—her cheeks ruddy with perfect
      health. Further forward, talking to one of the crew, was a man with a red face and slightly
      unsteady step. In the companion house was a governess, past her first youth, very much afraid
      of seasickness. She had brought her luggage up and heaped it round her to be ready for
      landing. Sherman sat on a pile of cable looking out over the sea. It was just noon; SS.
       <hi>Lavinia</hi>, having passed by Tory and Rathlin, was approaching the Donegal cliffs. They
      were covered by a faint mist, which made them loom even vaster than they were. To westward the
      sun shone on a perfectly blue sea. Seagulls come out of the mist and plunged into the
      sunlight, and out of the sunlight and plunged into the mist. To the westward
      <pb n="147"/> gannets were striking continually, and a porpoise showed now and then, his fin
      and back gleaming in the sun. Sherman was more perfectly happy than he had been for many a
      day, and more ardently thinking. All nature seemed full of a Divine fulfilment. Everything
      fulfilled its law—fulfilment that is peace, whether it be for good or for evil, for evil also
      has its peace, the peace of the birds of prey. Sherman looked from the sea to the ship and
      grew sad. Upon this thing, crawling slowly along the sea, moved to and fro many mournful and
      slouching figures. He looked from the ship to himself and his eyes filled with tears. On
      himself, on these moving figures, hope and memory fed like flames.</p>
     <p>Again his eyes gladdened, for he knew he had found his present. He would live in his love
      and the day as it passed. He would live that his law might be fulfilled. Now, was he sure of
      this truth?—the
      <pb n="148"/> saints on the one hand, the animals on the other, live in the moment as it
      passes. Thitherward had his days brought him. This was the one grain they had ground. To grind
      one grain is sufficient for a lifetime.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>II.</head>
     <p>A few days later Sherman was hurrying through the town of Ballah. It was Saturday, and he
      passed down through the marketing country people, and the old women with baskets of cakes and
      gooseberries and long pieces of sugarstick shaped like walking-sticks, and called by children
      “Peggie’s leg.”</p>
     <p>Now, as two months earlier he was occasionally recognized and greeted, and, as before, went
      on without knowing, his eyes full of unintelligent sadness because the mind was making merry
      afar. They had the look we see in the eyes of animals and dreamers.
      <pb n="150"/> Everything had grown simple, his problem had taken itself away. He was thinking
      what he would say to Mary Carton. Now they would be married, they would live in a small house
      with a green door and new thatch, and a row of beehives under a hedge. He knew where just such
      a house stood empty. The day before he and his mother had discussed, with their host of the
      Imperial Hotel, this question of houses. They knew the peculiarities of every house in the
      neighbourhood, except two or three built while they were away. All day Sherman and his mother
      had gone over the merits of the few they were told were empty. She wondered why her son had
      grown so unpractical. Once he was so easily pleased—the row of beehives and the new thatch did
      not for her settle the question. She set it all down to Miss Leland and the plays, and the
      singing, and the belladonna, and remembered with pleasure how
      <pb n="151"/> many miles of uneasy water lay between the town of Ballah and these things.</p>
     <p>She did not know what else beside the row of beehives and the new thatch her son’s mind ran
      on as he walked among the marketing country people, and the gooseberry sellers, and the
      merchants of “Peggie’s leg,” and the boys playing marbles in odd corners, and the men in
      waistcoats with flannel sleeves driving carts, and the women driving donkeys with creels of
      turf or churns of milk. Just now she was trying to remember whether she used to buy her wool
      for knitting at Miss Peters’s or from Mrs. Macallough’s at the bridge. One or other sold it a
      halfpenny a skein cheaper. She never knew what went on inside her son’s mind, she had always
      her own fish to fry. Blessed are the unsympathetic. They preserve their characters in an iron
      safe while the most of us poor mortals are going about the
      <pb n="152"/> planet vainly searching for any kind of a shell to contain us, and evaporating
      the while.</p>
     <p>Sherman began to mount the hill to the vicarage. He was happy. Because he was happy he began
      to run. Soon the steepness of the hill made him walk. He thought about his love for Mary
      Carton. Seen by the light of this love everything that had happened to him was plain now. He
      had found his centre of unity. His childhood had prepared him for this love. He had been
      solitary, fond of favourite corners of fields, fond of going about alone, unhuman like the
      birds and the leaves, his heart empty. How clearly he remembered his first meeting with Mary.
      They were both children. At a school treat they watched the fire balloon ascend, and followed
      it a little way over the fields together. What friends they became, growing up together,
      reading the same books, thinking the same thoughts.</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="153"/> As he came to the door and pulled at the great hanging iron bell handle, the
      fire balloon reascended in his heart, surrounded with cheers and laughter.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>III.</head>
     <p>He kept the servant talking for a moment or two before she went for Miss Carton. The old
      rector, she told him, was getting less and less able to do much work. Old age had come almost
      suddenly upon him. He seldom moved from the fireside. He was getting more and more
      absent-minded. Once lately he had brought his umbrella into the reading-desk. More and more
      did he leave all things to his children—to Mary Carton and her younger sisters.</p>
     <p>When the servant had gone Sherman looked round the somewhat gloomy room. In the window hung
      a canary in a
      <pb n="155"/> painted cage. Outside was a narrow piece of shaded ground between the window and
      the rectory wall. The laurel and holly bushes darkened the window a good deal. On a table in
      the centre of the room were evangelistic books with gilded covers. Round the mirror over the
      mantlepiece were stuck various parish announcements, thrust between the glass and the gilding.
      On a small side table was a copper ear-trumpet.</p>
     <p>How familiar everything seemed to Sherman. Only the room seemed smaller than it did three
      years before, and close to the table with the ear-trumpet, at one side of the fireplace before
      the arm-chair, was a new threadbare patch in the carpet.</p>
     <p>Sherman recalled how in this room he and Mary Carton had sat in winter by the fire, building
      castles in the air for each other. So deeply meditating was he that she came in and stood
      unnoticed beside him.</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="156"/> “John,” she said at last, “it is a great pleasure to see you so soon again. Are
      you doing well in London?”</p>
     <p>“I have left London.”</p>
     <p>“Are you married, then? You must introduce me to your wife.”</p>
     <p>“I shall never be married to Miss Leland.”</p>
     <p>“What?”</p>
     <p>“She has preferred another—my friend William Howard. I have come here to tell you something,
      Mary.” He went and stood close to her and took her hand tenderly. “I have always been very
      fond of you. Often in London, when I was trying to think of another kind of life, I used to
      see this fireside and you sitting beside it, where we used to sit and talk about the future.
      Mary—Mary,” he held her hand in both his—“you will be my wife?”</p>
     <p>“You do not love me, John,” she answered, drawing herself away. “You have come to me because
      you think it your duty.
      <pb n="157"/> I have had nothing but duty all my life.”</p>
     <p>“Listen,” he said. “I was very miserable; I invited Howard to stay with us. One morning I
      found a note on the smoking-room table to say that Margaret had accepted him, and I have come
      here to ask you to marry me. I never cared for any one else.”</p>
     <p>He found himself speaking hurriedly, as though anxious to get the words said and done with.
      It now seemed to him that he had done ill in this matter of Miss Leland. He had not before
      thought of it—his mind had always been busy with other things. Mary Carton looked at him
      wonderingly.</p>
     <p>“John,” she said at last, “did you ask Mr. Howard to stay with you on purpose to get him to
      fall in love with Miss Leland, or to give you an excuse for breaking off your engagement, as
      you knew he flirted with every one?”</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="158"/> “Margaret seems very fond of him. I think they are made for each other,” he
      answered.</p>
     <p>“Did you ask him to London on purpose?”</p>
     <p>“Well, I will tell you,” he faltered. “I was very miserable. I had drifted into this
      engagement I don’t know how. Margaret glitters and glitters and glitters, but she is not of my
      kind. I suppose I thought, like a fool, I should marry some one who was rich. I found out soon
      that I loved nobody but you. I got to be always thinking of you and of this town. Then I heard
      that Howard had lost his curacy, and asked him up. I just left them alone and did not go near
      Margaret much. I knew they were made for each other. Do not let us talk of them,” he
      continued, eagerly. “Let us talk about the future. I will take a farm and turn farmer. I dare
      say my uncle will not give me anything when he dies because I have left his office. He will
      call
      <pb n="159"/> me a ne’er-do-weel, and say I would squander it. But you and I—we will get
      married, will we not? We will be very happy,” he went on, pleadingly. “You will still have
      your charities, and I shall be busy with my farm. We will surround ourselves with a wall. The
      world will be on the outside, and on the inside we and our peaceful lives.”</p>
     <p>“Wait,” she said; “I will give you your answer,” and going into the next room returned with
      several bundles of letters. She laid them on the table; some were white and new, some slightly
      yellow with time.</p>
     <p>“John,” she said, growing very pale, “here are all the letters you ever wrote me from your
      earliest boyhood.” She took one of the large candles from the mantlepiece, and, lighting it,
      placed it on the hearth. Sherman wondered what she was going to do with it. “I will tell you,”
      she went on, “what I had thought to carry to the
      <pb n="160"/> grave unspoken. I have loved you for a long time. When you came and told me you
      were going to be married to another I forgave you, for man’s love is like the wind, and I
      prayed that God might bless you both.” She leant down over the candle, her face pale and
      contorted with emotion. “All these letters after that grew very sacred. Since we were never to
      be married they grew a portion of my life, separated from everything and every one—a something
      apart and holy. I re-read them all, and arranged them in little bundles according to their
      dates, and tied them with thread. Now I and you—we have nothing to do with each other any
      more.”</p>
     <p>She held the bundle of letters in the flame. He got up from his seat. She motioned him away
      imperiously. He looked at the flame in a bewildered way. The letters fell in little burning
      fragments about the hearth. It was all like a terrible dream. He
      <pb n="161"/> watched those steady fingers hold letter after letter in the candle flame, and
      watched the candle burning on like a passion in the grey daylight of universal existence. A
      draught from under the door began blowing the ash about the room. The voice said—</p>
     <p>“You tried to marry a rich girl. You did not love her, but knew she was rich. You tired of
      her as you tire of so many things, and behaved to her most wrongly, most wickedly and
      treacherously. When you were jilted you came again to me and to the idleness of this little
      town. We had all hoped great things of you. You seemed good and honest.”</p>
     <p>“I loved you all along,” he cried. “If you would marry me we would be very happy. I loved
      you all along,” he repeated—this helplessly, several times over. The bird shook a shower of
      seed on his shoulder. He picked one of them from the collar of his coat and turned it over in
      his
      <pb n="162"/> fingers mechanically. “I loved you all along.”</p>
     <p>“You have done no duty that came to you. You have tired of everything you should cling to;
      and now you have come to this little town because here is idleness and irresponsibility.”</p>
     <p>The last letter lay in ashes on the hearth. She blew out the candle, and replaced it among
      the photographs on the mantlepiece, and stood there as calm as a portion of the marble.</p>
     <p>“John, our friendship is over—it has been burnt in the candle.”</p>
     <p>He started forward, his mind full of appeals half-stifled with despair, on his lips gathered
      incoherent words: “She will be happy with Howard. They were made for each other. I slipped
      into it. I always thought I should marry some one who was rich. I never loved any one but you.
      I did not know I loved you at first. I thought about you always. You are the root of my
      life.”</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="163"/> Steps were heard outside the door at the end of a passage. Mary Carton went to
      the door and called. The steps turned and came nearer. With a great effort Sherman controlled
      himself. The door opened, and a tall, slight girl of twelve came into the room. A strong smell
      of garden mould rose from a basket in her hands. Sherman recognized the child who had given
      him tea that evening in the schoolhouse three years before.</p>
     <p>“Have you finished weeding the carrots?” said Mary Carton.</p>
     <p>“Yes, Miss.”</p>
     <p>“Then you are to weed the small bed under the pear-tree by the tool-house. Do not go yet,
      child. This is Mr. Sherman. Sit down a little.”</p>
     <p>The child sat down on the corner of a chair with a scared look in her eyes. Suddenly she
      said—</p>
     <p>“Oh, what a lot of burnt paper!”</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="164"/> “Yes; I have been burning some old letters.”</p>
     <p>“I think,” said John, “I will go now.” Without a word of farewell he went out, almost
      groping his way.</p>
     <p>He had lost the best of all the things he held dear. Twice he had gone through the fire. The
      first time worldly ambition left him, on the second love. An hour before the air had been full
      of singing and peace that was resonant like joy. Now he saw standing before his Eden the angel
      with the flaming sword. All the hope he had ever gathered about him had taken itself off, and
      the naked soul shivered.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>IV.</head>
     <p>The road under his feet felt gritty and barren. He hurried away from the town. It was late
      afternoon. Trees cast bands of shadow across the road. He walked rapidly as if pursued. About
      a mile to the south of the town he came on a large wood bordering the road and surrounding a
      deserted house. Some local rich man once lived there, now it was given over to a caretaker who
      lived in two rooms in the back part. Men were at work cutting down trees in two or three parts
      of the wood. Many places were quite bare. A mass of ruins—a covered well, and the wreckage of
      castle wall—that
      <pb n="166"/> that had been roofed with green for centuries lifted themselves up, bare as
      anatomies. The sight intensified, by some strange sympathy, his sorrow, and he hurried away as
      from a thing accursed of God.</p>
     <p>The road led to the foot of a mountain, topped by a cairn supposed in popular belief to be
      the grave of Maeve, Mab of the fairies, and considered by antiquarians to mark the place where
      certain prisoners were executed in legendary times as sacrifices to the moon.</p>
     <p>He began to climb the mountain. The sun was on the rim of the sea. It stayed there without
      moving, for as he ascended he saw an ever-widening circle of water.</p>
     <p>He threw himself down upon the cairn. The sun sank under the sea. The Donegal headlands
      mixed with the surrounding blue. The stars grew out of heaven.</p>
     <p>Sometimes he got up and walked to and fro. Hours passed.
      <pb n="167"/> The stars, the streams down in the valley, the wind moving among the boulders,
      the various unknown creatures rustling in the silence—all these were contained within
      themselves, fulfilling their law, content to be alone, content to be with others, having the
      peace of God or the peace of the birds of prey. He only did not fulfil his law; something that
      was not he, that was not nature, that was not God, had made him and her he loved its tools.
      Hope, memory, tradition, conformity, had been laying waste their lives. As he thought this the
      night seemed to crush him with its purple foot. Hour followed hour. At midnight he started up,
      hearing a faint murmur of clocks striking the hour in the distant town. His face and hands
      were wet with tears, his clothes saturated with dew.</p>
     <p>He turned homeward, hurriedly flying from the terrible firmament. What had this glimmering
      and silence to do with him—this luxurious
      <pb n="168"/> present? He belonged to the past and the future. With pace somewhat slackened,
      because of the furze, he came down into the valley. Along the northern horizon moved a
      perpetual dawn, travelling eastward as the night advanced. Once, as he passed a marsh near a
      lime-kiln, a number of small birds rose chirruping from where they had been clinging among the
      reeds. Once, standing still for a moment where two roads crossed on a hill-side, he looked out
      over the dark fields. A white stone rose in the middle of a field, a score of yards in front
      of him. He knew the place well; it was an ancient burying-ground. He looked at the stone, and
      suddenly filled by that terror of the darkness children feel, began again his hurried
      walk.</p>
     <p>He re-entered Ballah by the southern side. In passing he looked at the rectory. To his
      surprise a light burned in the drawing-room. He stood still. The dawn was brightening towards
      <pb n="169"/> the east, but all round him was darkness, seeming the more intense to his eyes
      for their being fresh from the unshaded fields. In the midst of this darkness shone the
      lighted window. He went over to the gate and looked in. The room was empty. He was about to
      turn away when he noticed a white figure standing close to the gate. The latch creaked and the
      gate moved slowly on its hinges.</p>
     <p>“John,” said a trembling voice, “I have been praying, and a light has come to me. I wished
      you to be ambitious—to go away and do something in the world. You did badly, and my poor pride
      was wounded. You do not know how much I had hoped from you; but it was all pride—all pride and
      foolishness. You love me. I ask no more. We need each other; the rest is with God.”</p>
     <p>She took his hand in hers, and began caressing it. “We have been shipwrecked. Our goods have
      been cast into the sea.”
      <pb n="170"/> Something in her voice told of the emotion that divides the love of woman from
      the love of man. She looked upon him whom she loved as full of a helplessness that needed
      protection, a reverberation of the feeling of the mother for the child at the breast.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div type="group">
    <head> DHOYA.</head>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head> I.</head>
     <p>Long ago, before the earliest stone of the pyramids was laid, before the Bo tree of Buddha
      unrolled its first leaf, before a Japanese had painted on a temple wall the horse that every
      evening descended and trampled the rice-fields, before the ravens of Thor had eaten their
      first worm together, there lived a man of giant stature and of giant strength named Dhoya. One
      evening Fomorian galleys had entered the Bay of the Red Cataract, now the Bay of Ballah, and
      there deserted him. Though he rushed into the water and hurled great stones after them
      <pb n="174"/> they were out of reach. From earliest childhood the Fomorians had held him
      captive and compelled him to toil at the oar, but when his strength had come his fits of
      passion made him a terror to all on board. Sometimes he would tear the seats of the galley
      from their places, at others drive the rowers to some corner where, trembling, they would
      watch him pacing to and fro till the passion left him. “The demons,” they said, “have made him
      their own.” So they enticed him on shore, he having on his head a mighty stone pitcher to fill
      with water, and deserted him.</p>
     <p>When the last sail had dropped over the rim of the world he rose from where he had flung
      himself down on the sands and paced through the forests eastward. After a time he reached that
      lake among the mountains where in later times Dermot drove down four stakes and made thereon a
      platform with four flags in the centre for a hearth,
      <pb n="175"/> and placed over all a roof of wicker and skins, and hid his Grania, islanded
      thereon. Still eastward he went, what is now Bulban on one side, Cope’s mountain on the other,
      until at last he threw himself at full length in a deep cavern and slept. Henceforward he made
      this cavern his lair, issuing forth to hunt the deer or the bears or the mountain oxen. Slowly
      the years went by, his fits of fury growing more and more frequent, though there was no one
      but his own shadow to rave against. When his fury was on him even the bats and owls, and the
      brown toads that crept out of the grass at twilight would hide themselves—even the bats and
      owls and the brown toads. These he had made his friends, and let them crawl and perch about
      him, for at times he would be very gentle, and they too were sullen and silent—the outcasts
      from they knew not what. But most of all, things placid and
      <pb n="176"/> beautiful feared him. He would watch for hours, hidden in the leaves, to reach
      his hand out slowly and carefully at last, and seize and crush some glittering halcyon.</p>
     <p>Slowly the years went by and human face he never saw, but sometimes, when the gentle mood
      was on him and it was twilight, a presence seemed to float invisibly by him and sigh softly,
      and once or twice he awoke from sleep with the sensation of a finger having rested for a
      moment on his forehead, and would mutter a prayer to the moon before turning to sleep
      again—the moon that glimmered through the door of his cave. “O moon,” he would say, “that
      wandereth in the blue cave, more white than the beard of Partholan, whose years were five
      hundred, sullen and solitary, sleeping only on the floor of the sea: keep me from the evil
      spirits of the islands of the lake southward beyond the mountains,
      <pb n="177"/> and the evil spirits of the caves northward beyond the mountains, and the evil
      spirits who wave their torches by the mouth of the river eastward beyond the valley, and the
      evil spirits of the pools westward beyond the mountains, and I will offer you a bear and a
      deer in full horn, O solitary of the cave divine, and if any have done you wrong I will avenge
      you.”</p>
     <p>Gradually, however, he began to long for this mysterious touch.</p>
     <p>At times he would make journeys into distant parts, and once the mountain oxen gathered
      together, proud of their overwhelming numbers and their white horns, and followed him with
      great bellowing westward, he being laden with their tallest, well-nigh to his cave, and would
      have gored him, but, pacing into a pool of the sea to his shoulders, he saw them thunder away,
      losing him in the darkness. The place where he stood is called Pooldhoya to this day.</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="178"/> So the years went slowly by, and ever deeper and deeper came his moodiness, and
      more often his fits of wrath. Once in his gloom he paced the forests for miles, now this way
      now that, until, returning in the twilight, he found himself standing on a cliff southward of
      the lake that was southward of the mountains. The moon was rising. The sound of the swaying of
      reeds floated from beneath, and the twittering of the flocks of reed-wrens who love to cling
      on the moving stems. It was the hour of votaries. He turned to the moon, then hurriedly
      gathered a pile of leaves and branches, and making a fire cast thereon wild strawberries and
      the fruit of the quicken tree. As the smoke floated upwards a bar of faint purple clouds
      drifted over the moon’s face—a refusal of the sacrifice. Hurrying through the surrounding
      woods he found an owl sleeping in the hollow of a tree, and returning cast him
      <pb n="179"/> on the fire. Still the clouds gathered. Again he searched the woods. This time a
      badger was uselessly cast among the flames. Time after time he came and went, sometimes
      returning immediately with some live thing, at others not till the fire had almost burnt
      itself out. Deer, wild swine, birds, all to no purpose. Higher and higher he piled the burning
      branches, the flames and the smoke waved and circled like the lash of a giant’s whip.
      Gradually the nearer islands passed the rosy colour on to their more distant brethren. The
      reed-wrens of the furthest reed beds disturbed amid their sleep must have wondered at the red
      gleam reflected in each other’s eyes. Useless his night-long toil; the clouds covered the
      moon’s face more and more, until, when the long fire lash was at its brightest, they drowned
      her completely in a surge of unbroken mist. Raging against the fire he scattered with his
      staff the burning
      <pb n="180"/> branches, and trampled in his fury the sacrificial embers beneath his feet.
      Suddenly a voice in the surrounding darkness called him softly by name. He turned. For years
      no articulate voice had sounded in his ears. It seemed to rise from the air just beneath the
      verge of the precipice. Holding by a hazel bush he leaned out, and for a moment it seemed to
      him the form of a beautiful woman floated faintly before him, but changed as he watched to a
      little cloud of vapour; and from the nearest of the haunted islands there came assuredly a
      whiff of music. Then behind him in the forest said the voice, “Dhoya, my beloved.” He rushed
      in pursuit; something white was moving before him. He stretched out his hand; it was only a
      mass of white campion trembling in the morning breeze, for an ashen morning was just touching
      the mists on the eastern mountains. Beginning suddenly to tremble with supernatural
      <pb n="181"/> fear Dhoya paced homewards. Everything was changed; dark shadows seemed to come
      and go, and elfin chatter to pass upon the breeze. But when he reached the shelter of the pine
      woods all was still as of old. He slackened his speed. Those solemn pine-trees soothed him
      with their vast unsociability—many and yet each one alone. Once or twice, when in some glade
      further than usual from its kind arose some pine-tree larger than the rest, he paused with
      bowed head to mutter an uncouth prayer to that dark outlaw. But when issuing once more, as he
      neared his cave, into the region of mountain ash and hazel the voices seemed again to come and
      go, and the shadows to circle round him, and once a voice said, he imagined, in accents faint
      and soft as falling dew, “Dhoya, my beloved.” But a few yards from the cave all grew suddenly
      silent.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head>II.</head>
     <p>Slower and slower he went, with his eyes on the ground, bewildered by all that was
      happening. A few feet from the cave he stood still, counting aimlessly the round spots of
      light made by the beams slanting through trees that hid with their greenness, as in the centre
      of the sea, that hollow rock. As over and over he counted them, he heard, first with the ear
      only, then with the mind also, a footstep going to and fro within the cave. Lifting his eyes
      he saw the same figure seen on the cliff—the figure of a woman, beautiful and young. Her dress
      was white, save for a border of
      <pb n="183"/> feathers dyed the fatal red of the spirits. She had arranged in one corner the
      spears, and in the other the brushwood and branches used for the fire, and spread upon the
      ground the skins, and now began pulling vainly at the great stone pitcher of the
      Fomorians.</p>
     <p>Suddenly she saw him, and with a burst of wild laughter flung her arms around his neck,
      crying, “Dhoya, I have left my world far off. My people—on the floor of the lake they are
      dancing and singing, and on the islands of the lake; always happy, always young, always
      without change. I have left them for thee, Dhoya, for they cannot love. Only the changing, and
      moody, and angry, and weary can love. I am beautiful; love me, Dhoya. Do you hear me? I left
      the places where they dance, Dhoya, for thee!” For long she poured out a tide of words, he
      answering at first little, then more and more as she
      <pb n="184"/> melted away the silence of so many inarticulate years; and all the while she
      gazed on him with eyes, no ardour could rob of the mild and mysterious melancholy that watches
      us from the eyes of animals—sign of unhuman reveries.</p>
     <p>Many days passed over these strangely wedded ones. Sometimes when he asked her, “Do you love
      me?” she would answer, “I do not know, but I long for your love endlessly.” Often at twilight,
      returning from hunting, he would find her bending over a stream that flowed near to the cave,
      decking her hair with feathers and reddening her lips with the juice of a wild berry.</p>
     <p>He was very happy secluded in that deep forest. Hearing the faint murmurs of the western
      sea, they seemed to have outlived change. But Change is everywhere, with the tides and the
      stars fastened to her wheel. Every blood drop in their lips, every cloud in the sky, every
      leaf in
      <pb n="185"/> the world changed a little, while they brushed back their hair and kissed. All
      things change save only the fear of change. And yet for his hour Dhoya was happy and as full
      of dreams as an old man or an infant—for dreams wander nearest to the grave and the
      cradle.</p>
     <p>Once, as he was returning home from hunting, by the northern edge of the lake, at the hour
      when the owls cry to each other, “It is time to be abroad,” and the last flutter of the wind
      has died away, leaving under every haunted island an image legible to the least hazel branch,
      there suddenly stood before him a slight figure, at the edge of the narrow sand-line, dark
      against the glowing water. Dhoya drew nearer. It was a man leaning on his spear-staff, on his
      head a small red cap. His spear was slender and tipped with shining metal; the spear of Dhoya
      of wood, one end pointed and hardened in the fire. The red-capped
      <pb n="186"/> stranger silently raised that slender spear and thrust at Dhoya, who parried
      with his pointed staff.</p>
     <p>For a long while they fought. The last vestige of sunset passed away and the stars came out.
      Underneath them the feet of Dhoya beat up the ground, but the feet of the other as he rushed
      hither and thither, matching his agility with the mortal’s mighty strength, made neither
      shadow nor footstep on the sands. Dhoya was wounded, and growing weary a little, when the
      other leaped away, and, crouching down by the water, began—“You have carried away by some
      spell unknown the most beautiful of our bands—you who have neither laughter nor singing.
      Restore her, Dhoya, and go free.” Dhoya answered him no word, and the other rose and again
      thrust at him with the spear. They fought to and fro upon the sands until the dawn touched
      with olive the distant sky, and then his anger
      <pb n="187"/> fit, long absent, fell on Dhoya, and he closed with his enemy and threw him, and
      put his knee on his chest and his hands on his throat, and would have crushed all life out of
      him, when lo! he held beneath his knee no more than a bundle of reeds.</p>
     <p>Nearing home in the early morning he heard the voice he loved, singing—</p>
     <quote>
      <l>“Full moody is my love and sad,</l>
      <l>His moods bow low his sombre crest,</l>
      <l>I hold him dearer than the glad,</l>
      <l>And he shall slumber on my breast.</l>
      <l>“My love hath many an evil mood</l>
      <l>Ill words for all things soft and fair,</l>
      <l>I hold him dearer than the good,</l>
      <l>My fingers feel his amber hair.</l>
      <l>“No tender wisdom floods the eyes</l>
      <l>That watch me with their suppliant light—</l>
      <l>I hold him dearer than the wise,</l>
      <l>And for him make me wise and bright.”</l>
     </quote>
     <p>And when she saw him she cried, “An old mortal song heard floating from a tent of skin, as
      <pb n="188"/> we rode, I and mine, through a camping-place at night.” From that day she was
      always either singing wild and melancholy songs or else watching him with that gaze of animal
      reverie.</p>
     <p>Once he asked, “How old are you?”</p>
     <p>“A thousand years, for I am young.”</p>
     <p>“I am so little to you,” he went on, “and you are so much to me—dawn, and sunset,
      tranquility, and speech, and solitude.”</p>
     <p>“Am I so much?” she said; “say it many times!” and her eyes seemed to brighten and her
      breast heaved with joy.</p>
     <p>Often he would bring her the beautiful skins of animals, and she would walk to and fro on
      them, laughing to feel their softness under her feet. Sometimes she would pause and ask
      suddenly, “Will you weep for me when we have parted?” and he would answer, “I will die then;”
      and she would go on rubbing her feet to and fro in the soft skin.</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="189"/> And so Dhoya grew tranquil and gentle, and Change seemed still to have forgotten
      them, having so much on her hands. The stars rose and set watching them smiling together, and
      the tides ebbed and flowed, bringing mutability to all save them. But always everything
      changes, save only the fear of Change.</p>
    </div>
    <div type="chapter">
     <head> III.</head>
     <p>One evening as they sat in the inner portion of the cave, watching through the opening the
      paling of the sky and the darkening of the leaves, and counting the budding stars, Dhoya
      suddenly saw stand before him the dark outline of him he fought on the lake sand, and heard at
      the same instant his companion sigh.</p>
     <p>The stranger approached a little, and said, “Dhoya we have fought heretofore, and now I have
      come to play chess against thee, for well thou knowest, dear to the perfect warrior after war
      is chess.”</p>
     <p>“I know it,” answered Dhoya.</p>
     <p>
      <pb n="191"/> “And when we have played, Dhoya, we will name the stake.”</p>
     <p>“Do not play,” whispered his companion at his side.</p>
     <p>But Dhoya, being filled with his anger fit at the sight of his enemy, answered, “I will
      play, and I know well the stake you mean, and I name this for mine, that I may again have my
      knee on your chest and my hands on your throat, and that you will not again change into a
      bundle of wet reeds.” His companion lay down on a skin and began to cry a little.</p>
     <p>Dhoya felt sure of winning. He had often played in his boyhood, before the time of his anger
      fits, with his masters of the galley; and besides, he could always return to his hands and his
      weapons once more.</p>
     <p>Now the floor of the cave was of smooth, white sand, brought from the sea-shore in his great
      Fomorian pitcher, to make it soft for his beloved to walk upon; before it had been, as it now
      is,
      <pb n="192"/> of rough clay. On this sand the red-capped stranger marked out with his
      spear-point a chess-board, and marked with rushes, crossed and recrossed each alternate
      square, fixing each end of the rush in the sand, until a complete board was finished of white
      and green squares, and then drew from a bag large chess-men of mingled wood and silver. Two or
      three would have made an armful for a child. Standing each at his end they began to play. The
      game did not last long. No matter how carefully Dhoya played, each move went against him. At
      last, leaping back from the board he cried, “I have lost!” The two spirits were standing
      together at the entrance. Dhoya seized his spear, but slowly the figures began to fade, first
      a star and then the leaves showed through their forms. Soon all had vanished away.</p>
     <p>Then, realizing his loss, he threw himself on the ground,
      <pb n="193"/> and rolling hither and thither, roared like a wild beast. All night long he lay
      on the ground, and all the next day till nightfall. He had crumbled his staff unconsciously
      between his fingers into small pieces, and now, full of dull rage, arose and went forth
      westward. In a ravine of the northern mountain he came on the tracks of wild horses. Soon one
      passed him fearlessly, knowing nothing of man. The pointed end of his staff he still carried.
      He drove it deep in the flank, making a long wound, sending the horse rushing with short
      screams down the mountain. Other horses passed him one by one, driven southward by a cold wind
      laden with mist, arisen in the night-time. Towards the end of the ravine stood one black and
      huge, the leader of the herd. Dhoya leaped on his back with a loud cry that sent a raven
      circling from the neighbouring cliff, and the horse, after vainly seeking to throw him, rushed
      off
      <pb n="194"/> towards the north-west, over the heights of the mountains where the mists
      floated. The moon, clear sometimes of the flying clouds, from low down in the south-east, cast
      a pale and mutable light, making their shadow rise before them on the mists, as though they
      pursued some colossal demon, sombre on his black charger. Then leaving the heights they rushed
      wildly down that valley where, in far later times, Dermot hid in a deep cavern his Grania, and
      passed the stream where Muadhan, their savage servant, caught fish for them on a hook baited
      with a quicken berry. On over the plains, on northward, mile after mile, the wild gigantic
      horse leaping cliff and chasm in his terrible race; on until the mountains of what is now
      Donegal rose before them—over these among the clouds, driving rain blowing in their faces from
      the sea, Dhoya knowing not whither he went, or why he rode. On—the
      <pb n="195"/> stones loosened by the hoofs rumbling down into the valleys—till far in the
      distance he saw the sea, a thousand feet below him; then, fixing his eyes thereon, and using
      the spear-point as a goad, he roused his black horse into redoubled speed, and with a wild
      leap horse and rider plunged headlong into the Western Sea.</p>
     <p>Sometimes the cotters on the mountains of Donegal hear on windy nights a sudden sound of
      horses’ hoofs, and say to each other, “There goes Dhoya.” And at the same hour men say if any
      be abroad in the valleys they see a huge shadow rushing along the mountain.</p>
     <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
    </div>
   </div>
  </body>
 </text>
</TEI>